<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Monomer-and Polymer-Based N-Heterocyclic Carbene Coating of Transition Metal Core Nanocolloids</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-9388-3660</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Arabzadeh Nosratabad</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Neda</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nb2009002696">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Mattoussi</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Hedi</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/scgrant">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Grant</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Samuel C.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016013562">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Ma</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Biwu</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1980-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/strouse">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Strouse</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Geoffrey F.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kennemur">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kennemur</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Justin Glenn</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>The unique size-dependent optical and physical properties of inorganic nanocrystals such as those made of metals and semiconductors have generated an enormous interest in exploiting them to develop a variety of applications. Due to their unique features, they have also been integrated into a variety of applications, including biological sensing, imaging, optoelectronic devices, and as fluorescent probes in biology. Growth of these materials using either hydrophilic or hydrophobic conditions yields nanocolloids that are not readily compatible with biological systems, due to either the hydrophobic nature of the ligands or the labile properties of the coatings. The main focus of this dissertation is to design and synthesis a series of molecular scale and multidentate N-heterocyclic carbene (NHC)-based ligands and apply them for the surface functionalization various inorganic nanocrystals and render them water soluble. We also summarize coordination interactions of NHC moieties with the gold surfaces to get better understanding about nature of NHC-Au bond. In Chapter 1, we summarize some of the basic optical and physical properties of inorganic nanomaterials including, quantum dots (QDs), gold nanoparticles (AuNPs), and gold nanoclusters (AuNCs). We briefly describe the history of growth strategies for preparing high quality QDs, AuNPs, and AuNCs. We then provide an overview of the surface functionalization methods to assemble colloidally stable and biocompatible nanoparticles followed by introducing the N-heterocyclic carbene (NHC)-based ligands as a novel metal anchoring group and their application in modern surface chemistry. In Chapter 2, we will focus on the synthesis of hydrophobic oleylamine-coated gold nanoparticles (OLA-AuNPs) and the surface coordination with N-Heterocyclic Carbenes (NHCs) relying on ligand substitution strategy. We detail the synthesis and characterization of three distinct water-compatible NHC-based ligands: an amine-modified small molecule, a monomeric NHC appended with a short poly(ethylene glycol) (PEG) block, and a modified poly(isobutylene-alt-maleic anhydride), PIMA, that simultaneously presents multiple NHC groups and several short PEG chains. We find that rapid competitive ligation onto the AuNPs (often requiring several minutes of mixing) takes place regardless of the exact structure of the ligand. Furthermore, the long-term colloidal stability of the NHC-stabilized AuNPs have been tested after phase transfer to water, a highly challenging chemical venue for such groups due to their moisture sensitive nature. Our experimental data show that the multidentate NHC polymer coating exhibits the highest affinity to AuNPs, which manifests in long-term colloidal stability in buffer media, absence of any aggregation or degradation build up for at least one year of storage. In addition, the NHC-polymer-coated AuNPs exhibit long term resistance to competition from reducing small molecules such as dithiothreitol, DTT. In Chapter 3, we introduce a top-down etching strategy using poly (ethylene glycol)-appended-NHC (PEG-NHC) ligands to promote surface digestion of gold nanoparticles (AuNPs). We find that under long term incubation conditions using excess molar ratios of PEG-NHC ligands, with respect to AuNPs, progressive etching of Au surfaces takes place. This progressively alters the plasmon absorption features, yielding the formation of NHC-Au complexes. This top-down etching method has provided us insights about the nature and strength of coordination interactions of NHC groups with Au surfaces; these interactions are inherent controlled by the σ-donating nature (soft Lewis base) of NHC which match the soft acidic nature of Au surfaces, resulting in very strong coordination interactions and binding. We use UV-vis absorption measurements to monitor the transformation process, where loss of plasmonic features of AuNPs with time takes place. We further characterize the digestion kinetics by extracting a characteristic time which is found to depend among others on the ligand to AuNP molar excess. We then combine these data with 2-D 1H, 13C NMR spectroscopy, matrix assisted laser desorption/ionization (MALDI), and transmission electron microscopy measurements to identify the structure and chemical nature of the resulting NHC-PEG-Au complexes. In Chapter 4, we describe the formation of fluorescent blue emitting ultrasmall gold nanoclusters (Au NCs), following the digestion process described in Chapter 3 above, achieved under thermal treatment. This route offers an elegant way to produce stable and homogeneously dispersed AuNCs. Specifically, we show that heating of Au-NHC complexes triggers the formation of ultra-small gold nanoclusters that are fluorescent in the blue region of the optical spectrum upon UV excitation. Here, the starting non-fluorescent NHC-Au(I) complexes undergo aurophilic interactions (as is the tendency for gold(I) compounds) and form blue fluorescent small size nanoclusters. We carry out a thorough characterization of the nanoclusters using analytical techniques such as UV-vis absorption, fluorescence spectroscopy and high-resolution transmission electron microscopy. Among others, we find that these nanoclusters show the excitation maximum at 380 nm and the emission maximum at 460 nm. Transmission electron microscopic analysis shows that most of these particles are &lt;1 nm. In Chapter 5, we provide a summary of the work assembled in this dissertation focusing on coordination interactions of N-heterocyclic carbene (NHC)-based ligands with the inorganic nanocrystals, along with the future research directions that expand on the ligation of NHC ligands with other transition metal cores including iron, silver, and platinum nanoparticles and their potential applications.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 6, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Hedi Mattoussi, Professor Directing Dissertation; Samuel C. Grant, University Representative; Biwu Ma, Committee Member; Geoffrey S. Strouse, Committee Member; Justin G. Kennemur, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022986">
      <mods:topic>Chemistry</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082094">
      <mods:topic>Materials science</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002000242">
      <mods:topic>Nanoscience</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">ArabzadehNosratabad_fsu_0071E_17837</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
