<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Teacher Perceptions of Beginner-Level Piano Technique and Injury Prevention</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-8731-738X</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Archer</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Stephanie</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ddumlavwalla">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Dumlavwalla</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Diana Teresa</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2008117983">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Williams</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Heidi Louise</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2015017602">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Jones</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Evan Thomas</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dgspringer">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Springer</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">D. Gregory  (Douglas Gregory)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kvanweelden">
      <mods:namePart type="family">VanWeelden</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kimberly D.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Music</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Music</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Many studies have been conducted examining musicians' injuries and their prevention; however, most of this research focuses on the advanced pianist. Pedagogues and researchers agree that the early stages of piano study are crucial for developing proper habits regarding piano technique, and many believe that poor piano technique can be a factor in playing-related injury. An examination of piano teachers' perceptions and practices regarding beginner-level technique and injury prevention is necessary in order to further investigate and understand the causes and solutions to this medical phenomenon. The purpose of this mixed methods study was to investigate current perspectives and perceptions of pre-college piano teachers regarding teaching technique to the beginner-level student and the relationship those perspectives have with injury prevention. Several factors were examined including the extent these teachers' strategies reflected existing research concerning injury prevention and technique. Influences such as method books or prior education were also assessed to determine the root source of pedagogical choices. The researcher created a questionnaire that was distributed to pre-college piano teachers from across the United States. A total of 216 participants responded to the survey. The respondents answered questions regarding (I) demographic information; (II) teaching technique perspectives and practices; (III) method book information; and (IV) teaching injury prevention perspectives and practices. Both quantitative and qualitative data were collected. Results suggested that many teachers do believe the relationship between beginner-level technique instruction and injury prevention exists; however, the emphasis each participant places on certain techniques varies across demographic groups. When teachers were divided into groups according to their preferred method books, the order in which they introduced technical skills to students varied. Emphasis on various skills also differed when participants were organized into groups according to their personal experiences with playing-related musculoskeletal disorders. Other demographic groups such as the primary age group taught seemed to have little bearing on the responses. According to a pair of Pearson Correlation Coefficients, weak positive relationships were found to exist between the participants' awareness of injury prevention and their education level and between their awareness and their amount of teaching experience. A series of open-ended questions allowed for the participating teachers to describe their teaching philosophies and strategies in their own words. Many commented positively on the importance of teaching technique while others detailed tactics they used in teaching students. Some described strategies they used at various stages of learning. A few respondents even reported having no specific philosophies regarding the subject matter. These responses were also compared to existing research literature concerning piano technique. Many mentioned strategies that have been shown to benefit students in the injury prevention area include slow practice, warming up, and teaching students to avoid tension in their playing apparatus. While some stated that they often delay serious technical study until later in the student's playing career, many comments were made about prioritizing technique in order to prevent playing issues which many researchers have concluded as best practice for piano teachers. The prevalence of body awareness and technique methodology training was also surveyed. A majority (54.41%) of participants reported they had received some sort of training although that education varied from attending a local music teachers workshop to being certified in popular methods such as Alexander Technique or the Taubman Approach. Those who indicated more specific and detailed training often provided meticulous responses concerning their teaching philosophies. The researcher recommends for all beginner-level piano teachers to prioritize healthy piano technique with their students including using the parents of young students as a helpful resource to aid in the child's development. Teachers who feel inadequately prepared to aid students in this area should seek further education through workshops, books, conferences, and other opportunities to better equip themselves for teaching. This study provides the basis for more research to be conducted on beginner-level piano technique in order to assist in the prevention of future injuries and to promote healthy and fulfilling piano playing.  </mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the College of Music in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 10, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Beginner Piano Lessons, Injury Prevention, Piano Pedagogy, Piano Technique, Playing-Related Musculoskeletal Disorders</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Diana Dumlavwalla, Professor Directing Dissertation; Heidi Louise Williams, University Representative; Evan T. Jones, III, Committee Member; D. Gregory Springer, Committee Member; Kimberly VanWeelden, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85088796">
      <mods:topic>Music</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Instruction and study</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041021">
      <mods:topic>Education</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Study and teaching</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Archer_fsu_0071E_17813</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Music</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
