<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Developing New Routes Towards C-N Bond Formation via Electron Upconversion</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-1750-5526</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Elliott</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Quintin D.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="termsOfAddress">Jr.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016054557">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Alabugin</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Igor V.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Professor)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n84134993">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Locke</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Bruce R.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kennemur">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kennemur</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Justin Glenn</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007113222">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Zhu</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Lei</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1978-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (465 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>The work disclosed in this dissertation explores using two-center/three-electrons and electron upconversion in C-N bond formation. In particular, three areas will be discussed in detail: 1) computation exploration into intermolecular C-N bond formation between a methyl radical and various nitrogen nucleophiles; 2) DFT calculations are used to investigate electron upconversion in an intramolecular C-N bond formation between dimethyl malonitrile and anilines; 3) An intramolecular C(sp3)-H amidation which opens a new path to hydroxyisoindolines. Chapter One begins with a broad overview of N-heterocycles, their applications, and general approaches for constructing them. One approach, C-H activation, is expanded upon as a promising method for constructing and functionalizing N-heterocycles. Four general methods for C-H activation are introduced: 1) direct activation, 2) C-H activation with delayed C-N bond formation, 3) nitrogen assisted C-H activation, and 4) independent N-H/C-H activation. This final approach activates both the N-H and C-H bonds and transforms them into reactive intermediates. For instance, the formation of a radical and a (persistent) anion (typically C-radical and N-anion) can be used to productively form a three-electron bond. Due to the extra electron is "upconverted" and creates a species with a higher oxidation potential capable of being oxidized by a mild oxidant, such as molecular oxygen. Chapter Two further expands upon the concept of "electron upconversion" as a synthetic method for constructing C-N bonds. When the orbitals of the two centers mix two new orbitals are created, a bonding and anti-bonding orbital. When three electrons are used to make a bond two of those electrons will be stabilized in the bonding orbital and a single electron will be destabilized in an anti-bonding orbital. The result is a net stabilization of a single electron. Additionally, by moving a single electron from a non-bonding orbital to a higher energy anti-bonding orbital one transforms the reactant from a weaker reductant to a more potent reductant, allowing for a facile electron transfer. Chapter Three uses DFT calculations to probe the effects solvent polarity has on intermolecular three-electron bond formations as well as the ability to trap a methyl radical with a range of N-nucleophiles. Chapter Four explores if oxidation under basic conditions allows the formation of three-electron bonds (resulting in "upconverted" highly-reducing radical-anions). The benefit of this "upconversion" process is in the ability to use milder oxidants (e.g., O2) and to avoid high-energy intermediates. Comparison of the two- and three-electron pathways using quantum mechanical calculations reveals that not only does the absence of a strong oxidant shut down two-electron pathways in favor of a three-electron path but, paradoxically, weaker oxidants react faster with the upconverted reductants by avoiding the inverted Marcus region for electron transfer. Chapter Five presents An intramolecular C(sp3)-H amidation proceeds in the presence of t-BuOK, molecular oxygen, and DMF. This transformation is initiated by the deprotonation of an acidic N-H bond and selective radical activation of a benzylic C-H bond towards hydrogen atom transfer (HAT). Cyclization of this radical-anion intermediate en route to a two-centered/three-electron (2c,3e) C-N bond removes electron density from nitrogen. As this electronegative element resists such an "oxidation", making nitrogen more electron rich is key to overcoming this problem. Remarkably, this reaction also converts a weak reductant into much a stronger reductant. Such "reductant upconversion" allows mild oxidants like molecular oxygen to complete the first part of the cascade. In contrast, the second stage of NH/CH activation forms a highly stabilized radical-anion intermediate incapable of undergoing electron transfer to oxygen. Because the oxidation is unfavored, an alternative reaction path opens via coupling between the radical anion intermediate and either superoxide or hydroperoxide radical. The hydroperoxide intermediate transforms into the final hydroxyisoindoline products under basic conditions.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">November 2, 2022.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Igor Alabugin, Professor Directing Dissertation; Bruce Locke, University Representative; Justin Kennemur, Committee Member; Lei Zhu, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023022">
      <mods:topic>Chemistry, Organic</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Elliott_fsu_0071E_17552</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
