<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Generic Desires</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Genre, Agency, and the Potential for Change in the Research Article Composing Process of Newcomers</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-8394-6015</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hawkins</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Brendan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n98010396">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Graban</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Tarez Samra</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n90702801">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Sinke</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Suzanne M.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2015038714">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Lathan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Rhea Estelle</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1961-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2010050868">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Neal</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Michael R.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of English</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (203 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Rhetoric and Composition (R/C) practitioners have a variety of ways of enacting the object/motive (Russell, 1997) of the discipline: to study writers and writing. Differing approaches have been well documented in terms of pedagogical styles and their underlying philosophical assumptions (e.g., Berlin, 1982; Faigley, 1986; Berlin, 1988; Kopelson, 2003) or what "counts" as writing in the digital age (Yancey, 2004)—to name a few. Similarly, scholars have pointed out that the whole premise of "writers and writing" has and continues to support white ways of knowing and doing (e.g., Prendergast, 1998; Kynard, 2005; Kynard, 2013). Along with these scholars who contemplate the goals and objects of the discipline, recent Conference of College Composition and Communication calls for presentations (Lindquist, 2019; Hassel, 2020) suggest practitioners take a moment to (re)consider our values. This project offers another approach to answering the question disciplinary values examining how new R/C faculty navigate disciplinary values as they are instantiated in a specific genre, the academic research article (RA).The research article (RA) was chosen because it is an economically central feature of the tenure-track promotion process, as well as a pedagogically central feature of many writing programs' curricula. Furthermore, the RA is philosophically central as a site where knowledge is authorized, reinforcing what writers and what writing counts as publishable. Finally, the RA is culturally central within the discipline as a socializing feature. Writers who wish to publish RAs—and thus participate with this powerful text in the discipline—must contend with the RA's generic (genre) norms to produce a text that fits within the discipline's expectation of what a RA should do. These assertions of how the RA functions in academic spaces echo central tenets of rhetorical genre studies (RGS). RGS, my theoretical framework, acknowledges genres as socialactions (Miller, 1984) that help writers to perform the function of communities, disciplines, or activity systems (Bazerman, 2003) and, as such, are also socializing mechanisms for those communities (Bawarshi, 2003, p. 354). Therefore, writers' agency is located at the crux of social expectations and personal goals (e.g., Porter, 1986; Russell, 1997; Schryer et al, 2003). RGS also acknowledges that, given these features of genres, individuals are always navigating potentially competing (Russell, 1997) personal and disciplinary motives as they compose what Anis Bawarshi (2000) calls sites for the "articulation…and acquisition of desire" (p. 1-2). This study joins traditional ethnographic methods used in RGS and builds in additional research steps to locate not just texts and their social actions but also locate what might have been left behind, the "rhetorical silences" or strategic omissions (Randazzo, 2015). RGS research methods typically use ethnographic methods for researching in addition to a rhetorical reading of genres (Paré and Smart, 1994). To study genres as sites of desires, I employ a unique methodology in RGS to understand just what sort of desires composers navigate as they engage in the RA-composing process. I surveyed 72 recently graduated R/C faculty, collect documents constituting the "genre set" (Devitt, 1991; Bazerman, 2003) of their RA-composing process, and conduct interviews (Schryer, 2011; Randazzo, 2015) to locate not only what rhetorical moves made it to the final, published products, but also what rhetorical silences, repressions, and/or defenses they may have enacted. Studying "generic desires" helps describe the tensions between individual agency and community norms, but it also requires a different methodological approach to uncover just what desires writers negotiate and how, particularly the "repressions" and "defenses" writers may enact, which may not show up in a final draft (Bawarshi, 2000, p. 98). Bawarshi recognizes that writers exist in and across multiple communities and, similarly, even within a single community may occupy different social positions as writers take up different genres within the community (2000, p. 98). Generic desires are a potent concept for theorizing about genres, agency, and the potential for authors to impact community norms and values. My findings suggest that individuals navigate personal and professional desires along with the desires of the discipline—enacted through the genre and enforced by the journal review process—as they engage in the composing process. These desires shift along the process, demonstrating that articulating and acquiring genres is a mutable, not fixed process. Thus, my findings demonstrate in writers' own words how generic desire works and where the potential for disciplinary change through "knowledgeable resistance" (Powell, 2003) might exist in the RA-composing process.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of English in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 26, 2022.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">genre, rhetorical genre studies</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Tarez Samra Graban, Professor Directing Dissertation; Suzanne Sinke, University Representative; Rhea Lathan, Committee Member; Michael Neal, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113628">
      <mods:topic>Rhetoric</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Hawkins_fsu_0071E_17468</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>English</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
