<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Three Essays on Business-State Relations in Authoritarian Regimes</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-5429-4161</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hess</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Katelyn</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/qbeazer">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Beazer</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Quintin H.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/hkern">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kern</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Holger Lutz</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no95016942">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kantor</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Shawn Everett</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/adriscoll">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Driscoll</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Amanda M.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Political Science</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (99 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>This dissertation contains three essays that aim to better understand the topic of business-state relations in authoritarian regimes. To do this, I use various causal inference techniques and utilize Russia as my geographic focus. Below is an overview of each of the three essays. The first chapter examines whether some judges are more willing to rule in favor of the state than others during business disputes. While previous researchers have studied the court system in authoritarian regimes, very few have examined the factors that shape judges' decision-making, especially in the commercial realm. In this regard, I argue that public sector (e.g., the court bureaucracy, prosecutor's office, investigative services, or other government agencies) judges are more likely to rule in favor of the regime because they may have similar preferences to the autocrat or they may have career incentives because of their lack of employment options outside of the state. To test this hypothesis, I use original data from the Russian commercial courts on the career paths of judges and a sample of more than 200,000 court cases from the last decade. For my causal identification strategy, I exploit the random assignment of cases to judges, ensuring that there are no significant differences in case characteristics that could potentially impact judges' decisions. Ultimately, I found that public-sector judges are no more likely than private-sector judges to issue favorable rulings toward the state. The second chapter examines whether corruption scandals impact the value of politically connected firms. While extensive literature examines whether and how political connections affect firm value, no studies have examined whether corruption scandals influence this. To answer this question, I take advantage of the release of a widely viewed Russian documentary film about an alleged corruption scheme involving former Prime Minister Dmitry Medvedev and the anti-corruption protests that followed in March 2017. To estimate the impacts of these events, I use data on political connections to Medvedev and daily stock returns from the Moscow Stock Exchange. For my research design, I use an event study to gauge how investors reacted to these events. In addition, I use synthetic controls to control for any confounding factors. In the end, I found that investors did not respond to either the video or the protests. Finally, the third chapter explores whether economic sanctions impact the value of firms. While some scholars have examined how sanctions influence macroeconomic outcomes, such as trade or FDI, few have explored firm-level effects. To this end, I contend that investors would respond negatively to economic sanctions because they could cause firms to lose benefits, such as foreign direct investment, access to financing, and various goods and services. To test this hypothesis, I take advantage of the sanctions imposed on multiple Russian businesspeople and their firms for malign activity in April 2018. To estimate the relationship between sanctions and firm value, I utilize data on different firm-level covariates and daily returns from the Moscow Exchange. For my identification strategy, I use an event study to gauge how investors react to the sanctions. In addition, I use synthetic controls to control for any confounding events. Ultimately, I found that investors did not respond to the announcement about the imposition of sanctions against Russian firms or their leadership.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Political Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 28, 2022.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Quintin Hayes Beazer, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Holger Lutz Kern, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Shawn Kantor, University Representative; Amanda M. Driscoll, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104440">
      <mods:topic>Political science</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Hess_fsu_0071E_17313</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Political Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
