<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Analysis of the Challenges Faced by Novice Music Educators during Their Collegiate Education and Early in-Service Years</mods:title>
      <mods:nonSort>An</mods:nonSort>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-9042-2255</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">McAllister</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Daniel R.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="termsOfAddress">Jr.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2008036741">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kelly</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Steven N.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dgspringer">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Springer</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">D. Gregory  (Douglas Gregory)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kvanweelden">
      <mods:namePart type="family">VanWeelden</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kimberly D.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Music</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Music</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>The purpose of this study was to analyze the challenges faced by novice music educators during their collegiate education and early in-service years as professional educators. The specific research questions that guided this study included: (a) What are some common problematic themes experienced between novice music educators as they navigated the early years of teaching? (b) How prepared did participants feel when transitioning to the professional field, and what factors of their preservice education were most/least valued during the transition? (c) What skills or values (musical or non-musical) did participants contribute any of their self- proclaimed success to as a music educator? Additional research questions later asked during two interviews included: (d) What impact did the participants' mentor teachers have on their identities as novice music educators, specifically if their mentor teachers did not teach music? (e) What are three strongly held beliefs or teaching strategies participants felt were absolutely vital to transitioning to the professional field? (f) What have participants done to make their experiences as music educators more fulfilling, especially when dealing with COVID-19 restrictions and regulations? A literature review was completed to further explore this study's rationales and framework. The literature review outlined the issues that past and current pre-service educators and novice in-service educators have encountered during their collegiate educations and professional careers. In addition to these issues, the review of literature also defined and gave examples of the effects of teacher attrition and turnover. Specifically, the issues that have most heavily impacted early-career attrition and turnover were discussed. Additionally, novice music educators and their pre-service experiences were especially highlighted and discussed. Data from this study were collected from a web based survey that was distributed through convenience and snowball sampling and through the Florida Music Education Association's (FMEA) online mail-out. Due to the nature of these distribution strategies, a completion percentage was not calculated. Moreover, over the total number of participants that began the web based survey (N = 107), only approximately seventy-eight participants completed it in its entirety. Additionally, two interviews were completed to add a qualitative and exploratory perspective on the issues faced by pre-service students and novice in-service professionals. Data from the web based survey suggested that many issues such as poor administrative support, unruly student behavior, overwhelming professional duties, and other problematic themes cited in past literature are still pressing issues within the professional field. Additionally, almost half (47.78%) of the participants felt only somewhat prepared to enter the professional field and about a third (32.22%) of the participants were unsure if they were or felt they were not prepared to enter the professional field. Moreover, 60% of the participants cited they were concerned with how well they were performing their duties during their novice years of teaching, with 21% of the participants claiming they would likely leave the professional field before their fifth year of teaching. Fortunately, the participants had a lot of advice to offer in terms of coping strategies for success, both personally and successfully, as music educators. The interview portions, though short, offered valuable insights into the minds of two young music educators. While some of professional beliefs may differ slightly, the impact of their non-music teacher mentor during their early-career and identity development was the same. Non-music mentor teachers, though respected, do not hold the same value as seasoned music teachers do to young music educators. COVID-19 did not greatly impact either of these participants classrooms or day-to-day job duties. Overall, the issues faced by pre-service and in-service music educators seemed to have not changed drastically over the past several decades of modernization in the United States. While this thesis hoped to expand on past research and emphasize the troubles of the past and present, more should be done to alleviate the problems too many teachers face across the country. Otherwise, the current trends suggest that the staggering percentage of teachers already leaving the field may continue to rise, leaving even more vacancies in schools across the United States. Further results and implications are discussed within the paper.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the College of Music in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Music Education.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 3, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Attrition, In-service teachers, Preservice teachers, Turnover</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Steven N. Kelly, Professor Directing Thesis; D. Gregory Springer, Committee Member; Kimberly VanWeelden, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85088796">
      <mods:topic>Music</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Instruction and study</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">McAllisterJr_fsu_0071N_17880</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>MME, Master of Music Education</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Music</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
