<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-4.xsd"
           version="3.4">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Environmental Controls on Organic Carbon Productivity in the Midland Basin</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <namePart type="family">Bandy</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Terryl L. (Terryl Lynn)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jdowens">
      <namePart type="family">Owens</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jeremy D.</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Professor Directing Thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/sayoung2">
      <namePart type="family">Young</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Seth A.</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ywang4">
      <namePart type="family">Wang</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Yang</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Professor of Earth Ocean and Atmospheric Science)</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Earth, Ocean and Atmospheric Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (49 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >The Kasimovian (late Pennsylvanian) to early Roadian (middle Permian) is an interval of Earth history that experienced relatively stable climatic conditions highlighted by significant glaciation, which might represent an analog for current and future climate dynamics. The carbon isotope (δ13C) record during this interval is relatively stable with a few minor but relatively unexplored fluctuations of ~2‰, suggesting stable global OC burial even as peat and/or coal deposits declined at the end of the Permian. This suggests that carbon burial may have increased elsewhere, or changes in the inputs would be required to maintain a constant isotope record. One possibility is that marine OC burial increased to balance the waning peat and/or coal deposits. Enhanced marine OC productivity can possibly lead to increased burial, which would drive a global positive δ13C excursion. For example, the Midland Basin in Texas is characterized by significant Permian hydrocarbon source rocks, which may have affected the global carbon cycle and therefore isotope record. It is possible that there are other substantial marine sinks of OC during this time, but global distributions are not well-constrained. These deposits, however, may have been manifested as organic-rich black shale, or a small but widespread increase of OC globally, which could have accounted for the stability of the carbon isotope record. Resolving the potential mechanisms that may be driving local and global OC burial is imperative for understanding the Earth system feedbacks associated with ancient and potentially future climate perturbations. This research constrains local and potentially global marine redox conditions using a multi-geochemical proxy approach. Total OC contents and isotopes were analyzed to constrain local to global burial, respectively. Iron speciation and δ34Spyr were utilized to constrain local redox conditions – including local anoxic and euxinic (anoxic and sulfidic water-column) conditions and pyrite burial. Redox-sensitive trace metals were measured to interpret local conditions, which are best utilized in combination with Fe speciation, and under certain circumstances can help to decipher basin restriction or global trace metal drawdown due to widespread euxinia. Last, thallium isotopes have been analyzed on anoxic to euxinic samples to determine the global extent of oxic bottom waters and the basin’s connectivity to the open ocean. The combination of these traditional and novel geochemical redox proxies provide new context to interpret the local depositional environment of the Midland Basin. The collected results show that the black shales in the Midland Basin were deposited under low oxygen conditions and at a few points verging on euxinic. The data suggest that eustatic sea levels increased during sediment deposition. Associated with this sea level rise was an increase in bioessential nutrient availability (e.g., trace metals), which led to increased organic carbon drawdown and preservation within the basin.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Earth, Ocean and Atmospheric Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Science.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Spring Semester 2019.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 8, 2019.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jeremy Owens, Professor Directing Thesis; Seth Young, Committee Member; Yang Wang, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85054037">
      <topic>Geology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">2019_Spring_Bandy_fsu_0071N_15141</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Science</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2019-10-14T16:36:31.241-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
