<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-4.xsd"
           version="3.4">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Pedagogical Study of the Saxophone through the Lens of Acoustic Niche Hypothesis</title>
      <nonSort>A</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <namePart type="family">Childs</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Nicholas James</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2017135183">
      <namePart type="family">Deibel</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Geoffrey</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Professor Directing Treatise</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2008077068">
      <namePart type="family">Bish</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Deborah</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">1971-</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2002107071">
      <namePart type="family">Keesecker</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jeff</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2003072097">
      <namePart type="family">Von Glahn</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Denise</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">1950-</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">University Representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Music</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (78 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >The purpose of this document is to construct a pedagogical model for which we can better teach the adaptation and versatility of the saxophone within the musical world. In my experience, there seems to be an absence of discussion regarding the rich historical diversity of the instrument. When considering the development of the saxophone it is usually within the scope of a particular musical style, most often through the genres of classical music or jazz. By narrowing our scope to the field that we inhabit we leave out some of the most innovative and interesting approaches to the instrument, and concepts that could potentially be integrated into our own performance practices. Through an examination of how the instrument has adapted in response to technological, social and aesthetic changes we gain insight into the flexibility of the instrument and begin to dismantle barriers that often define “schools of playing.” By establishing the saxophone’s history of adaptation, I build an argument that there is no singular correct approach to sound, only a rich variety of choices. Soundscape ecologist Bernard Krause popularized the term “acoustic niche” which originated from his colleague Ruth Happel. Acoustic niche refers to the situation by which vocalizing creatures within a particular environment alter their frequencies to compensate for sonic changes to their territory caused by encroaching other species including humans. He states that examining, “the diversity and structure of natural sounds from a rainforest forcefully demonstrates very special relationships of many insects, birds, mammals, and amphibians to each other.” The adaptation of creatures’ vocalizations, rising and falling within certain frequency levels, is essential to their survival. Any “masking” or invasion by others threatens an individual’s ability to locate food sources, communicate danger signals and attract mates. In this context, acoustic niche theory becomes a useful metaphor for the development, adaptation, and trajectories of the saxophone in the instrumental world. Since its invention in the mid-nineteenth century, the saxophone has regularly adapted and altered its tonal profile to carve a place in a diverse spectrum of genres and musical styles. The opening chapter discusses the landscape of the saxophone community as a whole. This includes the genres of classical and jazz as well as niche communities such as Carnatic and popular musics. In this chapter I frame the issue of “specialization” and provide background material on acoustic niche theory. The second chapter seeks to complicate and enrich the saxophone’s historical narrative in order to demonstrate the logic of various communities existing within. The third chapter begins with a discussion of technological changes made to the instrument since its invention. The remainder of chapter three explores a variety of diverse tonal profiles that exist within general communities such as classical, jazz, popular and non-Western musics. The final chapter considers a practical application of these discussions and presents a sample pedagogical method.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Treatise submitted to the College of Music in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Music.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Spring Semester 2019.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 19, 2019.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Acoustic Niche, Historical Narrative, Pedagogy, Saxophone, Specialization, Tonal Profile</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Geoffrey Deibel, Professor Directing Treatise; Denise Von Glahn, University Representative; Deborah Bish, Committee Member; Jeffrey Keesecker, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041021">
      <topic>Education</topic>
      <topic>Study and teaching</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85088762">
      <topic>Music</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85088796">
      <topic>Music</topic>
      <topic>Instruction and study</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">2019_Spring_Childs_fsu_0071E_15184</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Music</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Music</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2019-10-14T16:36:31.241-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
