<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-4.xsd"
           version="3.4">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Elaborations of Classical-Model Sentences and Periods in Richard Strauss's Songs for Voice and Piano</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <namePart type="family">Tanis</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Joshua</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr94018466">
      <namePart type="family">Kraus</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Joseph Charles</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">1955-</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Professor Co-Directing Dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no98088565">
      <namePart type="family">Buchler</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michael Howard</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">1966-</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Professor Co-Directing Dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dfisher">
      <namePart type="family">Fisher</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Douglas L.</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">University Representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2003044981">
      <namePart type="family">Jones</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Evan Allan</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Music</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (188 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >In this dissertation, I address several ways in which Richard Strauss elaborates the Classical-model sentence and period paradigm: through harmonic elaborations by way of Strauss’s chromatic, Romantic-style harmonic palette; through formal elaborations by way of phrase expansion; or through elaborations of many musical parameters, which yield hybrid variants of sentences and periods. I offer labels for these hybrids based on their melodic-motivic, harmonic, and phrase-length profile: the Straussian Hybrid Sentence, the Straussian Hybrid Period, and the Lone Antecedent Phrase. These labels encapsulate a sense of their musical shape, showing how the resulting formal structures derive from familiar Classical models, but in some Strauss-specific ways. My methodology for analyzing Strauss’s songs takes on its own hybrid approach, which responds to Janet Schmalfeldt’s 1991 article on reconciling form-function theory with Schenkerian theory and analysis. It is often the case that where Strauss obfuscates normative Classical theme-types, he embeds the inherent unification of their formal structure in other ways, namely through voice leading and the melodic-motivic interplay between voice and piano. Accordingly, I present form overlays and voice-leading sketches for each song excerpt or full-song analysis. By so doing, I highlight how one kind of analysis informs the other, especially when one or the other type of analysis does not seem to fully account for a particular passage of music. To be sure, the form overlays and voice-leading sketches work in tandem with my analysis of poetic structure, meaning, and text-setting in each song. In Chapter 2, I investigate Classical-model sentences, sixteen-measure sentences, and Straussian hybrid sentences in excerpts from seven songs. Instances of Classical-model sentences and sixteen-measure sentences in Strauss’s songs adhere strictly to the melodic-motivic, harmonic, and phrase-length features described by William Caplin, such as in “Befreit,” Op. 39, No. 4, and “Ich trage meine Minne,” Op. 32, No. 1. In some cases, Strauss expands Classical-model sentences by various phrase-expansion techniques, such as in “Mohnblumen,” Op. 22, No. 2, and “Leises Lied,” Op. 39, No. 1. Yet in other songs, Strauss expresses elaborations of sentences whose melodic-motivic organization is noticeably different from the Classical model; specifically, these structures—which I label the Straussian Hybrid Sentence—exhibit a “presentation” phrase comprising a compound basic idea rather than a basic idea and its repetition (like Caplin’s Hybrid 3 model). I identify these structures in “Winternacht,” Op. 15, No. 2, “Wiegenliedchen,” Op. 49, No. 3, and “Allerseelen,” Op. 10, No. 8. In Chapter 3, I analyze examples of Classical-model periods, in addition to two related categories: the Straussian Hybrid Period and the Lone Antecedent Phrase. Straussian Hybrid Periods comprise a normative antecedent phrase (4-bar compound basic idea, ending with a weak cadence) followed by a hybrid consequent phrase that is guised as one of several possible formal outcomes, such as a sentence, a continuation phrase (like Caplin’s Hybrid 1 model), or a cadential unit (like Caplin’s Hybrid 2 model). In the case of any of these three options, the hybrid consequent phrase ends with a stronger cadence than the one at the end of the antecedent phrase. The final formal structure I address is the Lone Antecedent Phrase, which describes an antecedent phrase that is not followed by a consequent phrase, whether normative or hybrid. In these cases, it is difficult to speak of a “true” periodic design; rather, the first half of a perceived period is present, but there is no musical (or even rhetorical) completion of a complementary musical unit. In all, I survey six excerpts: “Für fünfzehn Pfennige,” Op. 36, No. 2, and “Ach weh unglückhaften Mann,” Op. 21, No. 4 (Classical-model periods); “Mit deinen blauen Augen,” Op. 56, No. 4, “Die Zeitlose,” Op. 10, No. 7, and “Schön sind, doch kalt die Himmelssterne,” Op. 19, No. 3 (Straussian Hybrid Periods); and “Das Bächlein,” Op. 88, No. 1 (Lone Antecedent Phrase). In Chapter 4, I provide three full-song analyses: “Zueignung,” Op. 10, No. 1, “Allerseelen,” and “Befreit.” Through analyses at multiple levels of formal and voice-leading structure, I highlight the inherent interaction between these two musical parameters, showing specifically how they relate to the poetry. In “Zueignung” and “Allerseelen,” there is a progression from obscurity to clarity that spans the duration of the song. Conversely, the poem from which “Befreit” is derived poses the opposite rhetorical effect—that is, “Befreit” traces a progression from clarity to obscurity. The analyses presented in Chapter 4 depict how Strauss’s use and elaboration of Classical theme-types is done so in the service of conveying poetic meaning over the span of an entire song.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the College of Music in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Spring Semester 2019.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 9, 2019.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Caplin, Form, Period, Schenker, Sentence, Strauss</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Joseph Kraus, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Michael Buchler, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Douglas Fisher, University Representative; Evan Allan Jones, Committee Member.</note>
   <identifier  type="IID">2019_Spring_Tanis_fsu_0071E_15125</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Music</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2019-10-14T16:36:31.241-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
