<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Technology-Enabled Citizen Participation</title>
      <subTitle>Equity and Effectiveness of Government Response</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-3244-9297</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Xu</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kewei</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n81065572">
      <namePart type="family">Berry</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Frances Stokes</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ttang4">
      <namePart type="family">Tang</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Tian</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2009109194">
      <namePart type="family">Ozguven</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Eren Erman</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2007031302">
      <namePart type="family">Yang</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kaifeng</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/aramaswami">
      <namePart type="family">Ramaswami</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Anuradha</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Reubin O' D. Askew School of Public Administration and Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (70 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>The technology-enabled citizen participation system has gained considerable attention for its ad­vantages in cost-saving, encouraging citizen involvement, and improving trust in government. In the era of smart technology and smart governance, emerging information communication technologies (ICTs), such as the Internet of things (IoT), and mobile apps can provide real-time and location-speciﬁc data that facilitate timely decisionmaking. With new technology tools, it is expected that government response to citizen coproduction requests will be greatly improved with better ability to obtain and process information. However, there is a lack of studies on how public oﬃcials use diﬀerent tools in implementation, and how to improve the eﬀectiveness and equity of governmental response to citizen requests. My dissertation serves the purpose of ﬁlling this intellectual gap. The ﬁrst chapter utilizes case-level 311 service requests data from 13 U.S. cities in 15 years, this study investigates the relationship between goal-setting and response time of service requests. Speciﬁcally, I ask two questions: (a) does having a case-level service target decrease response time of service requests? (b) does shorter target time decrease response time of service requests? I select 5 common service types across cities. In total, more than 4 million service requests are aggregated into 343 city-service observations. Utilizing case-level data, three measurements mean, median, 90th percentile are calculated and compared. The results conﬁrmed both of the hypotheses, that having a target decreases service response time, and among cities with service targets, a shorter target is associated with shorter response time. This study also explores issues in matching service types and choosing performance measurements. The second chapter investigates whether using technology-enabled coproduction aﬀects orga­nizational service delivery routine. I select the case of disaster recovery for the 2018 Hurricane Michael in the City of Tallahassee (Florida, U.S.). Interviews with city oﬃcials were conducted to guide the theoretical framework and provide insights on the results. I conduct Poisson regres­sion to investigate whether citizen requests aﬀect organizational service delivery time. The results show that although organizational routine and citizen requests do help reduce restoration time independently, there is no evidence indicating that citizen requests directly aﬀect organizational routine. The third chapter proposes an evidence-based and needs-based service delivery approach by using big data at the household level and machine learning techniques. This study uses 311 public service requests data to estimate the household-level needs for public services. I identify citizens' requesting behavior as a function of six factors: needs, awareness, accessibility, service condition, bystander eﬀect, and trust in government. Firstly, 5 types of machine learning model were trained using requesting behavior as the dependent variable and select the model with best performance. Secondly, I estimate household-level score of needs by setting other factors to an ideal scenario. I use survey data from 907 households and archival household-level data for 53,685 households in the City of Tallahassee (Florida) during 2018 Hurricane Michael to illustrate this method. The estimated score of needs was designed to reveal needs for services of those who do not utilize the citizen requests platform. The estimated score also shows a positive relationship with various socioeconomic indicators, which is consistent with previous studies on citizen request behavior. Our approach can help government decision makers better allocate resources based on ﬁne-scale analysis of needs, which echoes New Public Administration's call for equitable, proactive, client-central, and responsive decisionmaking.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Reubin O'D. Askew School of Public Administration and Policy in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 17, 2021.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Frances Stokes Berry, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Tian Tang, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Eren Erman Ozguven, University Representative; Kaifeng Yang, Committee Member; Anuradha Ramaswami, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85108741">
      <topic>Public policy</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85108611">
      <topic>Public administration</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2021_Summer_Xu_fsu_0071E_16392</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Public Administration and Policy</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-01-31T17:03:20.741646-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
