<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Exploration of Current and Potential Resources to Support Florida 4-H Volunteers</title>
      <nonSort>An</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-8148-2771</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Dillard</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Julie Pigott</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2003122703">
      <namePart type="family">Klein</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">James D.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jladams">
      <namePart type="family">Adams</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jonathan L.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2012011678">
      <namePart type="family">Dennen</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Vanessa P.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1970-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ajeong">
      <namePart type="family">Jeong</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Allan C.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Educational Psychology and Learning Systems</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (104 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>Volunteers are critical to the success of the Florida 4-H youth development program. They broaden the scope of county programs and increase program capacity beyond what a single 4-H faculty member could provide. Because of the reliance on volunteers to deliver positive youth development programming, the overall success of the organization could depend on the level of training and support volunteers receive (Arnold et al., 2009). Volunteer development is part of the overall volunteer management system aimed at preparing volunteers for their roles and responsibilities. Those on-going activities could include orientation, supervision, relaying policies and procedures, training, support, feedback, recognition, and continual management (Kyrwood, et al., 2016; Plesak, n.d.). While investing in volunteer development is expensive and time-consuming, it yields positive impacts related to the volunteer and within the organization (Manetti et al., 2015; Malinen &amp; Harju, 2016; Boone et al., 2013). Conversely, when organizations fail to provide effective volunteer leadership or volunteer investment, volunteer satisfaction decreases and volunteers leave resulting in organizational losses (Radhakrishna et al., 2011). Skills and competencies youth development volunteers should possess have been both researched and established in current literature. They include communication, organizational, subject matter, relational, leadership, technology, time management, facilitation, and teaching skills as well as policy and procedural knowledge and skills directly related to their volunteer roles (Culp et al., 2007; Kok et al., 2020). While there is empirical research on volunteer skills, competencies, motivations, and organizational benefits, research examining the specific resource needs of volunteers is scarce. Thus, how adults learn in the workplace holds implications for volunteer development. Activities like group participation, observing others, working through tasks, and working directly with clients as well as resources like documents, manuals, mentoring, and coaching could assist volunteers with fulfilling their roles and responsibilities (Eraut et al., 2004). In addition, job aids, check lists, videos, and resource sharing could provide further resources for supporting volunteers (Moore et al., 2019). The purpose of this research study was to explore what current resources Florida 4-H provides for its volunteers and to describe the beliefs related to volunteer support between the two stakeholder groups, Florida 4-H volunteers and Florida 4-H faculty members, and how those beliefs might differ between the two groups. Four research questions guided this study: • Research Question 1: What resources does Florida 4-H provide for its volunteers? • Research Question 2: What resources do Florida 4-H volunteers identify as helpful in fulfilling their roles and responsibilities? • Research Question 3: What resources do Florida 4-H faculty members identify as helpful for volunteers to successfully fulfill their roles and responsibilities? • Research Question 4: How do the beliefs of Florida 4-H volunteers and Florida 4-H faculty members differ as related to resources helpful in successfully fulfilling volunteer roles and responsibilities? The study consisted of an online questionnaire and follow-up interviews with both Florida 4-H volunteers and 4-H faculty members. Survey respondents included 229 volunteers and 32 faculty members. Follow-up interviews were conducted one-on-one with 10 volunteers and 10 faculty members. The results of this study indicated that volunteer resources should be delivered using a wide variety of methods that directly support volunteer work. Resources are particularly needed that support the 4-H club and youth project work. For example, both volunteers and faculty cited a need for training related to parliamentary procedures and resources like checklists and manuals to support running 4-H club meetings. In addition, study results indicated facilitating, improving, and supporting communication between 4-H volunteers and 4-H faculty and 4-H volunteers and Florida 4-H. For example, the Florida 4-H website was identified as lacking in functionality and overall organizational support to volunteers and faculty which directly affected youth and parent stakeholders. Findings from this study could help to establish a framework for resource development to support the Florida 4-H volunteer development program.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Psychology and Learning Systems in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Education.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">February 14, 2022.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">James D. Klein, Professor Directing Dissertation; Jonathan Adams, University Representative; Vanessa Dennen, Committee Member; Allan Jeong, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041141">
      <topic>Educational psychology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041146">
      <topic>Educational sociology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989">
      <topic>Education</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2022_Dillard_fsu_0071E_16949</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Education</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Psychology and Learning Systems</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-10-10T17:55:50.20129-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
