<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Childhood Maltreatment and Adult Romantic Relationship Outcomes</title>
      <subTitle>Social Support and Resilience as Protective Factors</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0004-4828-6922</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Bogart</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Stone M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lnjenkins">
      <namePart type="family">Jenkins</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lyndsay Nicole</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mradey">
      <namePart type="family">Radey</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Melissa</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n97051108">
      <namePart type="family">Osborn</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Debra S.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1968-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mswanbrowbecker">
      <namePart type="family">Becker</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Martin Swanbrow</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Educational Psychology and Learning Systems</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (191 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Childhood maltreatment is a pervasive and common occurrence within the United States, with an estimated 1/7 children experiencing child abuse or neglect per year (CDC, 2022) and 60% of adults reporting at least one traumatic event related to abuse or family dysfunction (CDC, 2010). A link between childhood maltreatment and negative mental health outcomes (e.g., depression, anxiety, PTSD, substance abuse) and physical health concerns (e.g., diabetes, heart disease, obesity) have been well established in the literature (Lang et al., 2020; Teicher et al., 2016). However, the pervasive impact of childhood maltreatment also expands to romantic relationship difficulties (Labella et al., 2018). While the connection between childhood maltreatment and poorer adult romantic relationship outcomes is well established in the literature (e.g., Cao et al., 2020; Friesen et al., 2010; Testa et al., 2005), identification of protective factors, such as social support and resilience, remains understudied. Protective factors are important to identify because not everyone with childhood maltreatment histories develop poorer romantic relationships in adulthood (Leonard &amp; Follette, 2002). Since social support (Gao et al., 2021b; Folger &amp; Wright, 2013) and resilience (Campbell-Sills et al., 2006; Edwards et al., 2014; Wingo et al., 2010) have been identified as general protective factors against childhood maltreatment, these were chosen to be examined within the context of childhood maltreatment and later adult romantic relationship outcomes. Literature examining social support's (Godbout et al., 2014; Liang et al., 2006; Nguyen et al., 2017) and resiliency's (Kimmes et al., 2018; Rellini et al., 2012) protective abilities for childhood maltreatment and adult romantic relationship outcomes is scarce. Therefore, the purpose of this study was to directly examine if social support and resilience had a moderation (i.e., protective) effect on the relationship between childhood maltreatment and adult romantic relationships. A secondary goal was to examine if these relationships differed by sex (i.e., male or female) as this was a major limitation within the cited literature (e.g., Campbell-Sills et al., 2006; Edwards et al., 2014; Liang et al., 2006). A sample of 203 adult participants"(ages 18 to 25 years old) were recruited from Amazon Mechanical Turk (Mturk). A correlational cross-sectional design was employed to investigate the following research questions: 1) Does current social support protect against childhood maltreatment's impact on adult romantic relationships outcomes while controlling for age, mental health, partner support, sex, and revictimization?, 2) Does current social support's protective ability differ depending on the source of support (i.e., family members vs friends) while controlling for age, mental health, partner support, sex, and revictimization?, 3) Does current social support protect against the negative impact of childhood maltreatment on adult romantic relationships outcomes to the same degree for men and women while controlling for age, mental health, partner support, and revictimization?, 4) Will current resiliency be protective against childhood maltreatment's impact on adult romantic relationships while controlling for age, mental health, partner support, sex, and revictimization?, and 5) Does current resiliency protect against the negative impact of childhood maltreatment on adult romantic relationships outcomes to the same degree for men and women while controlling for age, mental health, partner support, and revictimization? Measures included the Comprehensive Childhood Maltreatment Scale (CCMS; Higgins &amp; McCabe, 2001), The Adult Attachment Questionnaire (AAQ: Simpson et al., 1996), Short Form Health Survey—Emotional Wellbeing Subscale (SF-36; Ware &amp; Sherbourne, 1992), Dyadic Adjustment Scale (DAS; Spanier, 1976), Multidimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support (MSPSS; Zimet et al., 1988), Adult Resilience Measure-Revised (ARM-R; Jefferies et al., 2019), Revictimization Questionnaire, and a demographics questionnaire. Control variables within the analyses included age, sex, partner support, adult revictimization, and mental health. Data were analyzed using hierarchical linear regression modeling. Results from the analyses revealed that childhood maltreatment was a significant predictor of poorer adult romantic relationship outcomes. Total social support and friend social support were moderators within the total sample. When these relationships were examined by sex, no moderation effect was observed. Resilience was a protective factor within the total sample. When this was examined by sex, resilience was a protective factor only for women. Implications for theory, clinical practice, and future research are discussed.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Psychology and Learning Systems in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">September 20, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Childhood Maltreatment, Resilience, Romantic Relationship Outcomes, Social Support</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Lyndsay Jenkins, Professor Directing Dissertation; Melissa Radey, University Representative; Debra Osborn, Committee Member; Martin Swanbrow Becker, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85108459">
      <topic>Psychology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85083022">
      <topic>Medical sciences</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85123994">
      <topic>Social psychology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Bogart_fsu_0071E_18280</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Psychology and Learning Systems</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
