<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Longitudinal Bidirectional Associations between Parent Child Positive Relationships and Internalizing Problems in Middle Childhood</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0005-0428-0489</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Han</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Soojin</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2019122471">
      <namePart type="family">Wu</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Qiong</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Professor of human sciences)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ssiennick">
      <namePart type="family">Siennick</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sonja E.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lmcwey">
      <namePart type="family">McWey</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lenore M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jkimmes">
      <namePart type="family">Kimmes</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jonathan G. (Jonathan Gene)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Human Development and Family Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (92 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Middle childhood internalizing problems are prevalent and persistent, and parental factors play a significant role as both risk and protective factors for the issues. Guided by attachment theory and family systems framework, this longitudinal study examined the bidirectional associations among parental anxiety, parent-child positive relationships, and child internalizing problems across Grades 1, 3, and 5 (referred to as G1, G3, and G5 thereafter) among 683 resident biological dual parents and their child in NICHD Study of Early Child Care and Youth Development (SECCYD). Both mothers and fathers reported their own anxiety and depression symptoms at G1, and their perceived relationships with the child and the child's behavioral problems related to internalizing symptoms at G1, G3, and G5. Autoregressive cross-lagged panel models estimated the bidirectional relations between parent-child positive relationships and child internalizing problems, the mediation effects of parent-child positive relationships and child internalizing problems, and the different effects of mothers and fathers in these associations. A higher level of child internalizing problems at G1 predicted a lower level of mother-child positive relationships at G3. Maternal anxiety had a higher number of significant associations than paternal anxiety with parent-child positive relationships and child internalizing problems. Conversely, paternal depression, compared to maternal depression, had a higher number of significant effects on parent-child positive relationships and child internalizing problems. In addition, a multigroup path model by child sex was utilized to investigate the differences between boys and girls. For both boys and girls, a higher level of maternal anxiety at G1 predicted a lower level of mother-child positive relationships at G1 and G5, and a higher level of child internalizing problems at G5. Higher levels of paternal anxiety and depression at G1 were associated with a lower level of father-child positive relationships at G1. Higher levels of maternal and paternal depression at G1 were linked to a higher level of child internalizing problems at G1. A higher level of paternal depression at G1 was related to lower levels of father-child positive relationships at G3 and G5, and a higher level of child internalizing problems at G5. Furthermore, girls showed a more significant association between maternal depression at G1 and mother-child positive relationships at G1 than boys. For girls, but not boys, a higher level of child internalizing problems at G1 predicted a lower level of mother-daughter positive relationships at G3. Also, a higher level of maternal depression at G1 predicted a higher level of child internalizing problems at G3 only among girls but not boys. In contrast, for boys, but not girls, a higher level of mother-son positive relationships at G3 predicted a lower level of child internalizing problems at G5. This study integrated both attachment theory and family systems theory to investigate family processes. The findings underscore the importance of incorporating parental and child sex into the understanding of child outcomes during middle childhood. Implications for clinical interventions and future research are included. Keywords: child internalizing problems, parent-child relationships, intergenerational transmission, middle childhood, gender differences</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Human Development and Family Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 5, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">child internalizing problems, gender differences, intergenerational transmission, middle childhood, parent-child relationships</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Qiong Wu, Professor Directing Dissertation; Sonja E. Siennick, University Representative; Lenore M. McWey, Committee Member; Jonathan G. Kimmes, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85047028">
      <topic>Families</topic>
      <topic>Study and teaching</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Han_fsu_0071E_18780</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Family and Child Sciences</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
