<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Buying and Selling Foreign Aid</title>
      <subTitle>Donor Motivations and Public Perceptions of Foreign Aid</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-2587-8189</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Houser</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Zachary</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2023087575">
      <namePart type="family">Pietryka</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Matthew T.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2011009012">
      <namePart type="family">Ehrlich</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sean D.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/matolia">
      <namePart type="family">Atolia</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Manoj</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dhaim">
      <namePart type="family">Haim</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Dotan</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dhaim">
      <namePart type="family">Haim</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Dotan</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Political Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (101 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Chapter 1: How do states attain monetary status? States can attain monetary status by taking actions that promote the use of their currency. By linking diversification into its currency with policies that benefit the investing state, a reserve currency issuer can promote its currency even if the economic factors of the currency alone are insufficient to attract other nations to invest. Scholars have long studied the influence geopolitical and security considerations have on the rise and persistence of reserve currencies. However, security guarantees are not the only commodity reserve currency issuers can leverage to enhance their monetary status. I propose that foreign aid is an alternative tool that a reserve currency issuer can use to encourage states to invest in its currency. Using an instrumental variable, I demonstrate how China has used foreign aid to induce other nations to invest in the renminbi and thereby enhance its monetary status. My findings show that the probability that a country will adopt the renminbi as a reserve currency increases as the number of Chinese-financed aid projects the state receives increases. When a state's currency lacks the economic factors to achieve international reserve currency status, states can turn to foreign aid to buy monetary status. Chapter 2: What drives public support for foreign aid? Foreign aid is a crucial tool donor nations use to advance their interests at home and abroad. Therefore, to sell foreign assistance to the public, elites portray foreign aid programs as 1) a means to alleviate suffering in the recipient country (altruistic frame), 2) a tool to gain access to natural resources and help domestic industries at home (transactional frame), or 3) a way to enhance international status and prestige (status frame). Prior research has tested these frames in isolation and typically does not vary the type of aid being allocated or the regime type of the recipient country. Using an original pairwise conjoint experiment, this paper demonstrates how different frames impact attitudes toward different types of foreign assistance (humanitarian aid, military aid, and aid for economic development) going to democracies and non-democracies. My analysis shows that respondents are generally the most supportive of humanitarian aid, going to a democracy, that is framed as providing altruistic benefits to the recipient. However, conservatives and isolationists are more supportive of aid framed as providing the donor nation transactional benefits compared to aid framed as providing altruistic or status benefits. Chapter 3: How can elites frame foreign aid to increase public support for foreign aid spending? Using an original pre-post survey experiment, I test how different elite issue frames (transactional, altruistic, status) about the benefits of providing foreign aid impact public support for foreign aid spending. My analysis shows that framing foreign aid as providing transactional benefits to the U.S. and altruistic benefits to those in need increases support for foreign aid spending. In fact, on average, respondents go from wanting the U.S. to decrease foreign aid spending to increasing foreign aid spending after learning the transactional and altruistic benefits of providing foreign aid. Additionally, contrary to past findings, I find that framing foreign aid as providing transactional benefits to the U.S. increases support for foreign aid for both conservative (Republican) and liberal (Democrat) respondents.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Political Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">May 3, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Matthew Pietryka, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Sean Ehrlich, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Manoj Atolia, University Representative; Dotan Haim, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104440">
      <topic>Political science</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/h85067435">
      <topic>International relations</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Houser_fsu_0071E_18825</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Political Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
