<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Social Networks of an Inquiry-Oriented Linear Algebra Class and the Experiences of Women of Color within the Networks</title>
      <nonSort>The</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0004-8633-4868</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Kim</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Minah</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2011088772">
      <namePart type="family">Larson</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Christine (Christine J.)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kamy">
      <namePart type="family">Kim</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Amy C. H. (Amy Chan Hyung)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/aibourk">
      <namePart type="family">Ibourk</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Amal</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lperezfelkner">
      <namePart type="family">Perez-Felkner</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lara</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>School of Teacher Education</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (154 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >In postsecondary Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) education, equity issues regarding race and gender receive attention. On this attention, it is suggested to view from the sociopolitical perspective—mathematics is political, mathematics education is political, and equity is defined with the critical dimension of identity and power. Using the central tenets of the sociopolitical perspective and intersectionality, Black and Latina Women's counter-stories provide insights into systemic issues, but quantitative approaches remain challenges. On the other hand, it is discussed that active learning in STEM education is potentially equitable but not inherently. Thus, what mechanisms of active learning determine equity or inequity is essential. So, this study argues that social network analysis (SNA)—a quantitative approach to mapping social structures- is promising. Thus, this study utilized SNA to examine equity and zoom in on women of color's experiences considering social networks in an active learning classroom in undergraduate mathematics education. By adopting the two perspectives "social capital" and "identity" to interpret social networks, which are consistent with the sociopolitical perspective, this study investigates (1) the structures of social networks of students and how race and gender relate to the social networks, (2) the experiences of women of color, and (3) the relationships between social networks and the experiences of women of color experiences, in an inquiry-oriented linear algebra (IOLA) class. This study is a single case study of one IOLA classroom in a public Southeastern university. The primary data sources are (1) student nominations in required discussion board assignments to map classroom-wide social networks and (2) journals and individual interviews of women of color. SNA was used to visualize directed networks and to calculate measurements to find the relationships between student nominations and race and gender. Journals and interviews were analyzed through initial and axial coding. Then, the networks of women of color were tracked back and related to themes of journals and interviews. The results show that the social network has a statistically identical number of nominations between non-White and White students and men and women and a strong tendency of the same racial and gender groups to nominate each other. Also, the group of most influential students determined by centrality includes women of color disproportionally compared to the entire classroom representation. Additionally, the findings of journals and interviews by women of color describe socially affirmed experiences with female classmates in the IOLA setting class and uncomfortable experiences with men in STEM classes. The experiences related to race/ethnicity and general IOLA settings vary depending on the participants. This study implies the potential equitability of the IOLA class with intentional intervention to provide supportive and inclusive active learning experiences. Furthermore, potential additional labor for women of color and the interpretation of simultaneous solidarity and segregation that the IOLA setting classroom possesses are discussed. Lastly, this study suggests future research and practices of more active adoption of intersectionality and further investigation of equitable active STEM learning mechanisms.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the School of Teacher Education in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 6, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Christine Andrews-Larson, Professor Directing Dissertation; Amy Chan Hyung Kim, University Representative; Amal Ibourk, Committee Member; Lara Perez-Felkner, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082157">
      <topic>Mathematics</topic>
      <topic>Study and teaching</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Kim_fsu_0071E_18904</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Teacher Education</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
