<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Design, Architecture, and Function of Advanced Polypentenamers</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0000-5626-9912</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Leo</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Courtney M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kennemur">
      <namePart type="family">Kennemur</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Justin Glenn</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dhallinan">
      <namePart type="family">Hallinan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Daniel T.</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">Jr.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nb2002004599">
      <namePart type="family">Schlenoff</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Joseph B.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007113222">
      <namePart type="family">Zhu</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lei</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1978-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (145 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >This dissertation details the structure-property relationships of several advanced polypentenamers, a five-carbon backbone topology of the polyolefin family. Synthesizing precise, high molar mass, low dispersity polypentenamers was a challenging target until recently due to the low ring strain of cyclopentene (CP) and cross metathesis side reactions that occur during ring-opening metathesis polymerization (ROMP). The ROMP of pre-functionalized CP monomers presents a variety of precise, rubbery-like materials in the unsaturated form and linear polyethylene materials after hydrogenation. These functionalized polypentenamers can then undergo further post-polymerization reactions to produce advanced polymer architectures, such as bottlebrushes, or to modify existing functionalities. The variety of precise materials possible from ROMP of CP enrich our understanding of polymer structure-property relationships at the five-carbon topology, which is nearly impossible to replicate with other methods. Several advanced polypentenamer systems with well-defined structures were synthesized utilizing previously developed synthetic methods and the resulting materials properties of these polypentenamers were investigated. ROMP of bromoisobutyryl bromide (BIB) functionalized CP produced linear backbones, known as macroinitiators, from which, grafts were grown via atom transfer radical polymerization (ATRP) to afford bottlebrush (BB) polymers. A systematic library of these PCP-based BBs was prepared in order to study the onset on BB behavior as a function of increasing graft length in dilute solution. Another library of polynorbornene (PNB) BBs, with similar backbone length and sidechain length, was also prepared for direct property comparison to PCP BBs as a function of backbone flexibility. This study suggests that BB behavior begins with grafts as small as 4 repeat units long and provided a unique perspective compared to the typical PNB BB systems, which are the most prominently used type of backbone in literature. The sulfonation of hydrogenated poly(4-phenylcyclopentene) (p5Ph) was also investigated to further expand the diverse functionalization possible from polypentenamers. This was accomplished using acetyl sulfate, an underexplored method in literature, to generate sulfonated aromatic hydrocarbon polymers towards proton exchange membranes for clean energy devices. A library of sulfonated polymers with modulated levels of sulfonation was produced by using a consistent stoichiometric equivalents of reagents at varying reaction time. The resulting level of sulfonation was verified by several analytical and qualitative techniques that are commonly used in literature. This study provided a comprehensive investigation of the acetyl sulfate through a synthetic lens, which has been underexplored relative to other methods of sulfonation. Future material investigations will provide important structure-property relationships capable of improving the synthesis and design of fluorine-free polymer membranes. Finally, the synthesis of catechol-containing polypentenamers was investigated towards their potential use as underwater pressure sensitive adhesives (PSAs). Many ocean shellfish, such as sandcastle worms and mussels, use biological adhesives with high content of L-3,4-dihydroxyphenylalanine (DOPA) to bind themselves to rocks and other surfaces underwater. The ultimate goal of this project is to identify the influence of Tg on the adhesive strength of co- or terpolymers synthesized from CP derivatives. A small synthetic library was prepared and characterized in an effort to identify synthetic outcomes, copolymerization reproducibility, and resulting thermal properties of the copolymers towards better design of catechol-containing polypentenamers.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 21, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Polymers, ROMP, Structure-Property</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Justin G. Kennemur, Professor Directing Dissertation; Daniel Hallinan, University Representative; Joseph Schlenoff, Committee Member; Lei Zhu, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104660">
      <topic>Polymers</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022986">
      <topic>Chemistry</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023022">
      <topic>Chemistry, Organic</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Leo_fsu_0071E_18941</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
