<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Low Dimensional Metal Halide Perovskites and Hybrids for Light Emitting Diodes</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-5143-1690</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Liu</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">He</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016013562">
      <namePart type="family">Ma</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Biwu</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1980-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/sramakrishnan">
      <namePart type="family">Ramakrishnan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Subramanian</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/shatruk">
      <namePart type="family">Shatruk</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Mykhailo</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lnienhaus">
      <namePart type="family">Nienhaus</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lea</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (117 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Metal halide perovskites have emerged as highly promising materials for light emission, boasting several advantages over traditional light emitters. These include easy preparation, highly adjustable and pure emissions, as well as strong charge transport properties. One of the most rapidly developing areas of research in the use of metal halide structures is lead halide perovskites, the technology of lead halide perovskites as solution processable optical materials have improved significantly in the past five years for light emitting diode (LED) applications with the external quantum efficiency (EQE) of going from 0.1% to over 20%. While this is very impressive, one of the major issues that prevents the commercialization is that most perovskite and perovskite-like structures are only metastable under normal atmospheric conditions due to reactivity with water and oxygen. Achieving high stability for perovskites is notably effective through the creation of surface-passivated single crystalline nanocrystals with minimal defects. However, most perovskite nanocrystals developed to date have surface passivation by insulating organic ligands, resulting in inferior change transfer and energy level alignment in perovskites LEDs with low performance. Besides the instability, lead perovskite come with significant environmental and health issues impede future commercial applications. Hence, there is considerable interest in improving the stability and efficiency of perovskite LEDs and developing new class lead free materials and fabrication techniques to enhance their performance. In this thesis, chapters 2 and 3 are about to develop the high stability and efficiency of blue perovskite LEDs, and chapter 4 explores constructing efficient lead-free red perovskite-related LEDs. Stable blue LEDs based on CsPbBr3 nanoplatelets (NPLs) with surface passivation by a multifunctional organic sulfate was presented in chapter 2. We report a facile synthetic approach for the preparation of surface passivated CsPbBr3 nanoplatelets, by introducing an organic sulfate, 2,2-(ethylenedioxy) bis(ethylammonium) sulfate (EDBESO4), into CsPbBr3 NPL precursors. EDBESO4 can interact with CsPbBr3 through both EDBE2+ and SO42- to occupy Cs vacancies and bind uncoordinated lead atoms on the surface. The EDBESO4 treated CsPbBr3 NPLs are found to exhibit significantly improved stability as compared to pristine CsPbBr3 NPLs with capping ligands of oleylamine and oleic acid. With EDBESO4 treated CsPbBr3 NPLs as emitter, spectrally stable blue PeLEDs with an emission peak at 462 nm have been fabricated to exhibit EQEs of up to 1.77% and luminance of 691 cd m-2. This research project clearly shows the potential of using properly surface passivated perovskite NPLs as emitters for highly efficient and stable PeLEDs. Organic semiconducting ligands passivated CsPbBr3 NPLs for blue LEDs were presented in chapter 3. To fill the gap between CsPbBr3 NPLs blue emitter and high conductivity for enhanced blue LED performance, dual conducting organic ligands triphenyl(9-phenyl-9H-carbazol-3-yl) phosphonium sulfate and triphenyl(9-phenyl-9H-carbazol-3-yl) phosphonium bromide (TPPcarz2SO4 and TPPcarzBr) are meticulously designed for the passivation of CsPbBr3 NPLs. The processed CsPbBr3 NPLs films exhibit high luminescence efficiency and good stability with the passivation of TPPcarz2SO4 and TPPcarzBr. More importantly, TPPcarz2SO4 and TPPcarzBr, as energetically aligned conductive ligands, enables the improvement of charge mobility by orders of magnitude and avoids charge accumulation by balanced charge injection at the perovskite interface, therefore, breaking the key bottleneck of low efficiency and inferior stability of LED device based on 2D layered CsPbBr3. When employing the dual conductive organic ligands treated CsPbBr3 NPLs into LEDs, a maximum luminance and an EQE of 1511 cd m−2 and 4.15 % were achieved, respectively, which are the best values reported to date for pure blue LEDs based on CsPbBr3 NPLs. The meticulous design of conductive ligands in this work further pushes this bright class materials of blue CsPbBr3 NPLs toward practical device driven applications. Efficient red LEDs based on a zero-dimensional organic antimony halide hybrid was presented in chapter 4. We report a simple molecular engineering approach to addressing the issues of low conductivity and poor energy alignment in electrically driven LEDs based on zero-dimensional (0D) organic metal halide hybrids (OMHHs). A 0D OMHH TPPcarzSbBr4 was then synthesized for the first time, in which light emitting antimony bromide dimer anions (Sb2Br82-) are surrounded and isolated by TPPcarz+. Electrically driven LEDs with solution processed TPPcarzSbBr4 emitting layer exhibit a EQE of 5.12%, a peak luminance of 5957 cd m -2, and a current efficiency of 14.2 cd A-1, the best values reported to date for 0D OMHHs based electroluminescence devices. This work paves a new pathway to achieve desired functionalities in organic metal halide hybrids, which would guide the development of new generation hybrid materials for applications in optoelectronic devices.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 23, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Biwu Ma, Professor Directing Dissertation; Subramanian Ramakrishnan, University Representative; Mykhailo Shatruk, Committee Member; Lea Nienhaus, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022986">
      <topic>Chemistry</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Liu_fsu_0071E_18821</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
