<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Development of Assays for the Identification of Virulent Enterohemorrhagic Escherichia Coli Strains</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-8630-128X</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Velez</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Frank</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/psingh2">
      <namePart type="family">Singh</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Prashant</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kmjones2">
      <namePart type="family">Jones</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kathryn M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rnagpal">
      <namePart type="family">Nagpal</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ravinder</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/shennigar">
      <namePart type="family">Hennigar</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Stephen R.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jali">
      <namePart type="family">Ali</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jamel</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Health, Nutrition, and Food Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (110 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Escherichia coli (E. coli) is a diverse Gram-negative, rod-shaped, facultatively anaerobic, and non-sporing bacterium belonging to the family Enterobacteriaceae. Strains of E. coli can be found in the environment and the intestinal microflora of mammals. While many E. coli strains have developed an essential mutualism relationship in our colonized gastrointestinal tract, some have evolved with the ability to cause diarrheal disease in humans. Diarrheal disease-causing strains are categorized as intestinal pathogenic Escherichia coli (IPEC). IPEC can be further classified into five phenotypes: enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli (ETEC), enteroinvasive Escherichia coli (EIEC), enteropathogenic Escherichia coli (EPEC), enteroaggregative Escherichia coli (EAEC), Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli (STEC), and Enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli (EHEC).  While Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli (STEC) and enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli (EHEC) are interchangeably in scientific literature. However, based on the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO), STEC is defined as strains that harbor the stx gene that produces Shiga toxins but may not carry other virulent genes. Similarly, EHEC is defined as strains that harbor the stx and intimin (eae) genes (FAO, WHO, 2018). Strains that have both these genes are considered virulent, while strains that have only one or neither are considered potentially avirulent. Virulent strains with stx and eae are responsible for significant foodborne outbreaks, are a major foodborne pathogen implicated in red meat outbreaks, and are considered adulterants in beef products. On the contrary, potentially avirulent strains are not considered a significant concern for the red meat industry. Currently, MLG 5.03 is the standard method for the detection of virulent strains. However, this method suffers from high false-positive rates. The false-positive test results arise from this method as it uses separate primer pairs to detect stx and eae independently within a sample. The presence of multiple avirulent strains or other background genera that may also contain stx or eae found in meat samples result in the false detection of strain(s) containing both of these genes. The purpose of this study will be to initially standardize and validate four high-resolution melt (HRM) assays, followed by a conversation of these assays to industry-friendly hydrolysis probe (HP) assays for the differentiation of potentially virulent strains of EHEC serogroups belonging to O26, O103, O111, and O121. The designed primers and probes will target a conserved single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) located on the serogroup-specific fnl1, wbdK, wbtD, and vioA genes of O26, O111, O103, and O121, respectively. The assays will be validated using pure cultures strains from Canada, France, Switzerland, and the United States, laboratory-inoculated beef and spinach samples, laboratory fractionally inoculated ground beef samples, and DNA samples from the federal red meat surveillance program. This study will provide significant insight into the accurate identification of E. coli strains present in tested samples. The work will allow the food industry to continue preventing foodborne outbreaks while increasing the volume of raw food products brought to the market.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Health, Nutrition and Food Sciences in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 27, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Adulterants, Enterohemorrhagic Escherichia coli (EHEC), High-Resolution Melt, Real-time PCR, TaqMan, USDA</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Prashant Singh, Professor Directing Dissertation; Kathryn Jones, University Representative; Ravinder Nagpal, Committee Member; Stephen Hennigar, Committee Member; Jamel Ali, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086577">
      <topic>Molecular biology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">VELEZ_fsu_0071E_18605</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Nutrition, Food, and Exercise Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
