<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Obeah and Dancehall in Jamaica and Its Diasporas</title>
      <subTitle>Modes of Agency and Identity in Shapeshifting</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0008-6735-5275</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Walker</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">B. Zoe</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2011000513">
      <namePart type="family">Hellweg</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Joseph</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2003111440">
      <namePart type="family">Kavka</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Martin</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2014075955">
      <namePart type="family">McVicar</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michael J.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Religion</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (110 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >In this thesis, I seek to create a framework to understand how in Jamaica, colonial legacies persist in the contemporary period to reproduce a form of Afrophobia which conditions the demonization and villainization of Afro-Jamaican heritage traditions, and to chart how in the neo-colonial period, individuals in their formations of personhood, and efforts toward social mobility contend with such forms of Afrophobia. I map the genealogy of two of the most popular yet denigrated African derived practices in Jamaica, Obeah and Dancehall. Obeah is a set of ritual technologies often conflated with witchcraft which individuals employ to heal, perform divination, and to reach goals, and Dancehall is a Jamaican born music genre and subculture which is a central part of Jamaica's economic sector, providing employment for many of Jamaica's disenfranchised underemployed. Despite the significance and pervasiveness of these practices, religious communities along with Political and social elites disparage both Obeah and Dancehall, identifying them as low class, and attributing them as the demise of Jamaican society. In response to such demonization, individuals who strive to project an impression of respectability, hide that they participate in such practices, opting instead to embrace values coded as Christian, elite, moral, respectable, white, and European. Through so doing, individuals traverse poles between African-derived rituals, Africa, and Blackness, on one hand, and Christianity, Europe, and whiteness on the other. Persons therefore never exist with one static identity, but hold, and alternate between multiple identities to adopt to fluctuating, and unstable conditions in ways that enable them to socially climb, and escape marginalization. I refer to this process as "shapeshifting," the ability to appear as one thing then, at will transform into another. I identify shapeshifting as a form of embodiment, where in which individuals strategically alternate these often-opposing identities to maintain respectability. Christians for example, work Obeah despite claiming it goes against God and publicly condemning it, and many pastors allegedly hold vocations as Obeah specialist. Furthermore, individuals identify Jamaica's African inspired religions with Obeah, while practitioners deny such claims to seem more respectable, even while their practices mirror Obeah since they too are African derived. The spears of Obeah and Dancehall converge given that individuals have attributed the success of popular Dancehall artists to Obeah. Artists historically have not embraced such accusations, however, interestingly, a new generation of artists have begun to feature Obeah in their music, claiming it helps them gain success in extra-legal activities such as scamming. I highlight that this cultural expression provides social commentary on the state of poverty and underemployment in Jamaica which has made crime as the only avenue out of poverty for Jamaica's disenfranchised youth. Furthermore, I argue that artists who publicly endorse Obeah as a technology for social advancement despite its stigma are engaged in a form of decolonization. This paper draws on data gathered through archival research, social media analysis and multi-sited ethnography in south Florida, Queens New York and virtual platforms such as Zoom.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Religion in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Arts.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 24, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Joseph Hellweg, Professor Directing Thesis; Martin Kavka, Committee Member; Micheal J. McVicar, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85020279">
      <geographic>Caribbean Area</geographic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001534">
      <geographic>Africa</geographic>
      <topic>Civilization</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Walker_fsu_0071N_18950</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Arts</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Religion</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
