<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Investigating Nutrient Uptake and Plankton Community Composition</title>
      <subTitle>A Comparative Study between Regions of the Gulf of Mexico, Eastern Indian Ocean and Southern Ocean</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-6569-9540</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Yingling</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Natalia</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mstukel">
      <namePart type="family">Stukel</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michael R.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2010187986">
      <namePart type="family">Wulff</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Janie L.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/skranz">
      <namePart type="family">Kranz</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sven Alexander</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2006015588">
      <namePart type="family">Knapp</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Angela Noel</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1976-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2004084871">
      <namePart type="family">Mason</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Olivia Underwood</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (165 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Nutrient uptake dynamics, which are strongly influenced by plankton community composition, are an important aspect of pelagic food webs and biogeochemical cycles. For instance, in oligotrophic oceanic regions picoplankton dominate and have the ability to uptake nutrients even at low ambient concentrations, while in frontal mixing zones, complex nutrient co-limitation patterns and their interplay with light can alter plankton community structure over relatively small spatial scales. We begin this dissertation by investigating the oligotrophic Gulf of Mexico in Chapter 2, where we quantify primary productivity, nitrate and ammonium uptake rates throughout the water column. This chapter aims to determine the nitrogen sources that support this region, incorporating depth-resolved and diel sampling techniques. Our findings indicate that phytoplankton in the Gulf of Mexico rely heavily on regenerated production of ammonium to support primary production, characterized by low f-ratios and minimal diel variability in nitrate uptake, along with consistent high ammonium uptake throughout day and night. We applied a data assimilation method (Bayesian Markov Chain Monte Carlo) to constrain nutrient and light utilization dynamics by taxon-specific phytoplankton using our field measurements. The resulting parameters defined unique niches for Prochlorococcus, Synechococcus, diatoms, dinoflagellates, and prymnesiophytes. In Chapter 3, our study transitions to the oligotrophic Argo Basin in the eastern Indian Ocean, where we combine approaches used in Chapters 2 and investigate in-situ and shipboard incubations of primary production, nitrate and ammonium uptake coupled with carbon-based biomass estimates of pico-, nano- and microplankton in order to determine the depth-resolved nitrogen sources and dominant plankton groups that support this region. Our findings aligned with what was found in Chapter 2 in the Gulf of Mexico, where picoplankton, particularly Prochlorococcus and heterotrophic bacteria, were the biomass dominants. Primary production and phytoplankton specific growth rates declined with increasing depth (~4-fold to the deep chlorophyll max (DCM)), with no vertical pattern in biomass or particulate organic carbon (POC) with depth, suggesting light limitation likely plays a role at the DCM. Nutrient limitation is evident in this region with average peaks of nitrate uptake occurring at the DCM and ammonium uptake in the upper euphotic zone. High nutrient recycling, highlighted by a low f-ratio (0.004 to 0.21) and high ammonia uptake in the euphotic zone (15-fold higher than nitrate uptake) emphasizes the importance of nutrient recycling and the microbial loop in this region. In Chapter 4, our investigation moves to the Subtropical Convergence Front, a unique region in the Southern Ocean where subtropical and subantarctic waters converge to create a dynamic mixing zone that can support high plankton biomass and productivity. Here we use a combination of biomass estimation methods, including epifluorescence microscopy, flow cytometry and FlowCam, in order to determine depth-resolved variations in pico-, nano- and microplankton abundance and carbon based biomass in the euphotic zone, while examining vertical size-specific changes in carbon to chlorophyll a (C:Chla), this data allowed the quantification of the living to total carbon ratio. We find that subtropical-influenced waters were dominated by nanoplankton with low macronutrients and high Chla concentrations and offshore subantarctic-influenced waters had higher macronutrients and lower Chla with picoplankton dominated biomass in offshore regions, but microplankton-dominance in a coastal region. The subantarctic-influenced region had 2-fold higher C:Chla values due to a variety of environmental factors, including nutrient limitation and community structure. Significant primary production and rapid recycling by a strong microbial loop is evidenced by the living:total carbon ratio, which suggested that 67% of total particulate organic carbon in the euphotic zone of this region is attributed to live plankton and that non-living detritus comprises the remaining ~1/3. This dissertation highlights the critical understanding of nutrient uptake dynamics and carbon-based estimates of plankton groups in improving biogeochemical models for open-ocean ecosystems. Quantifying nutrient uptake is especially important in oligotrophic oceans that are vulnerable to a warming climate, as there will likely be an increase in stratification, which would reduce nutrient supplies from the subsurface to surface waters, hindering nutrient recycling and thus expanding oligotrophic regions throughout the oceans. Quantifying plankton community composition is equally essential, given plankton's significant role in driving marine photosynthesis, supporting marine food webs, and influencing ocean carbon uptake. The data presented in this dissertation offers valuable insights into the mechanisms and dynamics that drive marine pelagic food webs and biogeochemical cycles.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">May 30, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Ammonium Uptake, Community Composition, Nitrate Uptake, Pelagic Food Webs, Phytoplankton, Primary Production</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Michael R. Stukel, Professor Directing Dissertation; Jeanette Wulff, University Representative; Sven A. Kranz, Committee Member; Angela N. Knapp, Committee Member; Olivia Mason, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014203">
      <topic>Biology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Yingling_fsu_0071E_18996</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
