<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Science Teachers' Instructional Practices and Vision for Promoting Students' Intellectual Engagement in Science Classrooms</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0000-0518-875X</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Akcil Okan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ozlem</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2006073243">
      <namePart type="family">Southerland</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sherry A.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1962-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/akhurshid">
      <namePart type="family">Kurshid</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ayesha</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ljaber">
      <namePart type="family">Jaber</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lama</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/iwhitacre">
      <namePart type="family">Whitacre</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ian Michael</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>School of Teacher Education</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (235 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>Research in science education and current instructional reforms emphasize students' intellectual engagement in science classrooms as they use disciplinary ideas and practices to make sense of phenomena and solve problems. Reform-oriented science instruction that fosters such intellectual engagement for all students is possible. However, it is not yet prevalent in many science classrooms. To gain more insight into how to design and enact such science instruction supporting students' intellectual engagement, this dissertation study consists of an interrelated set of three investigations conducted in the context of a larger professional development project focused on promoting teachers' learning about and enacting reform-oriented science instruction. Each investigation builds on one other and contributes to the existing knowledge. The first investigation explores how teachers' instructional practices and features of classroom tasks work together to shape opportunities for students' intellectual engagement in science lessons. Specifically, we aimed to unpack instructional practices that can help to enhance students' engagement in rigorous intellectual work in science lessons and explore the consequences of these practices. Our data were drawn from the classrooms of science teachers who co-designed lessons promoting productive science talk. Working from recordings and work products from four different lessons for these teachers, we found that the potential demand on students' thinking was declined, maintained, or enhanced from what the lesson design afforded. Through a closer examination of instances of science instruction where placing a high demand on student thinking was a norm, we found that instructional practices associated with promoting students' engagement in rigorous intellectual work were consequential for promoting students' epistemic agency. Thus, we argue that maintaining and enhancing demand on students' intellectual work in cognitively demanding tasks creates opportunities for students to learn science-as-practice by acting as epistemic agents. The second and third investigations centered on understanding science teachers' instructional practices in relation to their instructional vision to gain insights into factors shaping science instruction. Through interviews and extended classroom observations, we examined the intersection between four teachers' instructional practices, instructional visions, and their student's engagement with a specific focus on either productive science talk or demand on students' thinking. Instruction promoting students' integration of science content and practices as they worked to figure out phenomena was observed in classrooms of teachers who had a sophisticated instructional vision of classroom tasks and the role of the teacher in instruction. In contrast, science instruction promoting students' intellectual work that involved isolated engagement in science practices or content was evident in the classrooms of teachers with a developing instructional vision. In addition, productive science talk was observed in the classrooms of teachers with a sophisticated instructional vision of classroom talk, while teachers with a developing instructional vision of productive talk struggled in facilitating such talk. Taken together with these findings, we argue that instructional vision can illuminate teachers' thinking about their work and exploring the intersection between teachers' instructional practice and vision can help to reveal teachers' understanding and reaction to reform efforts. Overall, the three investigations contribute to the field's understanding of teachers' instructional practices and vision of science instruction that can foster students' intellectual engagement. For professional development efforts that seek to develop teachers' capacity for reform-oriented instruction in science classrooms, this dissertation suggests concurrently attending the development of teachers' instructional practices and instruction vision.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of School Teacher Education in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 20, 2023.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">Cognitively Demanding Classroom Task, Demand on Students' Thinking, Instructional Vision, Productive Science Talk, Rigorous Science Instruction, Students' Epistemic Agency</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Sherry A. Southerland, Professor Directing Dissertation; Ayesha Khurshid, University Representative; Lama Z. Jaber, Committee Member; Ian Whitacre, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85118587">
      <topic>Science</topic>
      <topic>Study and teaching</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">AkcilOkan_fsu_0071E_17761</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Teacher Education</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
