<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Motion in Glass Formers</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0008-3470-677X</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Akkaoui</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Khalil</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nb2002004599">
      <namePart type="family">Schlenoff</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Joseph B.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/sramakrishnan">
      <namePart type="family">Ramakrishnan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Subramanian</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kennemur">
      <namePart type="family">Kennemur</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Justin Glenn</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016013562">
      <namePart type="family">Ma</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Biwu</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1980-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (236 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>The vast realm of glass forming materials (GF) encompasses a diverse range of substances from the versatile polymers to the renowned silicates. These materials possess the ability to transform into amorphous solids with no structural order at their glass transition temperature, Tg, which is usually preceded by a many-body cooperative relaxation process. The consensus on Tg is that while it mirrors some aspects of a thermodynamic phase transition, it is mainly defined by a timescale taken by the material to establish the equilibrium state (~ 100 s for example). Many polymers are often associated with the glass transition because of their amorphous structure as solids. When polymers are made to hold a charged group, the result is a polyelectrolyte, and when two polyelectrolytes of opposite charges are mixed in solution, the result is a polyelectrolyte complex (PEC). PECs are unique because unlike neutral polymers, they can be made to retain a significant amount of water. This makes PECs remarkably versatile due to their pliability, hence potential applicability. PECs can also help us bridge some fundamental gaps on the nature of relaxation in GFs since the dynamics of the smallest length scale (the cross-link here described to be a sticker bond between one Pol+ and one Pol- monomer segment) can be quantitatively studied. In this Dissertation, liquid-like PECs are probed to determine their key mechanical properties described by their viscoelastic response as a function of salt, temperature, and polymer chain size. Many characterization techniques such as, but not limited to, 1H-NMR, radiolabeling, ATR-FTIR and ionic conductivity were used to evaluate the stoichiometry and the environment of the PEC and its constituents. Light and neutron scattering techniques were utilized to determined molecular weights and size of statistical segments in our complexes. Ultimately, rheology was used to dissect the dynamics in PECs across different length scales and at various temperatures. A mechanism for structural relaxation is proposed wherein two dynamic units drive overall relaxation by a simple pair exchange. This is backed up with ionic conductivity measurements and an analytical expression which was successful in reproducing relaxation frequencies in not only PECs but also neutral polymers. Finally, microscopic "Aufbau" was used to build up a picture of unit motion in GFs, including but not limited to PECs, incorporating concepts that have provided a consistent thread of understanding over the last several decades. Such concepts pertain to an evolution a dynamic heterogeneity which cooperatively re-arranges. This is usually paralleled with a striking change in the material's properties such as viscosity, relaxation time, fractional free volume, and entropy. This picture describes the molecules or atoms in GFs as single units arranged in a disordered 3D structure. Correlated motion occurs among a minimum number of units, nmin, which ranges from 1 to 5 in an actual landscape of potential maxima and minima. The time taken for a GF to relax depends on the time it takes for an assortment of nmin units to relax throughout the material. At high temperatures (Arrhenius region), the motion of nmin units is not restricted to its nearest next neighbors. The time it takes for the GF to relax will only depend on an exponential term which describes a Boltzmann probability distribution of units as a function of temperature. Upon cooling, GFs lose free volume. Near Tg, in the supercooled region, neighboring units provide additional free volume for nmin units to relax. This introduces an extra probability term that recognizes the volume contribution to the overall relaxation. In recognition of the long-held belief that an equation describing glass dynamics in one material should be able to describe glass dynamics in all glass formers, wide variety of glassy materials, and materials with glassy response, were analyzed using literature data and tested the results against the analytical expression derived for relaxation frequencies in polymers.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 11, 2023.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">Glass transition, Polyelectrolyte complexes, Polymers, Relaxation time, Temperature, Viscosity</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Joseph B. Schlenoff, Professor Directing Dissertation; Subramanian Ramakrishnan, University Representative; Justin Kennemur, Committee Member; Biwu Ma, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022986">
      <topic>Chemistry</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Akkaoui_fsu_0071E_18268</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemical and Biomedical Engineering</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
