<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Processing of Ambiguous Relative Clauses in Early Spanish-English Bilingualism</title>
      <subTitle>Impacts of Language Mode and Individual Differences</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0009-3547-9676</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Anderson</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">James Matthew</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2015008326">
      <namePart type="family">Muntendam</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Antje</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="viaf"
         authorityURI="http://viaf.org/viaf/"
         valueURI="http://viaf.org/viaf/241126538">
      <namePart type="family">Kaschak</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michael P.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/gsunderm">
      <namePart type="family">Sunderman</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Gretchen L.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2006124985">
      <namePart type="family">Reglero</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lara</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Modern Languages and Linguistics</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (281 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>This dissertation studies the role of language activation on ambiguous relative clause attachment. Specifically, it explores attachment preferences of early Spanish-English bilinguals. Ambiguous relative clauses are syntactically ambiguous, as in (1):(1) Someone called [DP the [NP1 lawyer of [the [NP2 defendant]]]] that was by the elevator. The relative clause in (1) attaches to one of two possible constituents, NP1 or NP2. NP1 attachment is called high attachment because it is higher structurally; NP2 attachment is called low attachment. Languages exhibit distinct attachment preferences (Carreiras &amp; Clifton, 1999, Cuetos &amp; Mitchell, 1988, Grillo &amp; Costa, 2014, Mitchell &amp; Cuetos, 1991). Previous research on attachment focuses on unilingual contexts of language use. However, it is unclear how attachment preferences manifest when languages are proportionately active. Bilingual language activation fluctuates, and it is crucial to develop a comprehensive theoretical account of ambiguity processing to accurately understand bilingual sentence processing. As such, this project bridges this gap, examining relative clause attachment in three language modes (Grosjean, 1998): unilingual Spanish, unilingual English, and Spanish-English codeswitching, the use of multiple languages in the same dialogue. Codeswitching is practiced by several Spanish-English bilingual communities. Codeswithcing was operationalized by embedding ambiguous relative clauses into alternations, as in (2): (2) a. Someone called the lawyer of the defendant QUE ESTABA POR EL ASCENSOR. '...THAT WAS BY THE ELEVATOR." b. Alguien llamó al abogado del acusado THAT WAS BY THE ELEVATOR. xi 'Someone called the lawyer of the defendant...' Moreover, this dissertation examines effects of individual differences on attachment. This includes language dominance (Fernández, 2003), codeswitching use and exposure (Beatty- Martínez and Dussias, 2017), working memory (Kim &amp; Christianson, 2012), and cognitive control(Adler et al., 2020). As such, this project is interdisciplinary, considering sociolinguistic and cognitive variables. This dissertation touches on multiple theoretical perspectives. First, sociolinguistic variables such as codeswitching use and exposure test whether language experience shapes processing, predicted by the Linguistic Tuning Hypothesis (Mitchell &amp; Cuetos, 1991) and the Production-Distribution-Comprehension (PDC) model (Macdonald, 2013). Further, variation in working memory and cognitive control test relationships between processing and cognition described in the Sausage Machine Model (Frazier &amp; Fodor, 1978) and the Adaptability Control Hypothesis (Green &amp; Abutalebi, 2013). Finally, research on codeswitching effects predict distributional variation of linguistic structures between language modes on the grounds of convergence (Toribio, 2004), priming (Torres Cacoullos &amp; Travis, 2011), simplification (De Prada Pérez et al, 2021), or a combination (De Prada Pérez, 2018). This dissertation assesses if language mode effects extend to comprehension. Two experiments were conducted. First, in a pilot experiment, 23 Spanish-English codeswitching bilinguals completed three forced choice tasks, one for each language mode. Participants listened to sentences containing ambiguous relative clauses and answered a question prompting attachment. Also, participants completed The Bilingual Language Profile (BLP) (Birdsong et al., 2012) and portions of the Assessment of Code-Switching Experience Survey (ACSES) (Blackburn, 2013) to observe differences in language dominance, self-rated proficiency, and codeswitching use and exposure. Results revealed significant differences in attachment preference between unilingual Spanish and other language modes, but not between unilingual English and codeswitching. Moreover, increased Spanish proficiency strengthened language mode effects. In the primary experiment, a separate group of 36 U.S Spanish-English codeswitching bilinguals completed three visual-world eyetracking tasks, one per language mode. Participants listened to ambiguous relative clauses and looked at images of attachment options. Participants then answered a question prompting attachment. Participants completed the BLP and ACSES for language dominance and codeswitching use and exposure, formal measures of proficiency (the MELICET (English Language Institute, 2001) and DELE (Ministry of Education, Culture, and Sport of Spain, 2006) tests), a running span task (Bunting et al., 2006) for working memory, and an AX continuous performance task (Beatty-Martínez et al., 2020) for cognitive control. Results revealed the same language mode effects as the pilot on eye fixations and attachment preferences, but with different effects of individual differences. Specifically, effects of codeswitching exposure on language mode effects weakened with decreased cognitive control. Findings suggest early Spanish-English bilinguals demonstrate distinct processing and resolution of ambiguous relative clauses between unilingual modes, but in bilingual mode, patterns converge with unilingual English and diverge from unilingual Spanish. Moreover, effects of code-switching exposure and cognitive control support the ideas that language experience influences processing and code-switching exposure interacts with cognitive control. Finally, results reveal language mode effects on processing and resolution of ambiguous relative clauses, but may be attributed convergence, priming, or simplification, and more research is needed to make further distinctions.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Modern Languages and Linguistics in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 22, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Antje Muntendam, Professor Directing Dissertation; Michael Kaschak, University Representative; Gretchen Sunderman, Committee Member; Lara Reglero, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077222">
      <topic>Linguistics</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Anderson_fsu_0071E_18810</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Modern Languages and Linguistics</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
