<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Investigations into the Recruitment of Substrate Ambiguous Enzymes for Metabolic Innovation</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-8543-5833</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Campbell</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ryan P.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/bgmiller">
      <namePart type="family">Miller</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Brian G.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007113222">
      <namePart type="family">Zhu</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lei</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1978-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/wzhu">
      <namePart type="family">Zhu</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Wen</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mestroupe">
      <namePart type="family">Stroupe</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">M. Elizabeth (Margaret Elizabeth)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mroper">
      <namePart type="family">Roper</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michael Gabriel</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Program in Molecular Biophysics</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (229 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>Alterations in environmental conditions can selectively influence the evolutionary outcome of organisms. A striking example of this evolutionary response is metabolic innovation, where a change in an environment's chemical composition promotes the emergence of new metabolic pathways. Indeed, metabolic innovation encompasses many of today's most significant health-related issues, including antibiotic resistance or the bioremediation of anthropogenic toxins. The patchwork evolution model, by which genomic alterations recruit enzymes from existing metabolic pathways to perform new functions, is believed to be the predominant process facilitating metabolic innovation. Functional promiscuity is a distinguishing characteristic of the enzymes recruited for metabolic innovation, manifesting as either ambiguity in substrate recognition or promiscuity in chemical transformation. These promiscuous properties of modern enzymes fuel enzyme recruitment, composing a reservoir of hidden functions that can become beneficial during environmental change and subsequently be recruited for metabolic innovation. Despite recognizing that functional promiscuity is widespread in extant proteomes, what factors dictate the preferential recruitment of one functionally promiscuous enzyme over another candidate is unknown. Thus, it is currently impossible to accurately predict the trajectory of metabolic innovation. Model microorganism Escherichia coli contains four sugar kinases that are candidates for recruitment when the native glucokinase machinery is deleted — allokinase (AlsK), manno(fructo)kinase (Mak), N-acetylmannosamine kinase (NanK) and N-acetylglucosamine kinase (NagK). The catalytic efficiencies of these enzymes are 103 to 105-fold lower than native glucokinases, ranging from 2400 M-1 s-1 for the most active candidate, NagK, to 15 M-1 s-1 for the least active candidate, AlsK. Initially, to investigate the relationship between the catalytic activities of promiscuous enzymes and their recruitment, we performed adaptive evolution of a glucokinase-deficient E. coli strain to restore glycolytic metabolism. We observed preferential recruitment of NanK via a trajectory involving early mutations that facilitate glucose uptake and amplify nanK transcription, followed by nonsynonymous, active-site substitutions in NanK that enhance the enzyme's promiscuous glucokinase activity. These substitutions reduced the native activity of NanK. They also reduced organismal fitness during growth on an N-acetylated carbon source, indicating that enzyme recruitment comes at a cost for growth on other substrates. Notably, the two most active candidates, NagK and Mak, were not recruited, suggesting that catalytic activity alone does not dictate evolutionary outcomes. To determine if another candidate glucokinase besides NanK could restore glycolytic metabolism, we deleted nanK from the genome of the original glucokinase-deficient E. coli strain and repeated the same adaptive evolution experiments. Despite lacking the original preferred recruitment candidate of NanK, we observed a robust recovery of glycolytic metabolism that exceeded the fitness levels of the wild-type strain. Interestingly however, we did not observe the recruitment of any alternate glucokinase candidate besides NanK in these strains, suggesting that only NanK is the only latent glucokinase capable of being natively recruited in E. coli via an obvious mutational mechanism. Additionally, the addition of antibiotics as an additional environmental stressor only partially altered the recruitment trajectory of these strains, as while the identity of the observed mutations changes, their phenotypic impact remained the same. These results highlight our lack of knowledge regarding biological drivers of enzyme recruitment and emphasize the need for a systems-wide approach to identify factors facilitating or constraining this important adaptive process.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Molecular Biophysics in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 30, 2023.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Brian G. Miller, Professor Directing Dissertation; Lei Zhu, University Representative; Wen Zhu, Committee Member; Margaret Elizabeth Stroupe, Committee Member; Michael Gabriel Roper, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014253">
      <topic>Biophysics</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014171">
      <topic>Biochemistry</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086577">
      <topic>Molecular biology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Campbell_fsu_0071E_18126</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Molecular Biophysics</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
