<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Three-Dimensional Genome Organization of Mouse Nucleus Accumbens Medium Spiny Neurons in Cocaine Use Disorder</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-7305-2990</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Chitaman</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Javed Michael</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/feng">
      <namePart type="family">Feng</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jian</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2019055668">
      <namePart type="family">Orozco</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">David</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/marbeitman">
      <namePart type="family">Arbeitman</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michelle N. (Michelle Nina)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/pfraser">
      <namePart type="family">Fraser</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Peter H.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lyons">
      <namePart type="family">Lyons</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lisa C.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Biological Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (121 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>The mammalian genome is hierarchically organized within the nucleus to facilitate long-range interactions between promoters and cis-regulatory elements, such as enhancers, that govern cell type-specific gene expression. However, the role of three-dimensional (3D) chromatin structures in orchestrating transcriptional changes underlying substance use disorders is not fully understood. This dissertation investigates the 3D genome organization of mouse nucleus accumbens (NAc) medium spiny neurons (MSNs) and its implications for cocaine use disorder. In part, the lack of studies in this area of addiction research is due to limited 3D genome-wide profiling technologies suitable for use with animal studies in which low-abundance neuronal populations are being studied. To overcome this, I adapted available Hi-C and Promoter Capture Hi-C (PCHi-C) technologies to profile genome organization in FACS-isolated NAc D1 and D2 MSNs. I then integrated with neuronal subtype-specific ChIP-seq and RNA-seq to elucidate the relationship between genome topology and neuronal subtype-specific gene expression. Finally, these approaches were used to elucidate the 3D mechanisms involved in addiction-associated gene expression following chronic cocaine self-administration in mice. In Chapter 1, I introduce the significance of 3D genome organization in brain function, emphasizing the necessity of understanding higher-order chromatin structures to unravel the molecular mechanisms underlying addiction. This chapter reviews the existing literature on chromatin dynamics, enhancer—promoter interactions, and the methodologies for studying chromosome conformation, highlighting the importance of chromatin architecture in addiction biology and providing background for subsequent chapters. Chapter 2 details the adaptation of standard genome organization profiling methods for use with low neuronal input from adult mice. This chapter describes some of the technical challenges and optimizations required to achieve accurate cell type-specific genome organization maps from Hi-C and PCHi-C in mouse NAc MSNs isolated by fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS). In our study, the integration of PCHi-C and neuronal subtype-specific epigenomes enable multiscale profiling of hierarchical gene regulation, including super-enhancers involved in D1 MSN identity genes. Additionally, our analyses revealed distinct chromatin interaction profiles between D1 and D2 MSNs, underscoring the specialized regulatory landscapes of these neuronal subtypes. Notably, promoter interactions unique to D1 and D2 MSNs were identified, highlighting the importance of cell type-specific chromatin interactions in mediating neuronal functions and behaviors. In Chapter 3, I examine the effects of cocaine self-administration on 3D gene regulation in D1 MSN. This chapter discusses integrative analyses using Hi-C, PCHi-C, ATAC-seq, and RNA-seq data, demonstrating extensive chromatin remodeling and dysregulation of gene expression associated with aberrant chromatin architecture after chronic cocaine exposure. Specific enhancer—promoter interactions altered by chronic cocaine were identified, linking these changes to addiction-associated gene expression. Chronic cocaine exposure led to significant alterations in the 3D chromatin landscape, affecting the expression of key genes involved in synaptic plasticity and neuronal signaling pathways. Among these, Basp1 was identified as a promising candidate for future investigation due to its recent implication in cocaine action. This study also identified motifs for addiction-associated transcription factors as well as chromatin architectural proteins, which have yet to be studied in drug addiction. Chapter 4 summarizes the findings of the previous chapters, discussing their implications for understanding the etiology of cocaine use disorder. Additionally, I propose future avenues for drug addiction research, including the potential for therapeutic interventions targeting specific chromatin interactions identified in our study to mitigate addiction-related behaviors. This chapter also explores the broader implications of these findings for other neuropsychiatric disorders and highlights the potential for cross-disciplinary approaches to further our understanding of genome organization in brain function and disease. Overall, the results presented here offer novel insights into the 3D gene regulatory mechanisms that play a critical role in addiction-associated gene expression. By elucidating the mechanisms by which enhancer—promoter loops are remodeled during cocaine use, our results contribute to a comprehensive understanding of how chromatin architecture influences neuronal function and may provide insights for developing targeted interventions for substance use disorders in the future.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Biological Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Neuroscience.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 18, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jian Feng, Professor Directing Dissertation; David Orozco, University Representative; Michelle N. Arbeitman, Committee Member; Peter Fraser, Committee Member; Lisa C. Lyons, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91006099">
      <topic>Neurosciences</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086577">
      <topic>Molecular biology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00003585">
      <topic>Bioinformatics</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Chitaman_fsu_0071E_18889</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Biological Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
