<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Measuring Teacher Communication during Shared Reading with Children Who Have Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities and Limited Speech Abilities</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-6206-7268</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Collins</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sara Christine</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/abartonhulsey">
      <namePart type="family">Barton-Hulsey</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Andrea</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2009026723">
      <namePart type="family">Schatschneider</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Christopher</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mtherrien">
      <namePart type="family">Therrien</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michelle</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85213114">
      <namePart type="family">Wagner</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Richard K.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Communication and Information</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>School of Communication Science and Disorders</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (176 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>Children with intellectual and developmental disabilities (IDD) make up a heterogenous population with a range of support needs. Challenges in literacy acquisition are particularly common for children with IDD who also have limited speech ability, and may require augmentative and alternative communication (AAC). Shared storybook reading is an intervention approach used in naturalistic settings that supports literacy development in children with IDD. Previous studies have measured both adult and child communication during shared reading experiences, however, no study has used a measure of whole-group shared reading experiences adapted to document the integration of AAC instructional methods that align with a child's communication system, as well as strategies that support the child's engagement. This study examined teacher communication during whole-group shared reading activities that included children with IDD and limited speech. The study included four aims: (1) examine the reliability of the Systematic Assessment of Shared Book Reading (SABR) that had been adapted to document teachers' communication forms and strategies, in addition to functions, (2) describe teachers' communication forms, functions, and strategies using the adapted SABR assessment, (3) identify the relationships between teacher communication and child speech, language, vocabulary, and literacy abilities using both the original and adapted SABR assessment, and (4) describe teachers' perspectives on implementing literacy instruction that incorporates AAC through collaborative intervention alongside speech-language pathologists Fourteen preschool teachers and 14 children with IDD who used fewer than 20 spoken words were observed during whole-group shared reading activities. The study's aims were addressed using observational coding and survey procedures. Inter-rater reliability was obtained through computer an intraclass correlation alpha coefficient across 22 observed codes documented by two independent coders. Test-retest reliability was determined by computing correlations between final consensus codes documented in the first and second reading observations. Internal consistency was determined by computing Cronbach's alpha across four observed constructs. Descriptive statistics were used to depict the variability of teacher communication within this sample. Spearman rank-order correlations were used to determine the relationship between teacher communication and child abilities. Descriptive statistics were used to depict the range of perspectives of teachers on literacy instruction for children with IDD and limited speech. Results revealed high levels of inter-rater reliability and test-retest reliability across the majority of communication function and strategy codes, and all form codes that were observed. Acceptable to moderately high internal consistency was observed across all four observed constructs. While teachers communicated using a range of forms, functions, and strategies, there were no significant or strong relationships observed between teacher communication and child abilities. Moreover, there was no implementation of AAC strategies, or AAC forms beyond gesturing across all 28 shared reading observations. To address their literacy instruction, teachers reported they would engage in collaborative literacy instruction alongside an SLP and could easily implement evidence-based literacy instruction to support the reading development of children with IDD and limited speech ability if provided the resources in their school systems. Findings from this study suggest that an adapted measure of whole-group shared reading is a reliable method of comprehensively understanding teachers' communication with children with and without IDD and a range of speech ability. This study also provides information about the current support needs of teachers in order to successfully implement literacy instruction with students who have a range of abilities. Limitations and future directions are discussed.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the School of Communication Science and Disorders in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 20, 2023.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">assessment, augmentative and alternative communication, implementation science, literacy, preschool, shared book reading</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Andrea Barton-Hulsey, Professor Directing Dissertation; Christopher Schatschneider, University Representative; Michelle Therrien, Committee Member; Richard Wagner, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126455">
      <topic>Speech therapy</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Collins_fsu_0071E_18114</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Communication Science and Disorders</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
