<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Cardiomyopathies Bearing Pathogenic Variants Induce Maladaptive Response and Mechanosensing Effects in Cardiac Muscle Remodeling</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-9706-9319</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Coscarella</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Isabella Leite</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jpinto">
      <namePart type="family">Pinto</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jose R. (Jose Renato)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jirianto">
      <namePart type="family">Irianto</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jerome</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/pchase">
      <namePart type="family">Chase</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">P. Bryant</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/schelko">
      <namePart type="family">Chelko</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Stephen</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/clee">
      <namePart type="family">Lee</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Choogon</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Medicine</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Biomedical Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (159 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>As the leading cause of death worldwide, cardiovascular disease affects the lives of adults and children. Cardiomyopathies are a group of cardiovascular diseases that affect the heart muscle and are characterized by structural and functional abnormalities. There are several types of cardiomyopathies, including dilated cardiomyopathy, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy and arrhythmogenic cardiomyopathy, each with its own pathophysiology and clinical presentation. The clinical presentations vary by type and severity, but include shortness of breath, fatigue, chest pain, palpitations, leg swelling, heart failure, and sudden cardiac death. The etiology of cardiomyopathies can be multifactorial, including genetic predisposition in familial forms and acquired conditions such as infections, autoimmune reactions, toxins or systemic diseases. The pathology of cardiomyopathy involves alterations in muscle mechanics and promotes drastic changes in cardiac hemodynamics. The sarcomere, the mechanical unit of the heart, is frequently associated with pathogenic variants that play a crucial role in the pathophysiological development, leading to structural and functional abnormalities in the cardiomyocyte. Sarcomeric variants are often associated with dilated and hypertrophic cardiomyopathies, causing characteristic features such as dilation of the left ventricle and thickening of the left ventricular wall, respectively. On the other hand, desmosomal variants are commonly associated with arrhythmogenic cardiomyopathy and involve gene variants that encode proteins of the cardiac desmosome, a specialized cell junction that provides intracellular communication and structural integrity to cardiac tissue. In this dissertation, we will focus on specific variants that lead to cardiomyopathies and their maladaptive effects within the cardiomyocyte. The studies included in this dissertation aim to provide a broader view of the cardiomyopathy mechanics, and the cardio-protective effects associated with the pathology progression. In the first chapter, we summarize important points about cardiac mechanics and function to provide a detailed introduction to the following chapters. In Chapter Two, we discuss the mechanotransduction effects in the nuclear response to mechanical stress arising from defective sarcomeres carrying sarcomeric variants. Little is known about impaired contractility and nuclear stress, although nuclear mechanosensing is not new to the scientific community. Therefore, we show detailed connections between myofibril, cytoskeletal, and nuclear envelope proteins that are critical regulators of mechanical stimuli and demonstrate that nuclear remodeling is a critical aspect of the cellular response to altered mechanical forces in cardiomyocytes. In Chapter Three, we present novel findings on nuclear remodeling in cardiomyocytes bearing sarcomeric variants associated with hypertrophic and dilated cardiomyocytes. In this study, we show that impaired contractility modulates maladaptive behavior in nuclear morphology and stiffness. This study highlights the influence of nuclear remodeling, which may affect biological processes and signaling and contribute to the pathogenesis of cardiomyopathies. Understanding the interplay between mechanotransduction and nuclear remodeling in cardiomyocytes bearing sarcomeric variants is essential to elucidate the molecular mechanisms underlying disease progression and to identify potential therapeutic targets for intervention. By targeting these processes, it may be possible to modulate the cellular response to mechanical stress and mitigate the adverse effects of sarcomeric variants on cardiac function and structure. In Chapter Four, we study the nuclear changes in cardiomyocytes and discuss the potential functions of sarcomeric protein localization in the nucleus. Sarcomeric proteins are not usually found in the nuclear compartment, thus we suggest that they may have further roles in transport and regulation in cardiomyocytes. In Chapter Five, we provide important considerations for the current therapies for arrhythmogenic cardiomyopathy. We discuss the maladaptive effects of myocardial remodeling and identify a key modulator that is positively regulated during low to moderate exercise. In addition, living with a potentially life-threatening cardiac condition can cause anxiety, depression and emotional distress in individuals and their families, affecting their quality of life. Identifying a modulator that improves cardiac function in these individuals has significant implications for the development of better therapies. Finally, in Chapter Six, we integrate these studies by correlating the importance of a broader view of maladaptive effects on cardiac function and overall health. These conditions disrupt various biological processes critical to normal cardiac physiology. This collection of studies sheds light on understanding the maladaptive effects and biological processes affected in cardiomyopathies for the development of targeted therapeutic interventions aimed at improving outcomes and quality of life for affected individuals.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Biomedical Sciences in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">May 14, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">Cardiac Remodeling, Cardiomyocytes, Cardiomyopathy, Cardiovascular, hiPSC</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jose Renato Pinto, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Jerome Irianto, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Prescott Bryant Chase, University Representative; Stephen Chelko, Committee Member; Choogon Lee, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014203">
      <topic>Biology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85083064">
      <topic>Medicine</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014253">
      <topic>Biophysics</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Coscarella_fsu_0071E_18584</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
