<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Cortical-Hippocampal Interactions and Spatial Learning Are Impaired in Alzheimer's Disease and 40 Hz Stimulation Recovers Cognition</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-3730-8220</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Cushing</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Sarah D.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2012035962">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Wilber</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Aaron A. (Aaron Albert)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mhurdal">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hurdal</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Monica K.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rvincis">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Vincis</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Roberto</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/cmartin8">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Martin</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Christopher Basil</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/eckel">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Eckel</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Lisa A.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Psychology</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (141 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Spatial learning is impaired in humans with preclinical Alzheimer's disease (AD), and we've previously reported similar impairments in a mouse model of AD. Spatial navigation impairments are one of the earliest symptoms to appear in this disease, and could be the result of impairments in navigational computations, memory encoding or retrieval, or some combination of navigational and memory impairments. Both cortex and hippocampus are important for memory encoding and navigational computations, with interactions between these two regions supporting these processes. Memory reactivation during sleep is critical for learning related plasticity, and memory formation is correlated with hippocampal (HPC) sharp wave ripple (SWR) density, cortical delta waves (DWs), cortical spindles, and the temporal coupling of these events - postulated as physiological substrates for memory consolidation. Further, HPC-cortical dyscoordination is prevalent in individuals with AD. Thus, we hypothesized impaired memory formation mechanisms in HPC-cortical networks could account for spatial memory deficits. We assessed sleep architecture, SWR/DW dynamics and memory reactivation in a mouse model of tauopathy and amyloidosis (3xTg-AD) implanted with a recording array targeting parietal cortex (PC) and HPC. Mice underwent daily recording sessions of rest-task-rest while learning the spatial reorientation task. We assessed pattern reactivation by matching activity patterns from the approach to the unmarked reward zone to patterns during slow wave sleep (SWS). AD mice had more SWS, but reduced SWR and spindle density. The increased SWS compensated for reduced SWR and spindle density so there was no reduction in SWR or spindle number. In control mice hippocampal SWR-PC DW coupling was strengthened in post-task-sleep and was correlated with performance on the spatial reorientation task the following day. However, in AD mice SWR-DW and spindle-DW coupling were impaired. Thus, reduced SWR-DW coupling may cause impaired learning in AD and spindle-DW coupling during short rest-task-rest sessions may serve as a biomarker for early AD related changes in these brain dynamics. Previously, various forms of 40 Hz stimulation have been shown to clear AD pathology in mice and improve functional connectivity in preclinical AD patients. Thus, we assessed HPC-cortical coordination in 40 Hz or Sham stimulated 3xTg-AD/PVcre mice learning the spatial reorientation task. We implanted a 16-tetrode recording array targeting PC and HPC and an optical fiber targeting HPC. Daily recording sessions of rest-task-rest began as mice learned the VM, followed by HPC optogenetic stimulation, either 40 Hz or Sham. We assessed sleep quality metrics, DWs in cortex, and SWRs during SWS. Only 40 Hz stimulation increased 40 Hz power in HPC and to a lesser extent also PC. In SHAM stimulated mice SWR-DW cross-correlations were reduced, similar to 3xTg-AD mice. In 40 Hz stimulated mice, this phase-locking was rescued. Furthermore, the 40 Hz stimulation restored performance on the VM compared to Sham mice. However, this rescued HPC-cortical coupling no longer predicted performance as in NonTg animals. Instead, SWRs and DWs independently predicted performance in 40 Hz mice only. We also found reduction of amyloid beta (Aβ) in PC and ventral CA1, but no reduction in dorsal CA1, synaptically closer to stimulation. Thus, 40 Hz stimulation of HPC rescued learning and memory related functional interactions in the HPC-PC network during sleep and as a consequence rescued impairments in spatial navigation, despite a decoupling between HPC-cortical coupling and learning and memory. Furthermore, the observed effects seems to be mediated by direct 40 Hz impacts on brain dynamics (or another yet uncovered mechanism), due to an absence of robust glia, Aβ, and tau effects, contrasting previous reports. In addition to sleep, HPC-PC interactions are important in active navigation computations. In navigation, HPC is involved in creating a cognitive map-like representation of the environment. PC is involved in the translation of this cognitive representation based on body-centered location into the appropriate navigation decision. Thus, we tested the hypothesis that impaired HPC-cortical interactions during navigation underlie deficits in spatial navigation in a mouse model of AD. We decoded correct and incorrect trials from HPC and PC neural data on the spatial reorientation task. 3xTg-AD mice showed a different cross-region pattern compared to control, indicating that HPC-PC coordination impairments during active navigation may contribute spatial navigation deficits. Additionally, 3xTg-AD mice showed a shift in how the HPC mapped the spatial-reorientation-task, indicating underlying dysfunction in HPC may also contribute to spatial navigation deficits.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Psychology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 7, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Aaron A. Wilber, Professor Directing Dissertation; Monica Hurdal, University Representative; Roberto Vincis, Committee Member; Christopher Martin, Committee Member; Lisa Eckel, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91006099">
      <mods:topic>Neurosciences</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014203">
      <mods:topic>Biology</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002201">
      <mods:topic>Aging</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Cushing_fsu_0071E_18568</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Psychology</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
