<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Investigating Biological Carbon Pump Variability and Functionality</title>
      <subTitle>The Application of Old and New Conceptual Frameworks across Spatial and Temporal Scales</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-9648-086X</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Forrer</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Heather Jean</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mstukel">
      <namePart type="family">Stukel</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michael R.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016068194">
      <namePart type="family">Spencer</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Robert G. M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2006073243">
      <namePart type="family">Southerland</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sherry A.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1962-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n89605460">
      <namePart type="family">Chanton</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jeffrey P.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/sarah.fawcett">
      <namePart type="family">Fawcett</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sarah E.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/skranz">
      <namePart type="family">Kranz</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sven Alexander</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (163 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>The ocean is a central cog in the global carbon cycle, playing a major role in regulating the Earth's climate. A prominent mechanism driving uptake and sequestration of carbon is the "biological carbon pump" (BCP). Driven by newly sinking particulate organic matter (POM), the BCP sequesters atmospheric CO2 to the deep ocean via the transport of photosynthetically-fixed organic carbon from the euphotic zone (EZ) to depth. While there are multiple recognized controls on the BCP including the EZ biogeochemical environment (e.g., nutrient source and availability, temperature etc.), and food-web structure (e.g., zooplankton abundance), large uncertainties of the BCP magnitude remain due to sparse sampling and poor constraints on the mesopelagic remineralization rate. We apply two approaches to constrain BCP variability and functionality across spatial and temporal scales, including the implementation of the nitrogen (N) isotope (δ15N) mass balance approach to estimate the contribution of N2 fixation to export production in the understudied western tropical South Pacific (WTSP), and the introduction of a new conceptual framework, the molecular-level 'diagenetic clock', that relates molecular stability patterns of sinking POM to bulk flux metrics. Using geochemically-derived δ15N budgets, we quantified rates of N2 fixation, a new N source, and its importance for supporting export production in the WTSP, where shallow hydrothermal iron sources support EZ primary productivity. Results from the δ15N budgets yield high N2 fixation rates (up to 638 µmol N m-2 d-1) at stations impacted by hydrothermal activity, supporting the majority (64 to 92%) of export production in late spring. These results are consistent with contemporaneous 15N2 fixation rate estimates and molecular work describing high Trichodesmium spp. abundances associated with elevated N2 fixation rates. Further, the δ15N of sinking particulates collected over an annual cycle revealed temporally distinct N sources supporting export. This large N2 fixation-supported export flux describes the WTSP as a region of elevated carbon export, at least in the late spring, describing a more efficient BCP. Further, this sinking flux of reduced isotopic composition (~ -1‰) can have large implications for South Pacific basin-scale N mass balances. Further, we introduce a new conceptual framework, the molecular-level 'diagenetic clock', from a novel dataset of the molecular composition of sinking POM across dominant marine biogeochemical environments (i.e., nutrient-poor oligotrophic and nutrient-rich upwelling sites). We find distinct and inverse associations in molecular-level N-content and organic matter stability (the 'Island of Stability' formulae, IOS) across a productivity gradient from coastal upwelling to oligotrophic conditions. This is evident in the elevated N-content and low IOS relative abundance (%RA) observed at the coastal upwelling site that persisted to depths &gt;400 m, describing a fast flux of very 'fresh' organic matter in this region. Further, the strong particulate flux-IOS correlation (R2 = 0.91 and p &lt;0.001), describes an emergent, ubiquitous pattern of epi- and mesopelagic diagenesis across productivity regimes and depths. These findings highlight that although sinking speeds and EZ microbial diagenetic length scales vary across biogeochemical regions, the general trajectory of organic matter towards increased stability underpins a global ocean molecular signature of sinking POM and describes an emergent framework to assess BCP functionality through particle stability gradients across trophic regimes. We then applied the diagenetic clock to a Southern Ocean dataset, spatially across the Subtropical Convergence Zone and temporally in the Antarctic Zone (AZ) summer, where unique food-web structures and nutrient cycling regimes were observed. The Southern Ocean samples conformed with the molecular-level diagenetic clock, and we observed a strong flux-IOS correlation (R2 = 0.68 and p &lt;0.001). However, the range of IOS %RA largely aligned with temporal and spatial changes in primary productivity and associated primary processing (i.e., krill versus salp grazing and fecal pellet production). Notably, at the Subtropical Convergence Zone where a salp-dominant food web structure was observed, unique bioavailable molecular signatures (N- and sulphur (S)-enrichment) worked to reduce the IOS-flux gradient. While in the krill-dominant food web structure of the AZ, a strong bioavailable to stable gradient with regards to IOS and heteroatom %RA, was observed over the temporal summer. Although the degree to which fecal pellets drive IOS signatures remains unclear, we postulate that the different grazing and digestive mechanisms employed by krill and salps may cause distinct fecal pellet IOS signatures, potentially explaining the observed variability between the two regions. These findings in this dissertation have clear implications for our understanding of marine carbon sequestration, specifically constraining export production in an understudied region and offering new insights into microbes' roles in altering mesopelagic flux attenuation, largely determining relative remineralization length scales and thus carbon sequestration duration.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Earth, Ocean and Atmospheric Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 24, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">biological carbon pump, carbon export, molecular-level composition, nitrogen budget</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Michael R. Stukel, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Robert G. M. Spencer, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Sherry A. Southerland, University Representative; Jeffrey P. Chanton, Committee Member; Sarah E. Fawcett, Committee Member; Sven A. Kranz, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022928">
      <topic>Chemical oceanography</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Forrer_fsu_0071E_18930</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
