<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Sexual Selection, Population Structure, and Gene Flow in the Trinidadian Guppy (Poecilia Reticulata)</title>
      <subTitle>Insights for the Conservation of Genetic Variation</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-2651-7396</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Guerrera</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Alexa G.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kahughes">
      <namePart type="family">Hughes</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kimberly A.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1960-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/marbeitman">
      <namePart type="family">Arbeitman</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michelle N. (Michelle Nina)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86861195">
      <namePart type="family">Travis</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Joseph</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1953-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/eduval">
      <namePart type="family">DuVal</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Emily H.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/eduval">
      <namePart type="family">Duval</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Emily</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/sburgess">
      <namePart type="family">Burgess</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Scott C.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Biological Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (164 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>The diversity of life has fascinated evolutionary biologists since the conception of the field. Particularly captivating is the paradox of phenotypic variation found within a species: trait variation is required for adaptation, yet adaptation can erode this variation over time. While processes such as gene flow, mutation, and balancing selection can maintain genetic variation, quantifying how each of these processes proceed in natural populations remains poorly understood. Negative frequency-dependent selection in which rare phenotypes benefit from fitness advantages compared to common phenotypes has been implicated in the maintenance of several discrete polymorphisms in the wild. However, many ecologically significant traits are quantitative and the ecological mechanisms maintaining these polymorphisms are challenging to identify. One well-known example of a highly polymorphic trait is the color pattern of male Trinidadian guppies (Poecilia reticualta). Substantial evidence implicates female preference for rare or unfamiliar color patterns in the maintenance of color pattern variation. Yet, complex, highly polygenic traits, such as color pattern, can be subject to different selective pressures and warrants further exploration. One process that may promote or inhibit the maintenance of color pattern variation in guppies is male-male competition. When males compete more strongly toward phenotypically similar males, this should lead to a mating advantage for rare male types. This form of male-biased aggression can have profound effects on the maintenance of variation in sexually selected traits. In Chapter 2 of my dissertation, I explicitly tested whether male competitive behavior operates in negative frequency-dependent manner. Using three phenotypically distinct genetic lines, I asked whether males compete more strongly with similar competitor males compared to dissimilar. I found males were almost twice as likely to compete with dissimilar rivals and females prefer less competitive males. These findings suggest male competitive behaviors should promote positive frequency-dependent selection, and potentially oppose negative frequency-dependent selection imposed by female mate choice. In addition to various selective forces simultaneously operating in nature, different evolutionary forces affect trait variation. For example, varying rates of gene flow among patchy environments can affect the fate of alleles and their maintenance in the population. How gene flow is affected in systems that exhibit negative frequency-dependent selection is not clear. In Chapter 3 of my dissertation, I assessed whether male color pattern rarity contributed to the genetic rescue of small, inbred guppy populations. Using data from a long-term mark-recapture experiment in which genetically divergent individuals migrated into small recipient populations, I found color pattern rarity enhanced the reproductive and mating success of males with intermediate hybrid indices. Results from this project provide important insight into the potential selective process that contributed to hybrid vigor. In Chapter 4, I identified a potential behavioral mechanism responsible for gene flow within natural guppy populations. I explicitly tested whether immigrant males with unfamiliar color patterns benefited from increased female preference and evasion of male-male competition. I found immigrant males with unfamiliar color patterns were indeed more preferred by females and were subject to less competition than resident males. I also found color patterns tend to diverge among pools along increased geographic distances. Thus, dispersal and negative frequency-dependent selection likely promote gene flow and aid in the maintenance of genetic variation within populations. Whether male-male competition and female mate choice act in concordance with one another to select for the same trait, work in opposition by selecting for different extremes of the same trait, or act on different traits entirely can be informative for sexual selection results in complex and exaggerated male secondary sexual traits. In Chapter 5, I asked whether male-male competition and female mate choice act on the same male traits in guppies. I found evidence that males rely on different elements of guppy color pattern (increased black coloration and decreased orange) for initiating and winning competitive outcomes than what is preferred by females. These results substantiate my finding in Chapter 2 that males are more likely to compete with dissimilar rivals and provide a potential reason for why: males seem to be more successful when they exhibit greater phenotypic differences with their competitor. The proximate mechanism for such a competitive decision remains unknown. In conclusion, my dissertation characterizes the role male-male competition plays in maintenance of color pattern variation in guppies and suggest the two modes of sexual selection may be at odds. I also provide evidence that negative frequency-dependent selection likely contributed to the genetic rescue of small, inbred guppy populations and identified behavioral mechanisms that should promote gene flow in natural populations. More causal analyses are needed to determine the long-term fitness effects of male-male competition in this system and future investigations of the ecological scenarios in which negative frequency-dependent selection may be more likely to enhance beneficial gene flow into highly inbred populations should be performed. Overall, my work highlights the importance of considering the complex ecological and evolutionary interactions occurring in natural populations, particularly for those systems in which we hope to conserve.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Biological Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 7, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">Color pattern, Genetic variation, Guppies, Male-male competition, Poecilia reticulata, Sexual selection</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Kimberly A. Hughes, Professor Directing Dissertation; Michelle Arbeitman, University Representative; Joseph Travis, Committee Member; Emily DuVal, Committee Member; Scott Burgess, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014203">
      <topic>Biology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040752">
      <topic>Ecology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004042">
      <topic>Evolution (Biology)</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Guerrera_fsu_0071E_18921</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Biological Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
