<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Consequences of Myelin Debris Clearance by Microvascular Cells and Macrophages in the Progression of Secondary Spinal Cord Injury</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-8631-1966</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Hammel</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Grace Elizabeth Rachel Lydia</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/yren3">
      <namePart type="family">Ren</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Yi</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Biomedical Sciences Professor)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/fzhu">
      <namePart type="family">Zhu</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Fanxiu</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jpinto">
      <namePart type="family">Pinto</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jose R. (Jose Renato)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/bstefanovic">
      <namePart type="family">Stefanovic</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Branko</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Medicine</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Biomedical Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (125 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>Spinal cord injury (SCI) is a devastating and potentially life-threatening condition that can not only cause life-long chronic symptoms but also places an immense socioeconomic burden on the patients. SCI can be divided into two defined phases: primary injury and secondary injury. Primary injury is characterized by the initial mechanical damage caused by the injury, which is closely followed by the multifaceted and chronic secondary injury. This secondary stage of SCI can be marked by the propagation of an immense inflammatory cascade, widespread cell death, immune cell infiltration, scar formation, and disruption of the blood-spinal cord-barrier (BSCB). The work described in this dissertation aims to uncover the various consequences of cells phagocytosing myelin debris, a form of debris generated at an SCI lesion site, and the mechanistic role it plays in dramatically altering different cellular functions and promoting secondary injury progression after SCI. The changes in BSCB permeability after SCI have been well-established as a secondary injury hallmark, characterized as long-term disruption of the spinal cord vasculature radiating outward rostral and caudal of the lesion core. This disruption allows the influx of immune cells and other neurotoxic blood-associated substances into the spinal cord tissue, leading to chronic inflammation and an environment that hinders neuronal outgrowth and repair. Endothelial cells (ECs) form the innermost lining of the BSCB, which is composed of a collaborative cluster of several different cell types including pericytes and astrocytes surrounding a continuous EC membrane. The BSCB's function as a tightly regulated barrier is maintained by junctional proteins between ECs which restrict blood related substances from entering the spinal cord tissue. Alterations to these junctions can drastically impair BSCB function. A comprehensive understanding of the lesion related factors that may alter these junctional proteins and induce the increased BSCB permeability are as of yet unknown. One major goal of this work is to illustrate myelin debris' impact on endothelial junctions, demonstrate how it mechanistically promotes increased permeability and contributes to the breakdown of the BSCB, and investigate potential therapeutic techniques to block myelin debris' interaction with endothelial cells. The secondary stage of SCI involves the propagation of an extensive inflammatory cascade and immune cell infiltration, including bone marrow-derived macrophages (BMDMΦ). Another well documented event after SCI is the increased expression of members of the chondroitin sulfate proteoglycan (CSPG) family, such as neuron-glial antigen 2 (NG2), within the glial scar where it inhibits axonal growth. However, a complete picture of the cellular origins and function of this NG2 expression has yet to be made. In this study, we illustrate that certain BMDMΦ cells are among the first cells to express and secrete NG2/CSPG4 following SCI. We demonstrate, for the first time, that phagocytosis of myelin debris by BMDMΦ can induce NG2/CSPG4 expression within these cells, subsequently leading to increased proliferation and reduced phagocytic ability. These findings imply that BMDMΦ may have a more intricate role in secondary SCI progression than previously recognized, including their involvement as early contributors to the glial scar.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Biomedical Sciences in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 21, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">Blood-spinal cord-barrier, Neuroinflammation, Spinal cord injury</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Yi Ren, Professor Directing Dissertation; Fanxiu Zhu, University Representative; Jose Pinto, Committee Member; Branko Stefanovic, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91006099">
      <topic>Neurosciences</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Hammel_fsu_0071E_18960</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
