<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Role of Individual Differences and Effect of Task Repetition with Written Corrective Feedback in L2 Writing Development</mods:title>
      <mods:nonSort>The</mods:nonSort>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-1006-4617</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kim</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jeungeun</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/sli9">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Li</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Shaofeng</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/gsunderm">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Sunderman</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Gretchen L.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/phiver">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hiver</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Philip V.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2011024781">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Jones</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Ithel</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>School of Teacher Education</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (206 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Research on Task Based Language Teaching (TBLT), and learning has developed significantly in recent years. As a result of the popularity of TBLT, numerous studies in second language acquisition (SLA) have explored the effect of task repetition on L2 performance. However, while previous task repetition studies mainly focused on the effects of repeating the same task on the complexity, accuracy, and fluency (CAF) of oral language production, limited research has examined the influence of different types of task repetition on learners' written production. Moreover, although written corrective feedback has been extensively investigated in SLA, the synergy effect between task repetition and written corrective feedback in shaping the quality of individual writing task output has not received adequate attention. Notably, no study has yet compared the influence of two types of task repetition (identical repetition and procedural repetition), by providing two distinct types of feedback—direct feedback and metalinguistic feedback, on written production for upper-intermediate adult EFL learners. To address this research gap, the current study investigated the effect of task repetition and two types of feedback on the accuracy of students' written task performance. Additionally, recognizing the growing importance of individual differences (ID) in SLA, this study investigated the role of individual differences constructs such as working memory capacity, L2 writing anxiety, and L2 writing motivation on L2 learners' written production. Additionally, the level of motivation and anxiety to complete learning tasks was identified as another important factor contributing to individual variation (Kormos &amp; Wilby, 2019). Task motivation is a complex construct influenced by various contingencies associated with multiple actional contexts, making it more intricate than a simple composite of general and state motivation (Dornyei, 2002, 2005). Therefore, beyond general L2 writing motivation and L2 anxiety, the study also examined task-specific anxiety and motivation, which are transitory, to determine whether their levels change over time during task performance. Eighty adult Korean EFL learners participated in four intact classes randomly assigned to four treatment groups: identical repetition + direct feedback, identical repetition + metalinguistic feedback, procedural repetition + direct feedback, and procedural repetition + metalinguistic feedback. A pretest and posttest were employed. The two identical repetition groups repeated the same writing procedure with the same picture description, while two procedural repetition groups repeated the same writing procedure with different picture descriptions. Two types of feedback (direct and metalinguistic) were provided for each task repetition condition. To measure learners' writing development, overall accuracy and accuracy on three target structures (past tense, articles, and prepositions) were assessed. L2 writing motivation and L2 writing anxiety were measured before the treatment sessions began to explore learners' general orientation of motivation and anxiety toward L2 writing learning. However, task motivation and task anxiety were measured after they performed writing tasks each week as outcome measurers to observe their patterns. Questionnaires were used for all these four constructs, Lastly, a reading span test (RSPAN) was used for the working memory test. Results from ANCOVA indicated that the procedural task repetition groups significantly outperformed the two identical task repetition groups in overall accuracy and past tense accuracy. Regarding the role of individual differences in working memory, motivation, and anxiety, multiple regressions revealed distinct results based on treatments under each group. For both procedural task repetitions, anxiety was a positive predictor, while working memory was a negative predictor. In contrast to the two procedural task repetitions, anxiety was a negative predictor for both identical task repetition groups. Lastly, two-way repeated measure ANOVA results showed distinct motivational patterns after writing between the two task repetition groups. The two procedural task repetition groups increased their motivation, whereas the two identical task repetition groups decreased task motivation over time. Nevertheless, repeating either content or procedures appeared to alleviate learners' task-specific anxiety in writing tasks. The findings further our understanding of the language learners' perceived motivational and emotional factors influenced by task implementation and instructional strategies in the language learning context. These findings provide valuable insights into L2 pedagogy.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the School of Teacher Education in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">February 27, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Individual differences, L2 writing anxiety, L2 writing motivation, task repetition, working memory, written corrective feedback</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Shaofeng Li, Professor Directing Dissertation; Gretchen Sunderman, University Representative; Phil Hiver, Committee Member; Ithel Jones, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85043710">
      <mods:topic>English language</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Study and teaching</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Foreign speakers</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034895">
      <mods:topic>Curriculum planning</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Kim_fsu_0071E_18520</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Teacher Education</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
