<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Numerical Modeling of Hurricane Wave and Storm Surge Overtopping Sand Dunes and Barrier Island</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-2473-0609</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Ma</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Mengdi</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2013005601">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Huang</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Wenrui</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1961-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/sjung">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Jung</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Sungmoon</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/tzhao">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Zhao</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Tingting</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Geography Professor)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/yabdelrazig">
      <mods:namePart type="family">AbdelRazig</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Yassir</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>FAMU-FSU College of Engineering</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (156 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>This dissertation provides a comprehensive analysis of the intricate dynamics of coastal systems under the extreme stress of hurricanes. A multi-faceted study on the interactions between hydrodynamics, morphology dynamics, and various coastal defenses like sand dunes and vegetations during hurricane events is presented, employing advanced numerical modeling to enhance the understanding of coastal resilience and protection. It is constructed upon three pillars of research, each delving into different yet interconnected aspects of coastal defense mechanisms and their responses to hurricane-induced forces. The research begins by examining the protective functions of sand dunes against hurricane forces, utilizing a non-hydrostatic XBeach model (XBNH) to analyze wave dynamics with various storm surge after overtopping sand dunes. The research presents an in-depth analysis of wave behavior as they encounter sand dunes during hurricane-induced storm surges. The research focuses on Hurricane Michael as a case study, dissecting the dynamics of wave propagation, breaking, and overtopping. It offers a quantitative assessment of the dunes' ability to attenuate waves, pinpointing the conditions that precipitate maximum erosion and wave heights. The findings reveal that sand dunes are pivotal in reducing wave heights, particularly as storm surges intensify, with waves breaking at the dune base, overtopping, and losing their energy as they move inland. Through the model validation, the chapter establishes the superior performance of XBNH over the hydrostatic mode (XBSB), especially in critical metrics such as significant wave height and peak water surface elevation, where XBNH showed a markedly lower average and maximum error rates. This research not only underscores the precision of the XBNH, also provides the foundation for following research. The investigation then extends to the complex processes leading to barrier-island breaching during hurricane conditions. A case study using a two-dimensional XBNH model provides a detailed account of how hurricane-induced waves and storm surges interplay to alter island topography. The study reveals that supercritical flow conditions significantly contribute to the rapid erosion and eventual breaching of barrier islands, offering a predictive analysis of the morphological changes under extreme weather events. In addition, it provides a detailed account of the barrier-island's breaching evolution, through the analysis of bed elevation cross-sections and surge-wave profiles across various storm stages. This comprehensive examination not only reinforces the model's precision but also offers a deeper understanding of barrier island dynamics, contributing valuable knowledge to enhance coastal hazard mitigation strategies. The final aspect of the research integrates the hydrodynamic focus of the preceding chapters to explore the evolution of dune profiles, particular the role of vegetation in coastal protection. It highlights how different conditions of vegetation affect dune morphology under storm conditions. The study explores the use of the XBeach model to simulate these interactions, emphasizing the critical role of vegetation in mitigating erosion. Moreover, the chapter enriches the XBeach model's application by incorporating sensitivity analyses to different wind conditions, thereby broadening its predictive capability. The study's comprehensive approach illuminates the multifaceted relationship between vegetation, coastal morphology, and erosion processes. It highlights the indispensable role of vegetation in bolstering coastal resilience and provides strategic insights for coastal management, reinforcing the vital need for integrated environmental considerations in the design of coastal defense systems. To summarize, this dissertation underscores the importance of integrating hydrodynamics, morphological dynamics, and ecological considerations into coastal management practices. The results contribute valuable insights into the design and conservation of coastal defenses, promoting the development of more resilient communities in the face of increasing hurricane activities. Through the refined application of the XBeach model and the insights gained from its performance, the dissertation makes a significant contribution to the field of coastal engineering and environmental protection.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 29, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Coastal Hazard, Hurricane, Overtopping, Storm surge, Wave, XBeach</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Wenrui Huang, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Sungmoon Jung, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Tingting Zhao, University Representative; Yassir Abdelrazig, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85063458">
      <mods:topic>Hydrology</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Ma_fsu_0071E_18634</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Civil and Environmental Engineering</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
