<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Black Joy in Green Spaces a Nature-Inspired, Endarkened, Visual Narrative Inquiry about Black Women and Joy</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0008-2639-8084</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Omni</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Christal Mischelle</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/skshields">
      <namePart type="family">Shields</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sara Scott</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dmnudd">
      <namePart type="family">Nudd</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Donna M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/bparkerbell">
      <namePart type="family">Parker-Bell</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Barbara Faye</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007010325">
      <namePart type="family">Broome</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jeffrey L. (Jeffrey Lynn)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Fine Arts</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Art Education</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (160 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>What you are about to read is an a-typical dissertation developed to amplify the Black Joy message while disrupting the deficit narratives that have traditionally been the undercurrent of research regarding Black women. In response to Dr. Angela Dunbar's (2022) suggestion to "conduct research that moves beyond Black pain. Not just simply a matter of studying positive adjustment as an outcome or moderator of adversity but rather to have complete studies on non-oppressive everyday aspects…" (p. 4), Black Joy in Green Spaces served as a nature-inspired, Black Joy adventure that centered the voice and agency of Black women. Before you embark on this adventure, it is important to center my "current" Black experience that embodies both joy AND pain. I wrote this dissertation while grieving the impending death of my 16-year-old miniature pinscher, Rico, from a battle with cancer complicated by an auto-immune disease diagnosis, blindness, and hearing loss. Presently, I am grieving knowing that by the time you read these words, Rico will no longer be on this earthly plane. The grief is complex because I am being transported to the 10-days in 2016 when I watched the transition of my Mama from her 26-year battle with cancer. The overwhelming sadness experienced over the last several weeks have wreaked havoc on my emotional and mental well-being. Although heartbroken, I remain grateful and hold joy in my spirit. Rico could no longer walk for extended periods of time without falling and falling asleep, but he still enjoyed going for walks. I cradled him in my arms as we felt the gentle caress of the breeze, were kissed by the warmth of the sun, and delighted in the various aromas in the air. Rico transitioned to a spiritual plane, and it was Mother Earth who provided additional comfort during his final days. Through Rico's end-of-life journey, I am living my work in unimaginable ways. In this space, I am learning to deeply reassess the multi-generational narrative of being the "Strong" Black Woman so that I may openly pivot into a place of needing and accepting help. In this space, I am learning to challenge the White, patriarchal, capitalistic system of hyper productivity to let my BE-ing be enough. I have also learned that nature's ability to heal and restore are applicative to life AND death. As my mentor said, "You are in a sacred space and time, right now. Lean into the grief" (Haynes, personal communication, 2023). What you are about to read is that "lean in" process. Black Joy in Green Spaces leaned into the onto-epistemological strengths of Black and Brown women that ranged from both ancestral wisdom and embodied knowing, to Womanist thought, to Endarkened Narrative Inquiry, and to the personal stories from four generations of Black women to explore three primary research questions 1) What is the relationship between joy, green spaces, and Black women's experiences, 2) How does Black Joy show up for Black women who routinely commune with nature, and 3) How are the stories of Black women in green spaces used to conceptualize nature as a place of learning about and through Black Joy? This epic, intergenerational Black Joy adventure will invite you, Beloved SoulFlowers, into a space that creatively offers a novel, nature-inspired approach to address the problems of a flawed higher educational system that devalued pause along with the accompanying problems that comes with adopting an incomplete narrative that leaves Black women feeling a sense of obligation to tend to the needs of others over the needs of self. Black Joy in Green Spaces braided the fields of art education and public health to do more than contribute to a body of knowledge – it contributed to the bodies, minds, and spirits of Black women. This study utilized the primary research methods of walking, photography, and journal writing to enhance the emotional, physical, and social well-being of Black women and presented the findings as a digital storytelling project, Black Joy in Green Spaces: The Web Series, to make the research "realistic" and more relatable. My Beloved SoulFlowers, I choose not to reveal the findings in this abstract. Rather, I invite you to take a collective breath with me as you prepare to step into the world of Black Joy in Green Spaces. Are you ready? If so, join me in three…two…one: BBBRRREEEAAATTTHHHEEE!!! Let's begin…</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Art Education in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 8, 2023.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">Black Joy, Black Women, Kujima Theory of Collective-Self Motivation, Narrative Inquiry, Visual narratives, Womanism</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Sara Scott Shields, Professor Directing Dissertation; Donna Nudd, University Representative; Barbara Parker-Bell, Committee Member; Jeff Broome, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007505">
      <topic>Art</topic>
      <topic>Study and teaching</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85108638">
      <topic>Public health</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001992">
      <topic>African Americans</topic>
      <topic>Study and teaching</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Omni_fsu_0071E_18089</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Art Education</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
