<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Development of Sulfide-and Halide-Based Fast-Ion Conductors</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-4787-5739</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Poudel</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Tej Prasad</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/yhu">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hu</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Yan-yan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mhumayun">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Humayun</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Munir</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ehellstrom">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hellstrom</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Eric</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/tsiegrist">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Siegrist</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Theo</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/shatruk">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Shatruk</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Mykhailo</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>FAMU-FSU College of Engineering</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Program in Materials Science and Engineering</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (310 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>All-solid-state batteries (ASSBs) represent a promising advancement in electrochemical energy storage, with solid electrolytes (SEs) playing a crucial role. Sulfide and halide SEs have garnered substantial interest due to their distinct characteristics; sulfide SEs offer high ionic conductivity and stability with Li metal anodes, while halide SEs have better compatibility with high-voltage cathodes. This dissertation explores the structure-property relationship of mixed-anion frameworks in both sulfide- and halide-based SEs, aiming to fine-tune material structures and properties for enhanced battery performance. Firstly, we delve into the transformation of Li3PS4 via the introduction of LiBr. 31P NMR unveils the emergence of a glassy PS43− network interspersed with Br−. Solid-state NMR corroborates fast Li+ migration between PS43− and Br−, with increased Li+ mobility. A more than four-fold enhancement in ionic conductivity is observed upon LiBr incorporation (1.06 mS cm-1) into Li3PS4 (0.23 mS cm-1) resulting from the reduction of the energy barrier and transitioning Li+ transport dimensionality from 2D to 3D. The compatibility of Li3PS4 with Li metal is improved alongside an increase in critical current density (CCD) from 0.34 mA cm-2 to 0.50 mA cm-2 while preserving the electrochemical stability window. ASSB cells with 3Li3PS4:LiBr as the SE and TiS2 as the cathode active material (CAM) show robust high-rate and long-term cycling performance. Secondly, we incorporated LiBr and LiI simultaneously in Li3PS4 as a mixed-halide strategy. We achieve a two-fold increase in conductivity using a one-step ball milling technique. Subsequent low-temperature sintering further enhances conductivity to 4.43 mS/cm with a low activation energy of 0.29 eV. Furthermore, we engineered a cell configuration with stable milled SE layers toward Li metal and a high-conductive sintered SE separator in the symmetric cell with which CCD further increases compared to individual separators. In addition to sulfide-based SEs, Li-deficient lithium yttrium bromide, Li3-xYBr6-x, was prepared using the co-melting method. High-resolution X-ray diffraction and Rietveld refinement confirm the formation of the monoclinic structure with the C2/m space group with increased cation site disorder and polyhedral volume. Bond valence site energy calculations show the Li+ migration energy barrier from Li-deficiency. Ab-initio molecular dynamics simulations show the emergence of 3D-Li+ conduction. Solid-state NMR spectroscopy confirms the elimination of LiBr impurities and reveals increased Li-ion dynamics. An ionic conductivity of 4.49 mS cm-1 and activation energy of 0.28 eV were achieved. Furthermore, we synthesized a series of Li2.73Ho1.09Cl6-xBrx compounds using a solid-state co-melting approach. Crystal structure analysis revealed the presence of Li-ions in 2d octahedral sites of the C2/m space group for x ≥ 2. Analysis shows highly disordered cation sites with mixed occupancy of Li/Ho. 6Li solid-state NMR revealed a highly disordered local Li environment, which increases with Br/Cl substitution. The significant improvement in room-temperature ionic conductivity from 0.45 mS cm-1 for Li2.73Ho1.09Cl6 to 3.79 mS cm-1 for Li2.73Ho1.09Cl3.27Br2.73 is achieved with a significant decrease in activation energy from 0.38 eV to 0.32 eV, respectively. Further mixing anions and cations within a SE significantly enhances ionic conductivity by introducing controlled disorder at both cation and anion sites. This increases the system's configurational entropy and allows for the overlap of energy bands. Incorporating Mg2+ and Hf4+ into a Li3ClBrI mixed-rock-salt structure results in a substantial increase in ionic conductivity, reaching 0.88 mS cm⁻¹ for Li1.54Mg0.23Hf0.17Cl0.68BrI. The enhanced conductivity is attributed to a nanoscale solid solution between the disordered rock-salt and spinel structure. Moreover, introducing a mixed anion sublattice into cost-effective LiAlCl4 through a simple one-step mechanochemical milling process led to a 22-fold increase in ionic conductivity – from 0.0083 mS cm⁻1 to 0.18 mS cm⁻1 for Li2AlCl3S. This improvement can be attributed to the formation of new Li sites, enabling efficient 3D Li+ transport. The strategy leverages the inherent disorder to modify the Li-sublattice locally, leading to broader lithium-ion site occupancies and enhanced ion dynamics through polyhedral edge sharing. Mechanochemical milling of thiophosphate-based SEs combined with TiS2 CAM produces a composite material that leverages both cationic (Ti3+/4+) and anionic (S2-/n-, where n&lt;2) redox processes – resulting in ~2× enhancement in specific capacity. Catholytes containing mixed-anion SEs, especially with 3Li3PS4:LiBr, demonstrate better cycling performance compared to their mono-anion counterparts due to the improved ionic conductivity and thermodynamical stability. In summary, this dissertation explores innovative compositional design, optimal synthesis environment, and characterization of mixed-anion SEs, in addition to the utilization of these SEs in ASSBs. Overall, this research provides valuable insights into the development and application of high-performance ASSBs, addressing challenges associated with SEs in energy storage.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Materials Science and Engineering in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 26, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Yan-Yan Hu, Professor Directing Dissertation; Munir Humayun, University Representative; Eric Hellstrom, Committee Member; Theo Siegrist, Committee Member; Mykhailo Shatruk, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082094">
      <mods:topic>Materials science</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Poudel_fsu_0071E_18574</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Materials Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
