<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Sarcomeric Mutation Studies to Understand the Fundamental Basis of Cardiac Muscle Regulation and Pathogenesis of Cardiomyopathies</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2407-1455</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Rodriguez Garcia</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michelle</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jpinto">
      <namePart type="family">Pinto</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jose R. (Jose Renato)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/pchase">
      <namePart type="family">Chase</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">P. Bryant</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jdelp">
      <namePart type="family">Delp</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Judy Muller</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/gsalazar">
      <namePart type="family">Aranda</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Gloria Salazar</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Medicine</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Biomedical Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (149 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>According to the CDC, around 209.6 deaths per 100,000 habitants are associated with cardiovascular disease (CVD) in the United States of America. Inherited cardiomyopathies represent ~30% of CVDs. Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM), dilated cardiomyopathy (DCM), restrictive cardiomyopathy (RCM), and arrhythmogenic right ventricular cardiomyopathy (ARVC) are the most common classifications of inherited cardiomyopathies. HCM affects 1 in 500 individuals with CVD and is associated with hypertrophy of the left ventricle (LV) and decreased LV chamber. DCM affects 1 in 250 individuals with CVD and is related to LV dilation and the LV chamber's increase. Both HCM and DCM are disease that directly affects cardiac muscle mechanics and promote changes that affects the hemodynamics for the heart. The cardiac muscle is formed by bundles of muscle fibers. These muscle fibers are assembled by aggregations of cardiac muscle cells that connect at the structural level; the sarcomere comprises these cardiac muscle cells or cardiomyocytes, the muscle cells' basic contractile unit. Thin and thick filaments mostly form the sarcomere. The interaction between thin and thick filaments is associated with muscle contraction, where myosin heads from the thick filament attached to actin in the thin filament to produce force. The thick filament is mainly formed by myosin, a protein from the myosin family that is associated with contraction in striated muscle (both skeletal and cardiac muscles). Myosin's heads elongate from their backbone to interact with actin. In the presence of ADP·Pi myosin strongly binds to actin and produces shortening of the sarcomere, translating into muscle contraction. Once ADP·Pi is released, the myosin heads detach from actin, and a new cycle starts. The thin filament is formed by bundles of actin, which forms the backbone of the thin filament. In addition, the thin filament has other Ca2+ regulatory proteins directly associated with triggering muscle contraction in the cardiac muscle. The troponin complex (Tn) comprises three subunits: Troponin C (TnC) or Ca2+ regulatory subunit. In striated muscle, this subunit is directly linked to inducing Ca2+ dependent contraction. Troponin I (TnI) is the inhibitory subunit, and Troponin T (TnT) is the subunit that attaches the troponin complex to tropomyosin. Tropomyosin (Tm) is a stranded protein that lies on the actin bundles and blocks the myosin binding sites on actin. The cycling between the myosin heads and the binding to the myosin binding site on actin is known as cross bridges. In cross bridges cycling, myosin has two stages: "Super relaxed State," or SRX, where myosin is folded back to the thick filament backbone, and is not able to interact with actin, and the "Disordered Relaxed State," or DRX, where myosin head can interact with ATP and trigger the cross bridges formation. During the development of this dissertation, we will focus on specific variants that led to cardiomyopathies. Previous studies have identified variants that lead to HCM, such as β-myosin heavy chain (MYH7) and cardiac myosin-binding protein C (cMyBP-C). Also, other proteins that have been associated with DCM are Titin (TTN) and troponin T (TNNT2), to mention some proteins. On the projects developed during this dissertation, we will inquire on rare variants that lead to HCM or DCM and their impact on cardiac muscle physiology. Our first project investigates a variant of unknown significance on α -actinin 2. α-actinin 2 is a cross-linking protein located on the Z-disc. The Z-disc is an anchor structure in the sarcomere that allows the interaction of thin and thick filaments. A868T variant on α -actinin 2 has been reported to be of uncertain significance in the development of disease; however, during the development of this project, our group presented clinical, structural and mechanical data that suggest that the A868T variant induces an HCM-like phenotype. This project provides inside data that support the A868T variant as a pathological variant, which could help clinicians better assess patients in the clinical setting. In addition, this project supports the importance of the Z-disc structure for processes such as muscle contraction, which is typically linked to thin and thick filaments, and likewise, how alterations of the Z-disc can be detrimental to muscle contraction. Our second project studies the inhibition of a kinase as a potential therapeutic for treating HCM. A new mouse model was developed during this project, which had an A8V variant on cTnC and a conditional knock-out of cardiac Myosin Light Chain Kinase or cMLCK. cMLCK inhibition has been associated with structural changes that lead to dilation of the LV; however, our experimental mice with an A8V variant develop an HCM phenotype. Our hypothesis for this project was to reverse the HCM features of our experimental mice by using the basis knowledge of inhibition of cMLCK. In this section of the dissertation, we will only discuss RNAseq data, which suggests that our experimental mice present a recovery in cardiac transcriptomics that can be attributed to the inhibition of cMLCK. In addition, we discuss some canonical pathways that showed importance in our experimental group and how these pathways are essential for cardiac muscle physiology. Our data suggest that inhibition of cMLCK could potentially be used as a therapeutic target on HCM phenotypes. Our final project investigates the physiological role of Ca2+-binding sites III and IV of cTnC. For this project, our group created two knock-in (KI) mouse models, one with a mutation in Ca2+-binding site III or D105A variant and a second mouse model with a Ca2+-binding site IV variant or D141A variant. These mouse models D105A and D141A have a mutation on the first amino acid (aspartate) of the Ca2+-binding site III and IV which had been showed to be crucial for the stability of Ca2+ binding. Our goal for this project was to understand at a molecular level how Ca2+-binding sites III and IV on cTnC function in in vivo settings. Preliminary data from our mice models have shown that D105A and D141A variants induce DCM-like phenotype. This suggests that Ca2+-binding sites III and IV are pivotal in muscle contraction physiology. This dissertation section is still in progress, and some of the project's structural, molecular, and mechanical functions are underway. Integration of projects. These three projects reflect the importance of the sarcomere's different parts to maintain cardiac muscle dynamics. The different projects in this dissertation have allowed us to integrate clinical, basic, and translational research in the cardiac field. Projects like our α -actinin 2 have allowed us to integrate the basic structural knowledge better to understand the disease's clinical presentation. Our cMLCK project will enable us to use the basic understanding of the sarcomere and implement them as possible target therapy. Finally, our Ca2+-binding sites III and IV project is helping us understand the fundamental basic of cTnC.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Biomedical Sciences in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">October 30, 2023.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">alpha-actinin 2, cardiac muscle, Cardiomyopathy, muscle mechanics, muscle regulation, troponin-C</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jose Renato Dias Oliveira Pinto, Professor Directing Thesis; Prescott Bryant Chase, University Representative; Judy Delp, Committee Member; Gloria Salazar Aranda, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014203">
      <topic>Biology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85083022">
      <topic>Medical sciences</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">RodriguezGarcia_fsu_0071E_18303</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
