<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Molecular Sensitization Enabled Organic Metal Halide Hybrids and Complexes for Radiation Scintillation</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-8013-0598</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Shonde</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Tunde Blessed</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016013562">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Ma</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Biwu</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1980-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ehellstrom">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hellstrom</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Eric</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/shatruk">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Shatruk</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Mykhailo</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lnienhaus">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Nienhaus</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Lea</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (191 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>High-energy radiations such as X-rays and Gamma rays have become integral to our daily lives. They are utilized in various fields, including medical imaging, security screening, and scientific research. However, an efficient and reliable detector is required to unlock their potential fully. Scintillators play a crucial role in this process as they convert these invisible high-energy radiations into visible light photons. Despite years of research and numerous breakthroughs, scintillators still face significant challenges. Currently, the most commonly used scintillator materials are inorganic, such as NaI:Tl and CdWO4. While these materials are somewhat effective, they have some drawbacks. They are expensive to produce, and some may even be toxic. Additionally, many of these inorganic crystals do not meet the specific requirements of modern applications. As an alternative, organic materials like anthracene and stilbene have been explored as scintillators. Organic materials offer advantages over their inorganic counterparts, such as low cost, short scintillation decay time, and ease of processability. However, among many other challenges, their conversion efficiency or ability to convert radiation into charge carriers is a significant drawback. In this dissertation work, we explored the combination of the merits of both inorganic and organic materials into a single system addressing issues such as radiation absorption, scintillation light yield production, and radioluminescence decay lifetime. This work involved material and molecular design, material synthesis, characterization, processing, device fabrication, and application. The first part of this dissertation focused on increasing radiation absorption, enhancing scintillation light yield, and achieving a short radioluminescence decay lifetime. We explored three different methods. In Chapter 2, we investigated using organic metal halide hybrids as sensitizers to planar organic molecules (light emitter). We achieved spatial proximity and excellent spectral overlap between the sensitizer and the light emitter by embedding planar organic dye molecules and organic metal halide hybrids in a polymer matrix. This resulted in efficient energy transfer and a significant enhancement of radioluminescence. We also discussed challenges such as residual tailing emission and fluorescent quenching resulting from aggregation. In Chapter 3, we addressed some problems encountered in Chapter 2 with a new design concept. We ionically coupled an Aggregative-Induced Emissive (AIE) organic cation with a high Z metal halide anion, promoting efficient sensitization. This work synthesized and fully characterized a zero-dimensional (0D) organic metal halide hybrid, with the high Z metal halides acting as X-ray sensitizers and AIE organic cations as emitters. These materials were easy to prepare at low temperatures and exhibited high light yields with short decay lifetimes, dramatically enhancing X-ray scintillation. We also discussed efforts to improve solution processability in Chapter 4, where the AIE organic molecule was covalently bonded to derive an organic metal halide complex, achieving better solution processability. This covalently bonded complex demonstrated efficient molecular sensitization with zinc chloride, leading to high-energy radiation harvesting and charge transfer to the organic emitting units. The second theme of this dissertation, discussed in Chapter 5, focused on our approach to achieving scintillator-specific applications, particularly in radiotherapy. We utilized molecular engineering to control the effective Z value of organic metal halide hybrids, aiming to develop a scintillator with similar radiation interaction with water and body tissue. The work highlights the potential of organic metal halide hybrids in radiotherapy applications. In the appendix, a few of the new structures discovered during the course of this dissertation's experimental work are highlighted. Overall, this dissertation contributes to developing new scintillator materials and improves our understanding of the structure-property relationship in these materials. The findings can guide the design and application of scintillator materials and other optoelectronic devices. By addressing the challenges in scintillator development, this work paves the way for more precise and accurate detection of high-energy radiation in various fields, ultimately benefiting both scientific research and human safety.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 27, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Dosimetry, Organic metal complexes, Organic metal halide hybrids, Radiation, Scintillator, Sensitization</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Biwu Ma, Professor Directing Dissertation; Eric Hellstrom, University Representative; Mykhalio Shatruk, Committee Member; Lea Nienhaus, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022986">
      <mods:topic>Chemistry</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082094">
      <mods:topic>Materials science</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Shonde_fsu_0071E_18581</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
