<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Dynamics of Open Research Data Repository for Health Sciences in Universities</title>
      <subTitle>A Three-Paper Dissertation</subTitle>
      <nonSort>The</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-8143-7401</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Wibowo</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Muhamad Prabu</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007103328">
      <namePart type="family">Mon</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lorri M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n81065572">
      <namePart type="family">Berry</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Frances Stokes</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007104805">
      <namePart type="family">Stvilia</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Besiki</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/chinnant">
      <namePart type="family">Hinnant</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Charles C. (Charles Christopher)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Communication and Information</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>School of Information</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (172 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>This study explores multiple aspects of practices of opening and sharing health research data in university environments, including current trends, platforms, policies, and perceptions. This study consists of three papers: Paper 1: Exploring Policy Design Recommendations for Health Research Data Repositories that Promote Openness and Sharing: A Systematic Literature Review Paper 2: Adoption Patterns and Characteristics of Health Research Data Repositories in U.S. Universities Paper 3: Investigating the Practices and Preferences of Health Scholars in Opening and Sharing Research Data The first paper explores current trends and discussions on health research data repository policies that support openness and sharing through a systematic literature review. This study follows the PRISMA (Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses) approach in systematically gathering, selecting, and analyzing previous studies related to open research data repository practices and policies in the health sciences. This study selected 74 relevant articles to understand the current literature about open health data repositories. The first study's findings indicate that most articles analyzed policy documents and conducted in-depth case studies of repositories. These studies primarily focused on the United States, which emerged as the most-studied country in this field. This study suggests ten crucial recommendations that should be addressed in designing and developing health research data repository policy: standardization; data access, security, and protection; ownership and intellectual property rights; privacy and confidentiality; data acquisition and curation; data quality; training and user support; incentives and sanctions; transparency; and trust and trustworthiness. These recommendations can be used as policy design and evaluation metrics when developing health research data repositories. The second paper investigates the diffusion of health research data repositories implemented within U.S. (United States) university environments. This study uses Rogers' diffusion of innovation theory, focused on the timings of the implementation and events that influence the initiation of health research data repositories in U.S. universities. The unit analysis of this study is universities' internal units, including laboratories, libraries, and research teams, since a university can have more than one repository, and multiple universities and laboratories can manage a repository. This paper collects data on the initiation timing of health repositories through data entries indexed by re3data.org and by exploring the websites of the repositories. The second paper illustrates the adoption pattern of health research data repositories presented in an S-curve from 1987 until 2022. Several national events and policies potentially influenced some universities to implement health research data repositories, including NIH (National Institute of Health) data-sharing policies and policies that rule out the increase in public access to funded research. The study also shows the termination of health data repositories and its reasons that should be taken into account by relevant stakeholders if the main goal is to preserve research data as long as they can in a sustainable health research data repository. The third paper investigates health science researchers' perceptions of opening and sharing research data and the motivating and demotivating factors for engagement in open health data repositories. A total of 362 health science scholars in U.S. universities participated in an online questionnaire. Descriptive and inferential statistical analyses were conducted, including frequencies, cross-tabulations, descriptive ratio statistics, and the non-parametric Kruskal-Wallis Analysis of Variance. The study reveals that health scholars share data primarily with colleagues in their institution or project. They exhibit a lower tendency to engage in open research data practices through repositories and journal supplements. Motivating factors and challenges influencing researchers' decisions to open and share data were identified. Privacy and confidentiality concerns were major barriers, especially for scholars working with human-related data. Disciplinary variations and differences between funded and non-funded researchers were observed. Resources, policy compliance, and requirements were significant factors driving scholars to open and share data. The study provides insights for policy development to promote openness and sharing of health research data. This study results in a comprehensive understanding of open health big data within university environments. In addition, this study can help universities to decide the direction of big health data and open health research data policies.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the School of Information in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 9, 2023.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">health data sharing, health research data, open health data, research data management</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Lorri Mon, Professor Directing Dissertation; Frances Stokes Berry, University Representative; Besiki Stvilia, Committee Member; Charles C. Hinnant, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066150">
      <topic>Information science</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85083022">
      <topic>Medical sciences</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87002293">
      <topic>Information technology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Wibowo_fsu_0071E_17910</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Information Studies</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
