<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Unveiling the Dynamics of Community Resilience</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-7407-3320</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Yang</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jeonghwa</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dberlan">
      <namePart type="family">Berlan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">David G. (David Gregory)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ttholmes">
      <namePart type="family">Holmes</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Tisha Terrianne Joseph</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jwright4">
      <namePart type="family">Wright</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">James E.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2014058619">
      <namePart type="family">Yi</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Hongtao</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>School of Public Administration and Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (136 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>This dissertation investigates the interplay between community-based and non-government organizations, governmental strategies, and media in fostering community resilience across the United States, South Korea, and the Philippines. It explores how these entities collaborate to enhance community responses to various challenges, mainly focusing on their roles during crises and how they influence public outcomes. The first study examines the role of community-based organizations in South Korea in utilizing media to strengthen community networks and enhance social cohesion. By employing qualitative methods such as case studies and interviews, the research explores how these organizations leverage media to amplify marginalized voices and mobilize community support, thereby fostering greater community resilience. The findings reveal that effective use of media by community organizations not only increases their outreach and impact but also plays a crucial role in advocating for social change. The study emphasizes the necessity for policymakers and community leaders to support media-centric initiatives that facilitate community engagement and advocacy, enhancing the overall fabric of social cohesion. The second study focuses on the dynamics of social vulnerability management in the Philippines, particularly examining the collaborative governance models between government and community-based organizations during disaster management. This study uses grounded theory, taking an abductive approach to analyze several types of archival data. The findings highlight how active engagement and collaboration lead to more inclusive and equitable disaster management practices. It demonstrates that integrating collaborative governance into disaster management policies can significantly improve the handling of social vulnerabilities, urging the development of policies prioritizing social equity and community involvement in the decision-making process. The final study investigates how media in the United States frames the COVID-19 vaccine, with a specific focus on minority issues. Utilizing Natural Language Processing (NLP) techniques, the study conducts a content analysis of news articles to quantify framing and sentiment trends. This study showed the disparity between the sentiment scores and the statistical test results. It implies that policymakers should understand both the apparent and underlying impacts of media coverage on public opinion and use comprehensive analytical methods to discern real impacts from perceived trends. It suggests that public health officials and policymakers work closely with media outlets to ensure that health communication is balanced, comprehensive, and accurately represents all community segments' concerns, thereby effectively supporting public health objectives. This dissertation contributes significantly to the field of public administration by highlighting the importance of community engagement and the strategic use of media in promoting resilient and equitable community responses. Theoretical, methodological, and practical implications drawn from the studies provide valuable insights for enhancing community engagement and improving disaster response and public health strategies. Future research could expand upon these findings to further explore the effectiveness of these strategies in different contexts and over more extended periods, potentially offering more generalized solutions to global challenges in public administration and community management.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Askew School of Public Administration and Policy in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 13, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">David G. Berlan, Professor Directing Dissertation; Tisha J. Holmes, University Representative; James E. Wright II, Committee Member; Hongtao Yi, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85108611">
      <topic>Public administration</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Yang_fsu_0071E_18880</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Public Administration and Policy</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
