<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Geneses and Geochemical Relationship of Forearc Basaltic Magmas in Cascadia Columbia Transect, Cascades Arc</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0004-2292-130X</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Zhang</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Yin</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85215468">
      <namePart type="family">Salters</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Vincent J. M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ehellstrom">
      <namePart type="family">Hellstrom</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Eric</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mhumayun">
      <namePart type="family">Humayun</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Munir</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mye">
      <namePart type="family">Ye</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ming</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (248 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>Typically arc magmatism is restricted to a narrow band semi-parallel to the trench, with the slab surface sits at 70- to 170-km depth (Gill, 1981; Syracuse &amp; Abers, 2006). At the Cascadia Columbia Transect (CCT), the arc width is expanded towards both forearc and backarc. The Boring Volcanic Field, Indian Heaven Volcanic Field, and Mount St. Helens are three forearc volcanic fields in Cascadia Columbia Transect. Beneath the Boring Volcanic Field, the slab depth beneath volcanoes is estimated to be at only ~55 km (McCrory et al., 2012). The Cascadia Columbia Transect erupts variable magmas types including typical arc magmas: calc-alkaline basalt (CAB), basaltic andesite (BA), andesite (AND), and rhyolite (RHY). In addition, high-K magmas (HKCA), low-K magmas (LKT), and intraplate-type magmas (IPB) occur. As the overlying continental crust is 35-40 km thick (Syracuse et al., 2010), the thickness of forearc mantle is only 20 km. The variability of magmas in the transect is possibly related to the hot nature of the subduction zone, or unusual disturbance of the mantle thermal structure and/or mantle flow. To understand the underlying dynamics of magma generation beneath Cascadia Columbia Transect, I analyzed and compiled major element, trace element, and isotopic composition of Boring Volcanic Field, Indian Heaven Volcanic Field, and Mount St. Helens. The elemental and isotopic compositions of magmas are used to analyze and model the processes of magma generation in the mantle and evolution in the crust, including source mixing, melting peridotite, fractional crystallization, assimilation, and magma mixing. The most primitive magmas have distinct geochemical characteristics which indicates the primitive magmas are spatially separated during their ascent. All the three volcanic fields, overlap in isotopic compositions even for the primitive magmas. Though there are scattering in the isotopic compositions due to source heterogeneity, the trace elemental composition of Mount St. Helens basalts can be reproduced by mixing of more primitive Boring volcanic magmas and basaltic andesite. The three volcanic fields thus are proposed to have same mantle genesis with different extents of heterogeneity. Their sources (endmembers) are modeled by a three-component source mixing model involving a depleted background mantle, a sediment melt, and an eclogite melt from the mafic part of the slab. The model uses estimated source composition of the LKT magmas from ~6% of melting, to constrain the enrichment in the slab components. The source of the LKT magmas are the background mantle and this component is considered to be ubiquitously present. The level of enrichment of the other two components is determined by the trace element and isotopic composition of the primitive members of a magma type. It is concluded that the slab components added to the background mantle are depleted in large-ion lithophile elements (LILE), but Ba and Sr are more enriched. The most enriched high-K calc-alkaline magmas are generated separately from other magmas, with components with isotopic compositions the same as used for the other magma-types, but different trace element compositions. The high-field strength element depletion in the calc-alkaline magmas and the absence of such depletion in the intra-plate magmas are explained by the slab straddling at a critical point where rutile is residual or is dissolved in the melt. The magmas from Boring Volcanic Field and Mount St. Helens both show convergent compositional trend from primitive magmas to basaltic andesites, and Indian Heaven magmas also display a smaller range in elemental and isotopic characteristics at this silica content. Andesites and more felsic magmas form a single trend with silica. The modeled fractional crystallization paths indicate primitive magmas cannot evolve to felsic magmas through fractional crystallization alone in all the three volcanic fields. Instead, mixing lines between primitive and more evolved magma compositions show assimilation is a significant process in making the felsic magmas. The absence of more felsic magmas at monogenetic volcanic fields are explained by shorter residence time in the crust and the lower volume of erupted magma. The unique characteristics of felsic magmas of Mount St. Helens and the adjacent volcanic fields excludes widespread lateral movement of magmas within the crust.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Earth, Ocean and Atmospheric Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 29, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">Boring Volcanic Field, Cascadia Columbia Transect, Indian Heaven Volcanic Field, Mount St. Helens, Sr-Nd-Hf-Pb isotopes</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Vincent Salters, Professor Directing Dissertation; Eric Hellstrom, University Representative; Munir Humayun, Committee Member; Ming Ye, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85054037">
      <topic>Geology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Zhang_fsu_0071E_18688</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
