<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-4.xsd"
           version="3.4">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Application of Organic Synthesis to the Development of New Imaging Tools for Fluorescence Microscopy</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <namePart type="family">Macias Contreras</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Miguel Angel</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007113222">
      <namePart type="family">Zhu</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lei</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">1978-</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Professor Directing Dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2012037971">
      <namePart type="family">Piekarewicz</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jorge</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">University Representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kghanson">
      <namePart type="family">Hanson</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kenneth G.</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/bgmiller">
      <namePart type="family">Miller</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Brian G.</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (197 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >This dissertation consists of six chapters. Chapter one gives to the reader a brief introduction to several key concepts and backgrounds such as the relevance of zinc(II) ions in biology, the definition of small molecular probes and the development of protein tags, including the SNAP-tag technology, and bioorthogonal reactions for specific labeling of targets of interest. Chapter two is focused on the synthesis of small molecular probes for selective detection of zinc(II) ions. The rationale behind their chemical structures involves (1) using a 7-dimethylaminocoumrin derivative as a fluorophore with good absorbance at 405 nm and (2) subtle modification of chemical structure to tune binding affinity. A family of three sensors was synthesized and their photophysical characterization was conducted in both organic and aqueous solutions. One of the sensors has a binding affinitity towards zinc(II) in the nanomolar range, which is relevant to certain organelles where the zinc(II) concentration is believed to be in that range. All sensors were used to image low and high concentration of zinc(II) ions in live HeLa cells. Chapter three shows how a small molecular probe was evolved into a substrate for the self-labeling enzyme SNAP-tag. The replacement of the benzyl ring in a O6-benzylguanine (BG) derivative with a pyridyl ring generated a new class of compounds, O6-(5-pyridylmethyl)guanine (5PG). 5PG derivatives were shown to be taken up by the enzyme, demonstrating its substrate ambiguity. A fluorescent 5PG derivative was employed to selectively label intracellular compartments such as nuclear envelope, actin fibers, lysosomes and Golgi apparatus. The pyridine ring was introduced with the purpose of forming part of a tetradentate ligand for zinc(II); thus, making the pyridine an integral part of a coordination motif and not only an spectator group. Such unique situation enabled the imaging of low and high concentrations of zinc at precise locations. Chapter four focusses on the development of SNAP-tag substrates for intracellular bioorthogonal labeling. A series of BG derivatives carrying reactive handles such as azides and strained alkenes was synthesized. The occurrence of strain promoted azide-alkyne cycloaddition (SPAAC) and inverse electron demand Diels-Alder (IED-DA) reaction inside cells was demonstrated using fluorescence microscopy. By introducing first a reactive handle via SNAP-tag, followed by the reaction with a suitable fluorophore, two intracellular targets –nuclear envelope and actin fibers –were specifically labeled. But the real novelty of this work is the concurrent dual labeling inside live HeLa cells. To demonstrate the feasibility of the simultaneous labeling of two protein targets the orthogonal pairs SNAP/CLIP and SPAAC/IED-DA were used. Two-color fluorescent microscopic images showed the orthogonality of the two pairs. In one experiment, the nuclear envelope was labeled with a green dye via CLIP-IED-DA and the actin fibers through SNAP-SPAAC. In a second experiment, the targets were reversed and the correct labeling was found, proving the specificity and flexibility of the method. Chapter five is divided in three sections and is intended to show the results that were not included in Chapters two, three and four but that were significant to the completion of the projects associated with those chapters. The first section is focused on the synthesis of a small molecular probe complementary to the ones described in Chapter two. After trying different synthetic strategies, such a compound could not be made. The second section describes the synthetic journey that was travelled to obtain a chelating azide containing 5PG derivative. Several strategies were followed but eventually it was shown that a bifunctional pyridine derivative carrying alcohol and acetal functionalities was the key intermediate needed to obtain the target compound. Two other BG derivatives with chelating azide functionality were also prepared. The third section focusses on the application of the azido-containing BG derivatives in the bioorthogonal labeling of live and fixed cells. The copper-catalyzed azide-alkyne cycloaddition (CuAAC) mediated labeling was not possible in living cells but it was made available in fixed cells. Fixed cells were labeled at concentrations as low 25 μM Cu(II) and with or without the use of an auxiliary ligand, showing the superiority of chelating azides versus regular azides. Chapter six concludes the work presented in the entire document.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Spring Semester 2019.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 11, 2019.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">bioorthogonal labeling, fluorescence microscopy, intracellular imaging, SNAP-tag, zinc(II) sensing</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Lei Zhu, Professor Directing Dissertation; Jorge Piekarewicz, University Representative; Kenneth G. Hanson, Committee Member; Brian G. Miller, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023022">
      <topic>Chemistry, Organic</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">2019_Spring_MaciasContreras_fsu_0071E_14999</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2019-10-14T16:36:31.241-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
