<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-4.xsd"
           version="3.4">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Ring Opening Metathesis Polymerization of Low Ring Strain Species</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <namePart type="family">Neary</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">William James</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kennemur">
      <namePart type="family">Kennemur</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Justin Glenn</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Professor Directing Dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/alamo">
      <namePart type="family">Alamo</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Rufina G.</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">University Representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016054557">
      <namePart type="family">Alabugin</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Igor V.</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Professor)</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jsmith17">
      <namePart type="family">Smith</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Joel M.</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (203 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >The ring opening metathesis polymerization of cyclopentene has been historically challenging due to the low ring strain nature of the cyclic olefin. Due to these challenges, the ROMP of this unique monomer has been overlooked for many years. We aim to shine light on this material and hopefully highlight its synthetic utility in areas that lack synthetic diversity in this thesis. We began our adventure on the ROMP of cyclopentenes with the investigation of 4-phenylcyclopentene. The polymers produced from this monomer upon hydrogenation produced a precision ethylene-styrene copolymer with a phenyl on every 5th carbon backbone equating to a material with 71.2% styrene (w/w). Not only was this an area where single-site catalyst struggled, but this was the first time these polymers were produced in a precise manner. These materials lead our group to many other investigations such as investigations on its mechanical properties, post-polymerization modifications, and also a handful of collaborations. While this material brought a new interest of precision based materials to the Kennemur lab and laid one of the core foundations of our labs, it did leave some things to be desired, notably, the control of this polymerization process. Our emerging interest in this polymer quickly led us to find that controlling the polymerizations of cyclopentene based monomers using ruthenium based catalyst were problematic. With no system in place to control polymerizations, our group came up with a new methodology that utilizes cyclopentenes low ring strain and common thermodynamic principles to control the polymerizations. In this new methodology, termed variable temperature-ROMP, the simple variation of reaction temperature allowed for total control over the polymerization process for the first time. With this new methodology in hand, we aimed to synthesize complex architectures in which the newly formed precision materials were needed. The first structures we targeted were bottlebrush polymers. The successful polymerizations produced precision grafted polymers with grafts on every fifth backbone carbon, similar to the most common bottlebrush structures, poly(norbornene)s. This account was our first success in the realm of precision complex architectures, and hopefully many more architectures using these materials and the definitive correlation of structure to material properties will ensue. Out of all of experiments a graduate student imagines when joining a polymer lab, depolymerizing ones precious polymer back into starting material is the last thing they imagine. However, the unique topology of polypentenamers made this imagination a reality. Realizing that bottlebrush polymers produced from polypentenamers depolymerize in a unzipping mechanism unlocked a lot of possibilities for the future of this lab. This thesis will discuss in detail all of the success of polypentenamers in the Kennemur lab over the years and current work aimed to better understand these materials.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Spring Semester 2019.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 13, 2019.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Justin G. Kennemur, Professor Directing Dissertation; Rufina A. Alamo, University Representative; Igor A. Alabugin, Committee Member; Joel M. Smith, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022986">
      <topic>Chemistry</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">2019_Spring_Neary_fsu_0071E_15084</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2019-10-14T16:36:31.241-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
