<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Contribution of Storm Waves to Bed Shear-Stress and Sediment Movement near the Florida Panhandle Coast</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0004-5867-550X</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Aguirre Nunes</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Mariana</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2009143870">
      <namePart type="family">Speer</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kevin G. (Kevin George)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mhuettel">
      <namePart type="family">Huettel</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Markus</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n98061219">
      <namePart type="family">Chassignet</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Eric P.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (65 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Coastal areas are very dynamic places, and a lot of that is due to the movement of waves and currents, which are responsible for disturbances on the seabed by causing shear-stress. Bed shear-stress can cause sediment motion and transport, which is very important in coastal areas because of beach morphology changes, viability of coastal constructions, among others. However, sediment transport depends on very complex and interactive processes, some of which are still not very well understood or sometimes poorly calculated. Waves and currents are the main drivers of sediment movement in coastal areas. This study analyzed the wave contribution to the bed shear-stress near the coast of the Florida Panhandle. Florida is one of the most vulnerable states to hurricanes in the US, but the Peninsular Florida acts as a shield for the Gulf side from westerly hurricanes, and the wide West Florida Shelf protects this region from the Gulf waters. Dog Island Reef is located near the coast of the Florida Panhandle, on a low gradient and low energy continental margin. The region is composed mostly of sandy beaches, barrier islands, and low energy waves arrive at the shoreline. Four stations were chosen near Dog Island Reef to have sediments collected and analyzed for size distribution. The sediment sampling stations were strategically located in between two other sites where wave data were collected for four years (2008 – 2011). The wave data was acquired using moored ADCPs and narrowed down to the period of peak hurricane season (August 1st to October 31st). Relevant statistical wave parameters such as significant and maximum wave heights (HS and HMax), and wave directions (WDir) are presented for both sites during each storm period. The four sediment samples were classified into the textural group "slightly gravely sand", presenting a low percentage (~ 5%) of fine gravel or bigger; station 2 showed a high (72%) percentage of small sizes (fine sand or smaller) when compared to the other 3 stations (25%). Six tropical cyclones that passed through the Northeastern Gulf of Mexico in that period were selected for the analysis. All storms caused similar wave heights at site A (HS ~ 1.1 m, HMax ~ 1.7 m) with highest waves coming from south-southwest quadrants, and the highest wave caused by Tropical Storm Fay. Site B had more variability in wave height (HS 1.5 ~ 2.8 m, HMax 2.7 ~ 4.5 m) and spread directions. Tropical Storm Lee created southerly winds with the longest fetch, generating the highest waves in the record. All recorded wind directions followed an organized and delineated clockwise (counterclockwise for Fay) change of directions during storms closest approach to mooring sites, while wave directions followed that same pattern with a -15° offset approximately. The critical shear stress for initiation of movement was calculated for both sites considering median grain size d50 = 292.9 µm, and was 0.2 Nm-2. The mean calculated wave-induced stress was approximately 0.04 Nm-2 at both sites, and maximum of 0.52 / 1.11 Nm-2 for sites A/B respectively. Tropical Storm Lee caused the highest stresses for the longest time at both sites. During the four-year period analyzed, stress was above critical threshold of movement for less than 10% of the year, and storms were usually responsible for about 50% of that contribution.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Earth Ocean and Atmospheric Sciences in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Oceanography.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 11, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Bed Shear-Stress, Florida, Northearstern Gulf of Mexico, Reef, Storm waves, Tropical cyclones</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Kevin Speer, Professor Directing Thesis; Markus Huettel, Committee Member; Eric Chassignet, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093937">
      <topic>Oceanography</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">AguirreNunes_fsu_0071N_17999</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Science</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
