<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Examining the Impact of Pretrial Practices on Individuals and Communities</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-6455-6700</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Casey</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">William Michael</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jcopp">
      <namePart type="family">Copp</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jennifer E.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/stripodi">
      <namePart type="family">Tripodi</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Stephen J.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79075352">
      <namePart type="family">Blomberg</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Thomas G.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ssiennick">
      <namePart type="family">Siennick</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sonja E.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Criminology and Criminal Justice</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Criminology and Criminal Justice</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (182 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Research examining incarceration in jails has grown in recent years. Much of this work has focused explicitly on pretrial detainees; that is, those housed within local jails who have yet to be convicted. This population makes up a growing share of the jail population, and currently stands at roughly two-thirds of all jail inmates nationwide. The reason that most pretrial detainees find themselves in custody rather than awaiting trial in the community is not because they have been determined to pose an unmanageable threat to public safety, but rather because they could not pay a cash bail amount set by a judge. Recognizing the role of cash bail in America's reliance on jail incarceration, past work has attempted to identify the factors underlying judge's bail decisions, or to examine the negative consequences associated with our system of cash bail. However, this work suffers from three key limitations. First, past work on racial and ethnic disparities in pretrial detention has focused narrowly on judges' discretion and the factors underlying judicial decision-making. Second, prior research has considered the effects of cash bail and pretrial detention beyond the pretrial stage, including convictions and post-adjudication recidivism; however, this work has not considered the extent to which pretrial considerations shape cumulative disadvantage across the criminal justice system. Third, research on the consequences of bail and pretrial detention has focused primarily on individual-level criminal justice outcomes, largely neglecting the broader impacts of the cash bail system. Using data from Palm Beach County, Florida and the American Community Survey, and focusing on theoretical perspectives from the sentencing and communities and crime traditions, this dissertation aims to address these limitations through three empirical chapters. The first empirical chapter examines the role of bail schedules (i.e., policy documents that provide bail amount recommendations for different charges) in pretrial release, including whether bail schedules contribute to racial and ethnic disparities in release outcomes. Additionally, this chapter examines judges' adherence to the bail schedule during the initial court hearing, including whether judges similarly rely on schedule recommendations across racial and ethnic groups. The second empirical chapter extends this by examining whether the bail schedule contributes to adverse outcomes across multiple stages of the criminal case process (i.e., pretrial, conviction, sentencing) and whether the cumulative impact of these negative outcomes is greater for Black and Latino people relative to Whites. The final empirical chapter examines the distribution of cash bail across census tracts in Palm Beach County, Florida and identifies the community-level characteristics associated with high levels of cash bail. Evidence regarding the impact of bail schedules on racial and ethnic disparities in pretrial release was somewhat mixed. Contrary to expectations, Black and Latino felony defendants were more likely to be released via the bail schedule than their White counterparts. As expected, however, Latino people booked on a misdemeanor were less likely to be released than Whites. I attempt to explain these patterns, but also note that releases via the schedule comprise fewer than one in three cases. In contrast, most individuals booked into the Palm Beach County Jail appear before a judge for a bail hearing. The findings revealed that judges relied on the bail amount recommended by the schedule in roughly half of these hearings. Although departures were more frequently in the direction of issuing lower bail amounts, judges departed upward from the recommendation in more than one in five cases. Furthermore, while downward departures were issued similarly across racial and ethnic groups, judges were more likely to issue upward departures for Black and Latino people relative to Whites. These findings suggest that the bail schedule contributes to racial disparities primarily through its impact on judicial decision-making. Findings from the second chapter additionally revealed that the bail schedule contributes to cumulative disadvantage across the criminal justice system's stages. Specifically, those who were detained via the bail schedule fared worse during later stages of the criminal case process, including adjudication and sentencing. Furthermore, among felony defendants, these cumulative impacts were disproportionately experienced by members of racial and ethnic minority groups. Taken together, these findings suggest that local pretrial policies and practices play an important role in shaping pretrial decision-making, and that these pretrial decisions have cascading effects on later criminal justice system stages. Findings from the third chapter underscore that despite the important immediate and later consequences associated with local pretrial policies and practices, the effects of pretrial decisions--and the decision to issue money bail in particular—extend beyond the individual. Indeed, similar to other markers of criminal justice involvement, including arrest and incarceration, cash bail appears to be spatially concentrated in several areas within Palm Beach County, including census tracts that are characterized by high levels of concentrated disadvantage, high percentages of Black residents, and high levels of criminal justice activity.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the College of Criminology and Criminal Justice in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 7, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Cash bail, Ethnicity, Jails, Pretrial detention, Race</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jennifer E. Copp, Professor Directing Dissertation; Stephen J. Tripodi, University Representative; Thomas G. Blomberg, Committee Member; Sonja E. Siennick, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002994">
      <topic>Criminology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Casey_fsu_0071E_18178</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Criminology and Criminal Justice</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
