<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Education through Incarceration</title>
      <subTitle>Access to Education within Florida's Prisons</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0009-5082-8416</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Dross</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Megan M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/wecton">
      <namePart type="family">Ecton</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Walter</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2011019943">
      <namePart type="family">Newman</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Joshua I.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1976-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n97036418">
      <namePart type="family">Herrington</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Carolyn D.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/cmokher">
      <namePart type="family">Mokher</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Christine G.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (75 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Across the United States a significant number of individuals find themselves incarcerated each year. For the state of Florida, this number represents one of the highest in the country (Carson, 2021). Prior research has indicated that incarcerated populations across the country tend to have a lower literacy level and less education experience than most (Bender et al., 2016; Cho &amp; Tyler, 2010; Dewey et al., 2020; Lockwood et al., 2015; Pompoco et al., 2017). The addition of education to one's experience while serving their time in prison can not only improve these things but also their post-release job opportunities and the individual's quality of life while serving their time (Cho &amp; Tyler, 2010; Courtney, 2019; Lockwood et al., 2015; McCorkel &amp; DeFina, 2019; Pompoco et al., 2017). Knowing the benefits education can bring, this study looks to understand access to education programs for those housed in a Florida Department of Corrections facility. Specifically, this study examines what community and institutional factors may predict the offering of career and technical education (CTE) programs and academic and special education (ASE) programs and why. Through a series of logistical regressions, this study found that there are several factors that can predict certain education offerings both at the county and facility levels. For CTE programs, positive factors predicting that a facility will offer CTE include location in a rural county, the number of facilities within an area, being privately run, and potentially new legislation. For ASE programming, the size of the correctional facility population as well as the gender served were positive factors on the probability of program offering. Within both areas, there are also factors that can reduce the probability of program offering. For CTE programs these include increased enrollment within post-secondary education within the county, the race of the county population, the custody classification level of the correctional facility, gender served at the facility, and the percentage of residents committed to a correctional facility each year. For ASE programming, institutions in rural counties have a lower likelihood of offering ASE coursework. There are several study implications that focus on increasing access to education programs for those currently incarcerated in Florida. First is evaluating the connection between rural communities and correctional education offering. For CTE programs, location in a rural county is a positive relationship, while for ASE programs it is not. Understanding the support and value the rural community is bringing to CTE education can not only help to expand it, but also address what challenges may come to offering basic education in the same way. Additionally, the population of both the county and facility were significant in the odds of program offering. For counties with an increased diversity, odds of CTE program offerings declined. For every 1% increase of Black residents, the probability of CTE programs were lower by 10.4%. A similar trend was seen for those classified as Other showing 25.9% lower odds. Looking at the population of residents, it is important to dive deeper into this analysis, breaking down the population into further subgroups to truly understand the outcomes. Additionally, correctional facilities serving male residents showed a higher probability of ASE programs, but a lower probability of CTE programs. Focusing on the facility itself, both those locations with a highest custody classification of community or maximum saw lower odds of CTE program offering as compared to other custody classifications. In contrast, privately run facilities saw higher probability of CTE programs. While the study did conclude that education access was present for those incarcerated within Florida, several factors were identified that could hinder the offering of these programs in certain facilities and areas. The thing found most impactful was the location where an individual was housed. Focusing on both the physical location as well as the custody designation given to the facility, the likelihood of CTE and ASE program offerings differed. With a goal of expanding programming to all, knowing why both the opportunities and challenges exist provides context to expand partnership and legislation within the state system.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Education.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 4, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Corrections Education, Prison Education</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Walter Ecton, Professor Directing Dissertation; Joshua Newman, University Representative; Carolyn Herrington, Committee Member; Christine Mokher, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001028">
      <topic>Adult education</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Dross_fsu_0071E_18516</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Education</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
