<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Exploring the Experiences of MSW Students</title>
      <subTitle>from an HBCU to a PWI</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9643-6404</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Edwards</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Carol Campbell</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/eludwig">
      <namePart type="family">Ludwig</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Eric</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2012007578">
      <namePart type="family">Jones</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Tamara Bertrand</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2011019943">
      <namePart type="family">Newman</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Joshua I.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1976-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/cbeatty">
      <namePart type="family">Beatty</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Cameron C.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dm22w">
      <namePart type="family">Moraguez</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Daniel</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (111 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >HBCUs have contributed to the formation of strong leaders who have challenged many assumptions of our nation's founders, defended our sovereignty when attacked by internal and external enemies, and sacrificed for the betterment of their communities. HBCU campuses include opportunities for Black students to engage in religious and community service and to identify with cultural strengths that are expected to help them succeed (Albritton, 2012). HBCUs have higher retention and graduation rates for Black students, and "African American students attending HBCUs are up to 33% more likely to graduate than African American students attending a similar non-HBCU" (Gordon et al., 2021, p. 333). HBCUs are known to provide students with faculty mentors, supportive learning experiences, and a sense of belonging on campus (Kim &amp; Conrad, 2006). Students Although some HBCUs offer MSW programs, participants' decision to attend graduate school at FSU was motivated by the need for a clinically oriented program, internship opportunities, and a desire for new experiences. Following undergraduate studies, 74.8% of graduate social work students attend predominately White institutions (PWIs). However, Black students at PWIs reported that discrimination, isolation, and a lack of support services negatively affected their experiences and served as a distraction to learning (Banks, 2020; Beasley, 2020; Person &amp; Christensen, 1996). Additionally, research exploring Black students' experiences transitioning to a PWI for graduate studies has focused on science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) careers (Allen &amp; Dika, 2020; Charleston et al., 2014; McGee &amp; Martin, 2011). While there is a benefit in understanding the experiences of these students, the increase in the number of Black students pursuing careers in social work and other behavioral sciences warrants research (Bowie et al., 2011). Also, while Rasheem and Brunson (2018) added valuable research contributions focused on Black women and HBCU graduate social work programs, this study expands the conversation to address the unique experiences of Black HBCU graduates seeking MSWs at PWIs. The literature included in this study expands Black students' voices and provides diverse approaches to understanding how to create educational environments that meet their needs (Allen &amp; Dika, 2020; Ladson-Billings, 2013). Deconstructing deficit-based paradigms and elevating the voices of researchers engaged in developing culturally relevant pedagogy provides educational systems with an opportunity to create academic environments that value the intellectual and cultural strengths that students possess (Ladson-Billings, 2017; Royal &amp; Gibson, 2017; Yosso, 2005). Using a qualitative case study design, this study examined the experiences and perceptions of 17 Black Master of Social Work (MSW) students enrolled in the Florida State University (FSU) College of Social Work (CSW) who obtained an undergraduate degree from an HBCU. According to data from the FSU Office of Institutional Research, Black MSW student enrollment increased from 539 students in 2019 to 875 in 2023. The study findings are extricated through brave conversations filled with candor, wit, and resilience as participants recounted the cultural dissonance between their HBCU and PWI experiences. As a result, the study findings identify the cultural strengths and expectations HBCU graduates bring to PWI graduate social work programs, the environmental challenges Black students contend with, and the differences they encounter in faculty and peer relationships. The findings from this study provide implications that advance inclusive academic experiences for Black HBCU graduates attending Predominantly White Institutions (PWIs) for their MSW. To provide comparable levels of support Black students receive at HBCUs, PWIs must better meet the needs of Black students (Banks et al., 2020; Beasley, 2021). Credle and Dean (1991) noted that PWIs must create policies and practices that better meet African American students' culture and academic expectations if they are committed to retaining them. In accordance with the ADEI standards, CSWE's EPAS, and the FSW CSW DEI Plan, this study directly implicates aspects of social work education at PWIs that address implicit and explicit curricula, utilizing inclusive strategies that emphasize student identity, faculty development, and student engagement (Banks et al., 2020; Beasley, 2021; Herzig, 2004).</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Education.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 5, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Antiracism, Culture, Diversity, HBCU, PWI, Social work</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Eric Ludwig, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Tamara Bertrand Jones, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Joshua Newman, University Representative; Cameron Beatty, Committee Member; Daniel Moraguez, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009102068">
      <topic>Education, Higher</topic>
      <topic>Administration</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85118362">
      <topic>School management and organization</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041146">
      <topic>Educational sociology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Edwards_fsu_0071E_18705</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Education</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
