<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Underrepresentation of Racially and Ethnically Minoritized Allied Healthcare Faculty</title>
      <subTitle>An Exploratory Study of Faculty Experiences and Perceptions in Colleges Serving Rural Areas in Florida The Underrepresentation of Racially and Ethnically Minoritized Allied Healthcare Faculty: An Exploratory Study of Faculty Experiences and Perceptions in Colleges Serving Rural Areas in Florida</subTitle>
      <nonSort>The</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0008-9404-4050</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Kent-Smith</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Shana</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024 2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (93 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >The National Center for Education Statistics (NCES, 2022) reported that White faculty members constituted 74% of the total number of faculty, while racial and ethnically minoritized groups, including Black, Hispanic, Asian/Pacific Islander, and Native Americans, collectively comprised less than one-fourth of faculty members. Comparatively, a decade ago, NCES, (2013) illustrated similar trends, with only 21% of racially minoritized faculty showcasing negligible progress over the past 10 years. This underrepresentation extends beyond specific disciplines, suggesting a systemic issue prevalent across academia, especially in allied healthcare programs. According to Salsberg et al. (2021) study of 10 healthcare professions, there is a notable underrepresentation of Black, Hispanic, and Native Americans compared to their respective proportions in the population. The allied healthcare programs in this study include Cardiovascular Technologist, Emergency Medical Service, Diagnostic Medical Sonography, Radiographer, Occupational Therapist Assistant, and Respiratory Care. This abstract qualitative exploratory study aimed at to examine racial minority faculty experiences and perceptions of difficulties and success within allied healthcare full-time faculty in colleges serving the rural areas of Florida. Understanding the challenges faced by racially and ethnically minoritized faculty members is critical for addressing the persistent underrepresentation in allied healthcare fields (Abdul-Raheem, 2016; Allen &amp; Garg, 2016; Kaplan et al., 2018) by identifying the challenges of underrepresentation, and effective interventions to enhance racially minoritized healthcare faculty recruitment and retention. Addressing this shortage is pivotal for fostering diversity among faculty, improving graduation outcomes for diverse allied healthcare students, enhancing cultural competence within the healthcare workforce, and ameliorating healthcare disparities in underserved rural communities. By shedding light on biases, microaggressions, and skepticism regarding qualifications, the findings from this research underscore the pervasive nature of bias within academic environments. Consequently, academia faces an urgent imperative to confront these disparities and cultivate inclusive climates where all faculty members are valued for their scholarly contributions. Initiatives focusing on mentorship, professional development, and supportive leadership emerge as pivotal pathways to empower minoritized faculty to navigate and surmount prevailing obstacles. Addressing systemic barriers and fostering diversity, equity, and inclusion are crucial for enabling all faculty members, irrespective of background, to thrive and contribute effectively to academia and healthcare (Nair &amp; Adetayo, 2019; Poole &amp; Brownlee, 2020; Ratledge, 2020) The implication of this study for allied healthcare is the key necessity to recruit and retain a minoritized allied healthcare faculty by promoting mentorship and a supportive network for professional development. Overcoming system biases are critical to dismantling barriers faced by a minoritized faculty member, promoting their success, and enriching the cultural variety of healthcare education and profession. Moreover, the implications of this study extend beyond academia to inform broader societal conversations about systemic racism, discrimination, and social justice. The study contributes to ongoing efforts to address disparities in various sectors, including student experiences, institutional leadership dynamics, policy frameworks, and diversity and inclusion endeavors. Effective interventions necessitate decisive leadership action bolstered by robust policy frameworks to improve healthcare disparities in resource allocation and promote equitable support structures for all faculty. Mitigating stereotypes, biases, and resource disparities while fostering supportive leadership and mentorship is crucial for creating an environment where all faculty members feel valued, supported, and empowered to succeed (Luster-Edward &amp; Martin, 2018; Llama et al., 2019; Kelly et al., 2017; Kelly &amp; McCann, 2014). The study's findings supported recommendations needed for further research to advance knowledge about the experiences of minoritized faculty within academia and inform evidence-based interventions to mitigate disparities and promote a sense of belonging, intentional support, and welcome. Acknowledging and addressing the challenges faced by racially and ethnically minoritized allied healthcare faculty is crucial for institutions to fulfill their mandate of providing equitable opportunities for scholarly engagement and professional advancement. Pursuing these research avenues is essential for realizing academia's standard as an inclusive and intellectually vibrant community fostering the holistic development of all academic members in higher education. The exploratory study revealed support recommendations for practice to advocate for racially and ethnically minoritized full-time faculty members. The combination of proactive leadership for an engaging support system, cultural awareness training, and professional training to identify and navigate bias for all employees, and an intentional mentorship program to encourage collaboration and a supportive network is essential for minoritized healthcare faculty members to succeed.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Education A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Education.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 4, 2024 April 4, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Allied Healthcare Faculty, Healthcare Disparities, Minoritized Allied Healthcare Faculty, Underrepresented Racially and Ethnically Faculty</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Tamara Bertrand-Jones, Professor Directing Dissertation; Lama Jaber, University Representative; Cameron Beatty, Committee Member; Ann Wofford, Committee Member.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Tamara Bertrand-Jones, Professor Directing Dissertation; Lama Jaber, University Representative; Cameron Beatty, Committee Member; Ann Wofford, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001254">
      <topic>Educational leadership</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">KentSmith_fsu_0071E_18717</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Education</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
