<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Exploring the Relationship of Hope, Metacognition, and the Practices of L2 Teachers during Covid-19</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-6121-9290</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Obando</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Gabriel</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2006073243">
      <namePart type="family">Southerland</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sherry A.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1962-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/akhurshid">
      <namePart type="family">Khurshid</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ayesha</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/akhurshid">
      <namePart type="family">Kurshid</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ayesha</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/phiver">
      <namePart type="family">Hiver</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Philip V.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2008049381">
      <namePart type="family">Cabell</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sonia Q.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>School of Teacher Education</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (193 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >This work was designed to provide insight into how a disaster of historical proportions, in this case the COVID pandemic, influenced the work foreign language (L2) teachers in an English as a foreign language (EFL) setting. The research was situated within the framework of positive psychology (Seligman, 2011), with the investigation of the interactions of hope, metacognition, and teaching practices. In this work, Hope was understood to be a cognitive construct that refers to setting goals, finding pathways to achieve those goals, and using agency to persevere in those paths or find alternative ones (Snyder, 2002, 2005, 2018). This research hypothesized that the levels of hope experienced by L2 teachers were connected with other events in the classroom. The questions addressed in this research include the following: 1. What is the relationship between hope, metacognition, and foreign language teachers' practice during a period of intense global difficulty? 2. Is L2 teacher metacognition a mediating variable between hope and teacher practices? 3. What other aspects of L2 teacher hope, L2 teacher metacognition, and L2 teacher practices can be identified through teachers' reports of their teaching experiences during a period of intense global difficulty? Within an explanatory sequential mixed methods design, and using Likert surveys and interviews, I examined whether the levels of teacher hope, teacher metacognition and teacher practices were associated. The instruments used in in this research were the dispositional hope scale (DHS) (Snyder et al., 1991), the Language Teacher Metacognitive Inventory (LTMI) (Hiver et al., 2021; Jiang et al., 2016), and the Postsecondary Instructional Practices Survey (PIPS) (Walter et al., 2016). Interviews were conducted to provide complementary evidence of teacher hope levels, metacognition, and teacher practices of English as a Foreign Language (EFL) teachers during COVID-19. The High Leverage Teaching practices proposed by Glisan and Donato (2017) complemented the interview in regard to teacher practices as they supplement the 10 macrostrategies introduced by Kumaravadivelu (2006). The research questions were analyzed following a factorial confirmative approach, in which the components of each of the surveys were used to build the constructs they represent, and hypothesis were tested on them. This analysis included an exploratory factor analysis to examine internal reliability and a subsequent confirmatory factor analysis to do the actual testing of the underlying factor structure existence. Afterwards, the mediation analysis was achieved by fitting a SEM model and contrast the pathways among L2 teacher, hope, L2 teacher metacognition, and L2 teacher practices. Teacher interviews complemented the quantitative results, as four the four themes that emerged from the qualitative analysis (i.e., Foreign language teacher goals and pathway thinking, Foreign Language Teachers' Coping Strategies, Teachers' Metacognitive Classroom Experience, and Interaction in the Foreign Language Class) provided additional insights from participating teachers. Structural equation modeling suggested that L2 teacher metacognition is a significant mediator of the relationship structure between hope and instructional practices for the population under study. These findings speak to a connection between teacher hope, teacher metacognition, and teacher practices for L2 teachers during a period of social upheaval, something that can pave the way for other researchers working with teachers in different disciplines and during different periods of time. An important conclusion from this study was that understanding these constructs separately, their components and their connection may influence how teachers think about their profession with a view of improving of what they do in the classroom. Finally, tertiary teacher preparation institutions may be encouraged to measure these constructs in order to target interventions to influence how teachers think about their profession with a view of improvement. Keywords: teacher hope, teacher metacognition, teacher practices</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the School of Teacher Education in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">December 15, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">teacher hope, teacher metacognition, teacher practices</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Sherry A. Southerland, Professor Directing Dissertation; Ayesha Khurshid, University Representative; Phil Hiver, Committee Member; Sonia Cabell, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989">
      <topic>Education</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85074518">
      <topic>Language and languages</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Obando_fsu_0071E_18540</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Teacher Education</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
