<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Integrating Research into Conservation</title>
      <subTitle>Using Satellite Telemetry and Population Monitoring to Inform the Management of Hawksbill Turtles in Brazil</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-0696-329X</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Santos</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Armando Jose Barsante</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mfuentes">
      <namePart type="family">Fuentes</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Mariana</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/sburgess">
      <namePart type="family">Burgess</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Scott C.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/simona.ceriani">
      <namePart type="family">Ceriani</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Simona A.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dgrubbs2">
      <namePart type="family">Grubbs</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">R. Dean</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mhuettel">
      <namePart type="family">Huettel</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Markus</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n81122985">
      <namePart type="family">MacDonald</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ian R. (Ian Rosman)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (186 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Marine ecosystems are increasingly threatened by human activities, highlighting the urgent need for effective conservation strategies. This dissertation focuses on the hawksbill turtle (Eretmochelys imbricata) in Brazil as a case study to enhance marine conservation efforts. Recognized as keystone species for their ecological significance and classified as Critically Endangered by the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN), the charismatic flagship species, hawksbill turtle, serve as sentinel, important indicator for the health of marine biodiversity. Utilizing satellite telemetry and population monitoring, key demographic parameters and spatial ecology of nesting hawksbill turtles were investigated. The utilization distribution by tracked turtles overlapped with Marine Protected Areas (MPAs) and the potential threats, offered insights into broader marine conservation strategies. The second chapter advances our understanding of marine turtle population dynamics by refining the accuracy of demographic parameter estimates, specifically clutch frequency, which is pivotal for assessing marine turtle populations. Such parameter is broadly used to estimate number of individual nesting females based on the total number of nests, which often times is the only information available. In addition, this chapter demonstrate the significant impact of the presence of transient turtles on these estimates and are informative for study designs that aim estimate total number of nesting females within a season or for the population at large. The third chapter breaks down their nesting, foraging, and migratory behaviors to inform conservation management. A significant contribution of this work is the identification of key migratory corridors and foraging areas, particularly for the subpopulation from Rio Grande do Norte, Brazil, highlighting the need for spatially explicit conservation goals and targets. The effectiveness of Brazil's coastal MPAs in protecting the vital habitats for nesting hawksbill turtles was assessed. The findings reveal mismatches in the current MPA network, leading to recommendations for strategic MPA expansion and management, emphasizing ecological-scale approaches over political boundaries to accommodate the species' extensive migratory patterns. The research advocates for MPAs to not only cover high-use areas identified through telemetry but also to implement protection levels tailored to the hawksbill turtles' specific needs. Furthermore, the fourth chapter provides a nuanced understanding of hawksbill turtle internesting behavior, using a novel approach to discretize hidden behaviors during this critical period. Besides evidencing high fidelity to nesting beaches and residence areas, mapping the behaviors provided essential insights into their vulnerability to specific threats, including vessel strikes and accidental capture in fishing gear. It proposes evidence-based strategies to enhance MPA effectiveness, integrating technological advancements with conservation biology to inform policy and management decisions. The study's findings underscore the importance of adaptive management strategies, responsive to the evolving understanding of hawksbill turtle ecology. Beyond hawksbill turtles, the research offers a framework for applying similar conservation strategies to other marine species, underlining the potential for species-specific efforts to catalyze broader and effective environmental management and conservation. The dissertation calls for continued research and adaptive management in response to the dynamic nature of marine ecosystems and emerging threats, highlighting the role of science in effective conservation policies.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 20, 2022.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Adaptive management, Behavioral Ecology, Conservation Policy, Conservation strategies, Demographic analysis, Marine spatial planning</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Mariana Fuentes, Professor Directing Dissertation; Scott Burgess, University Representative; Simona Ceriani, Committee Member; Ralph Dean Grubbs, II, Committee Member; Markus Huettel, Committee Member; Ian MacDonald, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081138">
      <topic>Marine biology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Santos_fsu_0071E_18547</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
