<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Impact of Effort and Expectancy on the P300</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-7786-5948</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Simon</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jessica R.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2014091561">
      <namePart type="family">Proudfit</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Greg Hajcak</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mswanbrowbecker">
      <namePart type="family">Becker</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Martin Swanbrow</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/eckel">
      <namePart type="family">Eckel</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lisa A.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2001127053">
      <namePart type="family">Schmidt</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Norman B.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mkabbaj">
      <namePart type="family">Kabbaj</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Mohamed</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Psychology</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (100 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Motivationally significant stimuli activate motivational systems to support perception and action. Rewards are naturally occurring motivationally salient stimuli that activate approach behaviors, for example, effort for a reward. Two theories have been proposed regarding the impact of effort on subsequent reward salience. Effort discounting theories suggest that effort is costly and makes the outcome less salient. Comparatively, effort justification theories posit that the reward is more salient after exerting effort. Existing literature has supported both theories; however, the methods used (e.g., fMRI, behavior) were not temporally precise, so we extend this work by using electroencephalogram (EEG) to better understand the sequential effects of effort on reward processing. The P300 event-related potential has been used as a measure of motivational significance and is related to reward processing. The P300 is also associated with task relevance (experimentally manipulated significance) and stimulus expectations. Literature shows that P300 amplitude to reward feedback is increased following high compared to low amounts of effort, supporting effort justification theories or increased salience of the feedback after effort completion. Critically, however, these studies have failed to control for subjective stimulus expectations known to influence P300 amplitude. It may be that outcome feedback is more unexpected when more effort is required. When less effort is required, there may be no differences between expected and unexpected stimuli because participants can predict relatively well when the cue may be presented. To investigate the influence of both effort and expectancy on P300 amplitude to reward feedback we created a monetary reward task that varied effort and waiting, high and low amounts (duration) of effort (waiting), and expectancy. Expectancy was manipulated by having some trials countdown the number of presses left (countdown) as subjects exerted effort or waited, so participants know when the reward was coming. Alternatively, some trials stayed static (no countdown) and gave no information about upcoming reward presentation. From this task we also investigated mean differences in behavioral response rate, reaction time, and trial duration for effortful trials, and related the P300 amplitude to the behavioral measures. The initial study focused on these within subject differences, but it is known that effort for reward is disrupted in various psychological and neurological disorders, especially depression where anhedonia is a symptom that reflects problematic consummation and motivation for rewards. Indeed, P300 amplitude is consistently decreased in people with depression or anhedonia and may be a good biomarker of motivational salience deficits in people with anhedonia symptomology. Thus, we investigated relationships between P300 amplitude and self-reported anhedonia symptoms. We demonstrated that the amount of effort or waiting required influenced P300 amplitude—high effort amounts or waiting durations had larger P300 amplitudes than low effort or waiting, which varied by expectations. When subjects knew when to expect reward presentation (countdown), there was no difference between high and low amounts of either effort or waiting. Comparatively, when expectations were violated (no countdown), there was a significant difference between high and low amounts (durations) of effort (waiting). Additionally, effort for reward processing seems to be distinct from reward processing following waiting as P300 amplitudes were larger following effort conditions. The present study also demonstrated task effects on behavioral reaction times; when more effort was required, participants were quicker to start the trial, and participants that were faster at pressing across the task (shorter trial durations) had lower P300 amplitudes. Finally, individuals with lower experiences of pleasure or heightened anhedonia symptoms had blunted P300 amplitudes following effort compared to waiting conditions. These results provide evidence for effort justification theories and are interpreted within the motivational significance framework, which suggests salient stimuli in the form of surprising, unexpected, and task relevant reward stimuli may enhance attention and/or facilitate subsequent action by eliciting a larger P300 amplitude waveform. Moreover, the P300 was attenuated to reward feedback during effort conditions in individuals experiencing anhedonia symptomology suggesting disrupted processing of motivationally salient reward stimuli. Our results call for future investigation of expectations on reward processing in addition to task relevance.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Psychology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 13, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Effort, Expectation, Motivational Signficance, P300, salience, Surprise</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Greg Hajcak, Professor Directing Dissertation; Martin Swanbrow Becker, University Representative; Lisa Eckel, Committee Member; N. Brad Schmidt, Committee Member; Mohamed Kabbaj, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91006099">
      <topic>Neurosciences</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85108425">
      <topic>Psychobiology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Simon_fsu_0071E_18052</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Psychology</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
