<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Associations between Objectively Measured Habitual Physical and Sedentary Activity, the P300 and Depression in Older Adults</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-2167-324X</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Thompson</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Brittney</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2014091561">
      <namePart type="family">Proudfit</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Greg Hajcak</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2005015125">
      <namePart type="family">Patrick</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Christopher J.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n84205728">
      <namePart type="family">Charness</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Neil</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Psychology</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (58 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Deficits in cognitive processing, as measured by P300 activity, have been noted in older adults struggling with depressive symptoms, thus understanding factors that may influence cognitive processing are an important area of interest in the search to improve quality of life during older adulthood. Activity levels, such as physical activity (PA) and sedentary behavior, is one such factor. Although literature pertaining to the associations between PA levels, sedentary behavior and depression in older adults appear abundant, much of the recent work investigates the relationship between interventions, such as bouts of exercise throughout a week, workout types, and fitness levels. There is an evident gap in knowledge on the influence habitual activity levels (day-to-day activity) plays on the cognitive aspects of depression in older adults. The goal of our study was to utilize neurophysiological measures collected during a Go/No-Go task, in addition to accelerometers, which collect continuous data on habitual activity levels and self-report measures to investigate the relationship cross-sectional relationship between P300 amplitude and latency, depression symptoms and objectively measured habitual PA in a sample of older adults (n=75). Although no association was found between P300 activity and depression symptoms, heighten depressive symptoms were found to have a significant relationship with longer periods of prolonged sedentary behavior (sedentary bouts, SBs), but not overall sedentary activity. Furthermore, increased No-Go P300 amplitude was associated with higher levels of Daily Lifestyle Activity (e.g. slow walking, grocery shopping) as well as, higher daily incidences of prolonged periods of sedentary and moderate-vigorous activity (MVPA). Moreover, Go-Infrequent latency was shorter among participants who had longer periods of MVPA. Age was found to be associated with increased P300 latency as well as, habitual activity levels, such that older members of the sample engaged in lighter habitual activity and less MVPA. Exploratory analysis revealed subjective reports of time spent walking and in MVPA per day were associated with objectively measured Daily MVPA and prolonged periods of MVPA. In contrast, subjective reports of sitting per day were not associated with objectively measured sedentary activity, showing a potential limitation of subjective measures. Taken together, the current project demonstrates the negative influence prolonged periods of sedentary activity has both on depressive symptoms and cognitive processing as measured through P300 activity, while exploratory analysis illuminated the importance of objectively measured habitual activity over subjective reports as a potential tool to better understand the elements of day-to-day life that impact cognitive and psychological functioning of older adults.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Psychology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Science.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 5, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Depression, EEG, Older Adults, Physical activity</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Greg Hajcak, Professor Directing Thesis; Christopher Patrick, Committee Member; Neil Charness, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027067">
      <topic>Clinical psychology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Thompson_fsu_0071N_18260</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Science</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Psychology</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
