<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Paradigms of Parenting</title>
      <subTitle>Intensive Parenting across Identities Explored through Mixed Methodology</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-6860-6613</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Unhjem</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lexie</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lmcwey">
      <namePart type="family">McWey</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lenore M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mradey">
      <namePart type="family">Radey</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Melissa</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2019122471">
      <namePart type="family">Wu</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Qiong</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Professor of human sciences)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jkimmes">
      <namePart type="family">Kimmes</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jonathan G. (Jonathan Gene)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2022083038">
      <namePart type="family">Reynolds</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jamila Evans</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Human Development and Family Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (120 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Intensive parenting involves parents centering their children's needs, spending most of their free time engaging with them, and following the advice of child experts. Although most studies on intensive parenting have been qualitative, one group of researchers developed a quantitative measure for intensive parenting attitudes called the Intensive Parenting Attitudes Questionnaire (IPAQ). Studies have shown mixed results in terms of intensive parenting attitudes being linked with positive and negative outcomes. However, scholars have pointed to this construct as being rooted in White, middle-class ideals that are not necessarily accurate for parents with other identities and the IPAQ has failed to show measurement invariance across racial groups. The current literature lacks representation in understanding the experiences and effects of intensive parenting in racially and economically diverse populations, therefore, it is reasonable to question whether intensive parenting is a valid construct for all parents. This dissertation aimed to discover the extent to which this concept may or may not be inclusive for parents who do not identify as White and/or middle-class. Through theories of intensive parenting and intersectionality, this dissertation utilized a convergent mixed-method design to test the content validity of the IPAQ through a confirmatory factor analysis and measurement invariance analyses. Additionally, through semi-structured interviews, this study aimed to discover how key domains of intensive parenting were described. A racially, ethnically, and economically diverse sample of parents was recruited resulting in 465 participants for quantitative analyses, and 15 parents were selected for qualitative interviews. This study aimed to answer the following research questions: Among a racially and economically diverse sample of parents, what is the content validity of the IPAQ? And among a racially and economically diverse sample of parents, how are key domains of intensive parenting described? Through the confirmatory factor analysis, results indicated that the data did not fit the five-factor model of the IPAQ well. Seven alternative models were run to find better model fit and with one of these models, measurement invariance analyses were conducted. These tests revealed that the alternative model only showed configural invariance across racial groups but demonstrated scalar invariance across racial groups. Qualitative results suggested that intensive parenting is a relevant concept in a racially and economically diverse sample, as descriptions of the key domains were consistent with previous literature. The quantitative and qualitative data were merged through an integrative analysis to discover how results converged, diverged, and were expanded upon. These findings highlighted how contextual variables, such as race and socioeconomic status, played a key role in the quantitative and qualitative results. While intensive parenting appears to be an important construct in a racially and economically diverse sample, more research is needed to fully understand how to quantitatively measure intensive parenting attitudes, specifically for racially marginalized populations.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Human Development and Family Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 25, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Lenore M. McWey, Professor Directing Dissertation; Melissa Radey, University Representative; Qiong Wu, Committee Member; Jonathan Kimmes, Committee Member; Jamila Holcomb, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86000709">
      <topic>Mental health counseling</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Unhjem_fsu_0071E_18583</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Family and Child Sciences</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
