<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Discovery, Exploration, and Evolution of Treefrog Biofluorescence</title>
      <nonSort>The</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-6523-3030</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Whitcher</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Courtney</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/elemmon">
      <namePart type="family">Lemmon</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Emily C.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/marbeitman">
      <namePart type="family">Arbeitman</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michelle N. (Michelle Nina)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86861195">
      <namePart type="family">Travis</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Joseph</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1953-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/eduval">
      <namePart type="family">DuVal</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Emily H.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/eduval">
      <namePart type="family">Duval</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Emily</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kahughes">
      <namePart type="family">Hughes</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kimberly A.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1960-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Biological Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (178 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Visual communication plays an important role in the evolution of organisms, as selection processes often rely on the organism's physical appearance. For example, mate choice—often by females selecting the most attractive males—can lead to the evolution of brighter or more exaggerated patterns. However, there are instances where organisms have evolved physical attributes beneficial for sexual selection but costly in terms of energy expenditure or increased predation risk. A particularly valuable communication channel, then, would be one invisible to predators but helpful for identifying potential mates. Signals produced via the mechanism of fluorescence have been proposed to be such a channel. Although biologists have described biofluorescence in a diversity of taxa, there have been few systematic efforts to document the extent of biofluorescence within a taxonomic group or to investigate its general significance. These signals were recently discovered in amphibians. The goal of my dissertation was to: (1) assess the diversity of frog biofluorescence, (2) examine the function of fluorescence in predation on frogs, and to (3) reconstruct a highly supported phylogeny for a treefrog genus upon which we can (4) test for accelerated speciation of biofluorescence lineages within one treefrog clade. First, through a field survey across South America, I discovered and documented patterns of biofluorescence in tropical amphibians. Through these efforts, I more than tripled the number of species that have been tested for this trait and added representatives from previously untested anuran families. Fluorescence was ubiquitous; I recorded at least a low-level fluorescent signal from every individual I tested. I found evidence for ecological tuning (i.e., the specific adaptation of a signal to the environment in which it is received) of the novel anuran biofluorescent signals. For the majority (56.58%) of Anura species tested, the fluorescence excitation peak matches the wavelengths most abundant at twilight, the light environment in which most frog species are active. Additionally, biofluorescence emission spans both wavelengths of low availability in twilight and the peak sensitivity of green-sensitive rods in the anuran eye, likely increasing contrast of this signal for a conspecific receiver. With evidence of tuning to the ecology and sensory systems of frogs, my results suggest frog biofluorescence is likely functioning in anuran communication. After demonstrating the significance of frog biofluorescence as a potential signal, the next critical line of inquiry was to examine who is receiving the signal: potential predators, mates, or both. I began to test this through a case study experimentally testing the function of frog fluorescence in predation of a local treefrog species. Over half of the studies documenting biofluorescence in the last century suggest this fluorescent signal may affect predation; however, to date, only one other experimental study has tested this hypothesis. To address this question, I first quantified the spectral characteristics of a novel biofluorescence pattern in the Cope's Gray Treefrog, Hyla chrysoscelis. In both sexes of this species, the fluorescent signal is concentrated in an area that contains a proposed aposematic pattern that may warn predators of the frog's toxic secretions. I hypothesized that the biofluorescent trait may increase the conspicuousness of this pattern and enable the frogs to deter predators more effectively. I then tested this prediction by conducting a clay model field experiment to assess differences in predation attempts on fluorescent versus non-fluorescent H. chrysoscelis models by various predator types. I found no effect of biofluorescence on the overall presence, type, or location of predation, suggesting that biofluorescence alone does not act as an antipredator signal of H. chrysoscelis. This study represents one of the first attempts to experimentally test the effect of biofluorescence on predation in any organism and the first to do so in amphibians. Further work is needed to explore the role of this trait in predation in other systems and to investigate alternative functions for the biofluorescent signal in H. chrysoscelis. The final goal of my dissertation was to examine the evolution of biofluorescence across an amphibian clade. To do so, I first reconstructed, and time-calibrated, a highly supported phylogeny for one treefrog genus upon which we can test for trait-dependent accelerated speciation rates. With 108 recognized species, Dendropsophus is one of the most diverse genera of tropical treefrogs in the Western Hemisphere. Despite the broad distribution of the clade across Central and South America, little is known about the biogeographic origins and expansion of the group or how key life history traits have evolved in this taxon. I reconstructed a phylogeny of Dendropsophus based on 432 nuclear loci for 78 taxa (72% of species) obtained using anchored hybrid enrichment. I estimated divergence times within the clade to reconstruct the biogeographic history of the genus to test alternative models of dispersal. I also assessed the evolution of egg deposition mode and examined correlations with speciation rate and the extent of biogeographic expansions. I recovered a well-resolved phylogeny with very strong support at 92% of the nodes. I found evidence that the genus likely originated approximately 57 mya, occupying the Eastern Highlands and Amazonian-Orinocan Lowland, and underwent multiple expansions into the surrounding Central and South American biomes. The origin of the genus predates the beginning of the Andean uplift in western South America. The best supported biogeographic hypothesis for the Dendropsophus clade is one of unconstrained dispersal between the Eastern Highlands and Amazonian Basin. My results suggest that the majority of Dendropsophus groups originated via range expansion speciation events that occurred during the Andean uplift. Overall, my phylogenomic data provide clear resolution of the evolutionary relationships among species of Dendropsophus. My study provides insight into the biogeographic origin and expansion of the clade and demonstrates that the dispersal of this group was not as heavily constrained by a changing ecological history as previously hypothesized. The evolution from an aquatic to terrestrial egg deposition mode was not correlated with speciation rate or the extent of biogeographic expansions. Given Dendropsophus is one of the most broadly ranging genera in South and Central America, my highly supported tree will be an invaluable tool for future clade-specific and comparative studies investigating the evolution of life history traits, mating behaviors, and ecological associations throughout these regions. Finally, I mapped the evolution of biofluorescence across the Dendropsophus treefrog genus. I utilized ancestral state reconstruction to examine the evolutionary history of biofluorescent traits (intensity, area, and color) within the genus. Dendropsophus is a widespread, diverse South American genus, and studies have examined clade-specific drivers of diversification, but only within the context of ecological constraints and not color pattern divergence. The biofluorescent patterns I discovered in Dendropsophus range from widespread, full body coverage to location-specific patches. Hence, my goals of this study were to (1) map these traits across the recently published, highly supported, time calibrated Dendropsophus phylogeny based on anchored hybrid enrichment data, and (2) use state-dependent diversification models to determine if biofluorescence parameters affect speciation rate to ascertain whether visual (fluorescence) signals have contributed to an accelerated rate of speciation within the genus. My study provides the first insight into the evolutionary history of biofluorescence in Dendropsophus frogs. My results suggest a biofluorescent ancestor for the clade with an intense, widespread, green emission phenotype. I found evidence of a strong phylogenetic signal between the traits of fluorescence and the Dendropsophus phylogeny. Finally, fluorescent intensity, but not emission color, influenced speciation rate in the genus; and the influence of fluorescent area is still unresolved. Dendropsophus lineages with greater than 10% biofluorescent intensity had a speciation rate over 7.2 times faster than the speciation rate for lineages with less than 10% fluorescent intensity. The combination of my findings suggests there is an adaptive function of frog fluorescence for intraspecific communication. I found (1) evidence for sensory drive of the frog fluorescent signal, (2) this signal meets criteria of ecological significance for intraspecific communication, (3) no effect of fluorescence on predation of frogs, and (4) a correlation between treefrog fluorescent intensity and an increased speciation rate. Together, these results highlight the potential importance of this recently discovered trait and the need for further exploration of this novel signal to determine its function in anuran communication.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Biological Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 22, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Emily Lemmon, Professor Directing Dissertation; Michelle Arbeitman, University Representative; Joseph Travis, Committee Member; Emily DuVal, Committee Member; Kim Hughes, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014203">
      <topic>Biology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Whitcher_fsu_0071E_18606</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Biological Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
