<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Tablas De Sarhua</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Indigenous Aesthetics in the Context of Contemporary Peruvian Art</mods:subTitle>
      <mods:nonSort>The</mods:nonSort>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Germana Roquez</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Gabriela</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2010041982">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Carrasco</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Michael</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2003097651">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Herrera</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Robinson A.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1966-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2013043288">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Niell</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Paul B.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1976-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n92121683">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Bearor</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Karen A. (Karen Anne)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1950-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2013033964">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Dowell</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kristin L.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Fine Arts</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Art History</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (332 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>In this dissertation I examine the Tablas de Sarhua, paintings on board made by the people of the Andean peasant community of Sarhua, through an art history lens informed by the discourse on indigeneity and decoloniality. Since at least the nineteenth century, Sarhuinos make paintings on planks of wood on the occasion of the construction of a new house to record the family members who contributed to its construction. The paintings depict not only the people involved, but also a Catholic saint, the image of the sun, and a text in Spanish. The main purpose of these objects is to represent and therefore maintain systems of reciprocity and social cohesion within the community. Beginning in the 1970s, Sarhuino migrants living in Lima created a new kind of Tabla intended for the urban audience. The new Tablas, painted on rectangular wooden panels, initially depicted costumbrista scenes of rural Sarhua and later came to also address themes of social injustice and migrant life in Lima. Their enthralling story speaks to how objects made to commemorate social links within a rural town were transformed initially into paintings intended for the urban public and now have become embraced by the contemporary art world. The Tablas de Sarhua have followed a path similar to other forms of Indigenous art worldwide. However, like other Andean art objects linked to rural circuits, the Tablas and their rich history have received attention from the global art system only in ways still tainted by antiquated definitions of modernity and flawed the categories of craft, folk and tourist art. In this dissertation I analyze the Tablas de Sarhua within a new theoretical framework, one that brings the discipline of art history to bear on this material, and that positions the Tablas within the broader discourse on Indigenous art. I reconsider the aesthetic production of non-Western societies as responses and intrinsic components of modernity and contemporaneity. In order to study the paintings of Sarhua within their own systemic development, one of the main objectives of this dissertation is to unpack the way these paintings respond to colonial dynamics, both in Sarhua and in Lima, and to demonstrate the Sarhuino painters' complex and active negotiation of power through the adaptation of their old practices and the appropriation and re-elaboration of modern Western aesthetics and knowledge to respond to and challenge colonial hegemony. In this dissertation I focus on five main topics spanning the changing contexts of the Tablas. I contend that reassessing their history, leads to a better appreciation of their contemporary manifestation. First, I tie the origins of the Tablas to the nineteenth century transit from colonial to Republican times, a period when other forms of peasant arts developed in the Andes. Then, I track the specific ways in which the Tablas coalesced through the complex relationship between objects, images, Sarhuino practices, and social spaces. Third, I demonstrate how Sarhuino artists in the capital city of Lima reshaped their old aesthetics and appropriated visual elements of the urban environment to negotiate with systems of political and social power. I contend that Sarhuinos created a style legible to urban audiences to communicate their own concerns, while at the same time they found in the Tablas a way to reinforce their group identity. Fourth, I analyze how Tablas are linked to other visual arts created in Lima in the 1970s and how they circulated through different regimes of value, being considered as folk-art, tourist art, and art pieces. I deconstruct the static categories attached to Tablas and demonstrate the shifting and contested discourses and values constructed about them. Finally, I look at the role of workshops in the development of the new paintings of Sarhua and at the individual agencies and diverse goals of the contemporary Sarhuino painters. I also examine the increasing role play by Sarhuino women artists and how some of them are responding to the hegemonic discourse, not only in terms of class and race, but also of gender, challenging the patriarchal social order from their particular situation and from there contributing to re-shape Peruvian contemporary art.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Art History in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 14, 2021.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Andes, Contemporary Art, Decoloniality, Indigenous Art, Latin America, Race, class, and gender</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Michael D. Carrasco, Professor Directing Dissertation; Robinson Herrera, University Representative; Paul Niell, Committee Member; Karen Bearor, Committee Member; Kristin Dowel, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007488">
      <mods:topic>Art</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>History</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85074879">
      <mods:geographic>Latin America</mods:geographic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">2021_Summer_GermanaRoquez_fsu_0071E_16670</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Art History</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-01-31T17:03:20.741646-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
