<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Boy Man</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Multiple Literacies and Navigating Black Southern Boyhood in the Works of Kiese Laymon</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-2417-0883</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Johnson</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kenneth L.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="termsOfAddress">II</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016135651">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Gaines</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Alisha</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007084452">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Cuyler</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Antonio C. (Antonio Christopher)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1978-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2015038714">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Lathan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Rhea Estelle</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1961-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2006055609">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Howard</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Ravi</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of English</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (152 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Boy Man: Multiple Literacies and Narrating Black Southern Boyhood in the Works of Kiese Laymon focuses on Mississippi-born author Kiese Laymon's three published manuscripts: Long Division, a novel; How to Slowly Kill Yourself and Others in America, a collection of letters and personal essays; and Heavy: An American Memoir. Through these three works, Laymon tells his and his characters' stories, employing multiple literacies to allow himself and his characters navigate the minefield of the United States South, adolescence, and transgenerational trauma on the journey toward growth and healing. These literacies align with the New Literacy Studies movement, a concept of literacy embracing one's culture and the expression thereof beyond historical conceptions of literacy as the ability to read and write. This project focuses on Laymon's use of these literacies – cultural, cipher, and language literacy – as Laymon's way of critiquing systemic, monolithic views about Black boys and reimagining new pathways of education, maturation, and cultural expression. This project argues two things: first, Laymon's writing champions the importance of multiple literacies beyond reading and writing to introduce and demystify societal misinformation about the abilities of Black boys to be rational, intelligent, and emotional human beings; second, Laymon's work inserts necessary conversations about 21st century Black southern boyhood, advocating for a more careful and nuanced discussion of the experiences, voices, and realities of Black boys in the South. Ultimately, I argue for Laymon's work to be recognized as canonical for his ability to write across and transform multiple fields of study, inclusive of (but not limited to) southern studies, Black masculinity studies, literacy studies, hip-hop studies, education, and race. Chapter One analyzes Laymon's lone novel, Long Division, and interprets his use of character doubles as a reimagination of Atlanta rap supergroup OutKast. Specifically, Laymon's fictive "Can You Use That Word in a Sentence" is a reimagination of OutKast's win and disruption at the 1995 Source Awards. Through the implementation of cultural literacies, Laymon's narrator Citoyen "City" Coldson and antagonist LaVander Peeler, and OutKast rhetorically disrupt hegemonic structures to reject stigmas of Black boy illiteracy and Black southernness as inherently inferior. Chapter Two interrogates the necessary curation of Black boy spaces within education settings. Focusing on Laymon's essay "Hip-Hop Stole My Southern Black Boy" from How to Slowly Kill Yourself and Others in America and lunchtime sentence battles between City and LaVander in Long Division, I argue that Laymon uses what I call "cipher literacies" as means for himself and his characters to engage in vocal expressions of literacy, rejecting historicized performances of literacy in education, and critique institutional assumptions of Black boys' illiteracy in education. Through these in-school ciphers, Black boys carve out exclusive space to find their voices, reinscribe and reinforce identity, express their mastery of multiple languages, and subvert their assumed illiteracy. Chapter Three addresses the critical lack of conversations centered on Black men's bodies. In analyzing Heavy, I argue Laymon's memoir is necessary for conversations around Black men's body dysmorphia and disordered eating, the desirability of fat Black men, and the need for Black men's body literacy. Chapter Four examines Laymon's use of letter writing in How to Slowly Kill Yourself and Others in America as a source of reconciliation and therapy for himself and other Black men. Laymon's insertion of letters at the beginning and in the middle of a book of essays creates a chamber of epistolary warnings and echoes: In writing to his deceased Uncle Jimmy, he reconciles with missed opportunities to show love to his "warning" against making poor choices; in "The Echo," Laymon creates space for he and other Black men to practice the love and support they desperately need.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of English in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 1, 2021.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">African American Literature, Black Boyhood, Black Literacy, Black Masculinity, Kiese Laymon, Southern Studies</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Alisha M. Gaines, Professor Directing Dissertation; Antonio C. Cuyler, University Representative; Rhea Estelle Lathan, Committee Member; Ravi Howard, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077507">
      <mods:topic>Literature</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001992">
      <mods:topic>African Americans</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Study and teaching</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">2021_Summer_JohnsonII_fsu_0071E_16671</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>English</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-01-31T17:03:20.741646-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
