<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Effects of a Single Music-Assisted Mindfulness Relaxation (MAMR) and Psychoeducation Session with Electronic Resource on Wellbeing of Informal Caregivers</mods:title>
      <mods:nonSort>The</mods:nonSort>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Steiner</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Adrienne Claire</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lgooding">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Gooding</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Lori F. (Lori Fogus)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/bholzman">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Holzman</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Bruce</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n91075721">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Standley</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jayne M.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kvanweelden">
      <mods:namePart type="family">VanWeelden</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kimberly D.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2006097242">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Carr</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Dawn C.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Music</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (97 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Various health conditions, and/or aging can result in the need for care assistance. The number of Americans who need care assistance has grown over the past several decades, with the amount expected to increase as the number of individuals entering older adulthood rises. Informal caregivers are those who assist others with medical or other personal tasks without pay. Due to the complex demands of caregiving, informal caregivers often report high levels of stress and decreases in psychosocial wellbeing, especially when compared to those who are not caregivers. Research has indicated the need for support interventions to address informal caregivers' needs, yet the unique needs of this population have posed challenges in developing appropriate and accessible resources. The purpose of this dissertation was to investigate the effects of a single music therapy session utilizing a music-assisted mindfulness relaxation intervention with psychoeducation session and electronic resource on psychosocial wellbeing of informal caregivers of adults with chronic health needs. Intervention data collection sessions were conducted at an adult day facility, community wellness clinic, and community church sites, and were led by a board-certified music therapist. The intervention facilitated was a music-assisted relaxation exercise utilizing research-supported live guitar accompaniment, guided breathing prompts, imagery, and a spoken mindfulness loving-kindness meditation. Following the music-assisted mindfulness relaxation (MAMR), a psychoeducation discussion was facilitated to educate participants about the techniques experienced and provide strategies for incorporating into daily life practices. Participants were given an electronic recording of the same MAMR done in the intervention session and prompted to use the resource in their preferred manner over a two-week time period. Participants, who were adults aged 62-89 and provided assistance to an individual over the age of 50 for at least five hours per week, for at least the past three months. Perceived stress and wellbeing were measured along with participants' perception of the MAMR intervention and MAMR electronic resource. Perceived stress was measured using a researcher created tool (Likert-type scale) and wellbeing was measured using the WHO (Five) Wellbeing Index (1998 version). Subjects completed the perceived stress score before and following the intervention. The WHO wellbeing index was completed by participants prior to the intervention and two-weeks post session. Results indicated there was a significant difference between perceived stress scores prior to and following the MAMR intervention. Further analysis of perceived stress difference score indicated no difference between those who lived with the care receiver and those who did not. However, results did indicate a significant difference between those who engaged a minimum to moderate level and those who engaged at a maximum level in caregiving duties. Results of WHO wellbeing analysis also indicated a significant difference between scores from pre intervention to two-weeks post intervention. Further analysis indicated there was not a significant difference in WHO wellbeing difference scores between those who used the intervention one time or not at all, and those who used the intervention two times or more. No significant difference was found between those who lived with care receiver and those who did not, and those with minimum to moderate caregiving levels and those with maximum caregiving levels and WHO wellbeing difference scores. Participants' perception of the intervention indicated the use of several techniques when facilitating a similar music-assisted relaxation with informal caregivers in clinical music therapy practice. The outcomes of this study warrant the need for future research to determine effective ways to use this intervention with the informal caregiving population.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the College of Music in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Summer Semester 2019.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 13, 2019.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">electronic resource, informal caregivers, mindfulness, music-assisted relaxation, music therapy, wellbeing</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Lori Gooding, Professor Directing Dissertation; Bruce Holzman, University Representative; Jayne Standley, Committee Member; Kimberley VanWeelden, Committee Member; Dawn Carr, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85088796">
      <mods:topic>Music</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Instruction and study</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2019_Summer_Steiner_fsu_0071E_15342</identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Music</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2020-01-08T16:41:25.408-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
