<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<diss>
   <DISS_submission publishing_option="0" embargo_code="0" third_party_search="Y">
      <DISS_authorship>
         <DISS_author type="primary">
            <DISS_name>
               <DISS_surname>Blair</DISS_surname>
               <DISS_fname>Daneisha</DISS_fname>
               <DISS_middle/>
               <DISS_suffix/>
            </DISS_name>
            <DISS_contact type="future">
               <DISS_contact_effdt>06/28/2021</DISS_contact_effdt>
               <DISS_address>
                  <DISS_addrline>2915 Sharer Road</DISS_addrline>
                  <DISS_addrline>Apt. 1432</DISS_addrline>
                  <DISS_city>Tallahassee</DISS_city>
                  <DISS_st>FL</DISS_st>
                  <DISS_pcode>32312</DISS_pcode>
                  <DISS_country>US</DISS_country>
               </DISS_address>
               <DISS_email>db18g@my.fsu.edu</DISS_email>
               <DISS_school_email>db18g@my.fsu.edu</DISS_school_email>
            </DISS_contact>
            <DISS_citizenship/>
            <DISS_orcid/>
         </DISS_author>
      </DISS_authorship>
      <DISS_description page_count="54"
                        type="masters"
                        external_id="http://dissertations.umi.com/fsu:16741"
                        apply_for_copyright="no">
         <DISS_title>THE IMPACT OF SURFACE ROUGHNESS AND SURFACE TEMPERATURE ON THE MOTION OF THE DEEPWATER HORIZON OIL SPILL</DISS_title>
         <DISS_dates>
            <DISS_comp_date>2021-12</DISS_comp_date>
            <DISS_accept_date>01/01/2021</DISS_accept_date>
         </DISS_dates>
         <DISS_degree>M.S.</DISS_degree>
         <DISS_institution>
            <DISS_inst_code>0071</DISS_inst_code>
            <DISS_inst_name>Florida State University</DISS_inst_name>
            <DISS_inst_contact>Earth, Ocean &amp; Atmospheric Science</DISS_inst_contact>
            <DISS_processing_code>N</DISS_processing_code>
         </DISS_institution>
         <DISS_advisor>
            <DISS_name>
               <DISS_surname>Bourassa</DISS_surname>
               <DISS_fname>Mark</DISS_fname>
               <DISS_middle>A</DISS_middle>
            </DISS_name>
         </DISS_advisor>
         <DISS_cmte_member>
            <DISS_name>
               <DISS_surname>Sura</DISS_surname>
               <DISS_fname>Philips</DISS_fname>
               <DISS_middle/>
               <DISS_suffix/>
            </DISS_name>
         </DISS_cmte_member>
         <DISS_cmte_member>
            <DISS_name>
               <DISS_surname>Hart</DISS_surname>
               <DISS_fname>Robert</DISS_fname>
               <DISS_middle/>
               <DISS_suffix/>
            </DISS_name>
         </DISS_cmte_member>
         <DISS_cmte_member>
            <DISS_name>
               <DISS_surname>Parfitt</DISS_surname>
               <DISS_fname>Rhys</DISS_fname>
               <DISS_middle/>
               <DISS_suffix/>
            </DISS_name>
         </DISS_cmte_member>
         <DISS_categorization>
            <DISS_category>
               <DISS_cat_code>0557</DISS_cat_code>
               <DISS_cat_desc>Meteorology</DISS_cat_desc>
            </DISS_category>
            <DISS_keyword/>
            <DISS_language>en</DISS_language>
         </DISS_categorization>
      </DISS_description>
      <DISS_content>
         <DISS_abstract>
            <DISS_para>This study provides, to our knowledge, the first detailed analysis of how oil changes air-sea interaction in a two-way coupled model (COAWST), and how the modified surface stress and surface Ekman current change the transport of the oil. Our results highlight the substantial influences of oil-related changes in surface roughness, surface wind, surface and near surface temperature differences, boundary-layer stability, and corresponding changes in surface stress and oil transport. These results are dependent on the effectiveness of our tuning of the modeled oil concentration on the surface. These considerations are examined in part by running twin coupled modeling simulations with and without the influences of oil. Subsequently, we compare the results by using a flux model with parameterizations selected to match those selected in COAWST adapted to either ignore or account for different atmospheric/oceanic processes in calculating surface stress. This approach investigates the effects of oil separately on boundary-layer stability, surface wind, and surface roughness and how those conditions impact surface stress. The model results find that surface stress changes due to oil-related damping of surface roughness are always negative in the absence of changes to model input parameters (i.e., wind speed and boundary-layer stability). However, oil-related changes to 10 m wind speed appear to play a much dominant role than oil-related changes in roughness in the changes in stress. The wind speed changes due to reduced surface friction (which increase stress) and due to changes in stability (which increase or decrease stress). We find that oil-related changes in boundary-layer stability play a dominant role in the changes in stress. This finding indicates that the vast majority of the changes in modeled stress are due to the changes in modeled stability and wind. This finding is contrary to the assumption by an idealized study where the changes in scatterometer observed roughness were assumed to be entirely due to damping of the roughness by oil. Finally, the results indicate that the oil-related changes in surface roughness, surface wind, and boundary-layer stability combined to result in surface stress changes are not large enough to cause a major impact on the surface current and oil transport. The results from this study indicate that the feedbacks from the surface oil presence to the oil movement itself are minor for forecasting the transportation of the oil due to the small impact on surface stress unless the fractional oil coverage is much greater than found in this study.</DISS_para>
         </DISS_abstract>
         <DISS_binary type="PDF">Blair_fsu_0071N_16741.pdf</DISS_binary>
      </DISS_content>
      <DISS_restriction/>
      <DISS_repository>
         <DISS_version/>
         <DISS_agreement_decision_date/>
         <DISS_acceptance>0</DISS_acceptance>
         <DISS_delayed_release/>
         <DISS_access_option/>
      </DISS_repository>
      <DISS_creative_commons_license>
         <DISS_abbreviation/>
      </DISS_creative_commons_license>
   </DISS_submission>
</diss>
