<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Friendship or Blame</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>How to Publicly Respond When the Immoral Is Your Friend</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-8629-2021</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Isern-Mas</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Carme</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr90006375">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Clarke</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Randolph K.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/awestlund">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Westlund</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Andrea C. (Andrea Carol)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Philosophy</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (36 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Given a friend who has committed a grave moral transgression against someone else, how should one react to them in the public sphere? In this paper, I focus on cases of unacknowledged, grave transgressions with a human victim, involving public figures. Based on the impact of expressions of blame and expressions of friendship in the public sphere, I argue that in the public sphere one should not show friendship with a moral transgressor; instead, one should publicly blame their friend. The kind of blame at stake in these cases is expressed, third-party blame, that is, blame expressed by someone who is neither the victim nor the transgressor of the wrong at stake. I conduct my argument through three steps. First, I argue that expressions of friendship are incompatible with public expressions of blame in the public sphere because they convey incompatible public meanings to those outside the relationship. When we show publicly that we are friends with someone we make an implicitly normative assessment. As we tend to be friends with those who we value, when someone has friends, we interpret that person as being valued. On the other hand, expressing third-party blame conveys the message that the blamed person deserves retribution, revision of our relationships with them, or being held accountable, among others. This message seems to be at odds with the message that is conveyed through expressions of friendship. Secondly, after making the case that expressions of friendship might be perceived as expressions of support in some contexts, I argue that we should not express friendship with a wrongdoer in the public sphere because: (1) it might convey condonation; (2) it might generate testimonial injustice for the victims; and (3) it might serve to silence the victims. In reply to an objection from the supporting nature of friendship, which claims that friends should support each other especially in hard circumstances, I notice that my claim does not prevent private expression of friendship. My only concern has to do with the impact of expressions of friendship when performed in public, and hence perceived by bystanders and the victim. Thirdly, I argue that, given a friend who has committed a moral transgression outside the relationship of friendship, we should express third-party blame to them in the public sphere. In favour of this path of action, I provide four reasons. First, because it conveys the message to our friend, and to the moral community that we find that behaviour blameworthy, and that we condemn it. Second, because it expresses support to the victim. Third, because it conveys the message to the moral community that, in similar situations, we support the claims of other presumed victims, and that we condemn the behaviours of other presumed transgressors. And fourth, because it conveys the message that such behaviour should not be part of those behaviours that we normatively expect from each other. Finally, I reply to the objection from the business condition, that is, the claim that expressing third-party blame might be an instance of meddlesome blame. I rebut this objection by appealing to the privileged position that a friend might hold in relation to another friend and appealing to the position of that friend as a member of the moral community. Finally, I reply to three anticipated objections: the charge of judgmentalism, the objection that expressions of blame and of friendship are compatible, and the objection from disagreement. In response to the charge of judgmentalism, I have rejected this charge in cases involving friends, or severe moral transgressions; in response to the objection that expressions of blame and of friendship are compatible, I have argued that my argument works even though one rejects the incompatibility claim; and, finally, in response to the objection from disagreement, I have acknowledged it as a strategic assumption in my theoretical framework.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Philosophy in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Arts.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 8, 2022.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">blame, condonation, friendship, public sphere, silencing, third-party</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Randolph K. Clarke, Professor Directing Thesis; Andrea Carol Westlund, Committee Member; Marcela Herdova, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85045096">
      <mods:topic>Ethics</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100849">
      <mods:topic>Philosophy</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">2022_IsernMas_fsu_0071N_17196</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Arts</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Philosophy</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-10-10T17:55:50.20129-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
