<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Determinants of State and Local Preemption Behavior</title>
      <nonSort>The</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-8963-9668</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Artiles</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Alexandra</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/adriscoll">
      <namePart type="family">Driscoll</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Amanda M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n81065572">
      <namePart type="family">Berry</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Frances Stokes</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2011075894">
      <namePart type="family">Atkeson</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lonna Rae</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1965-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2018003154">
      <namePart type="family">Hassell</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Hans J. G.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Political Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (171 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >This dissertation consists of three essays examining the role of state preemption on local government in the U.S. and Canada. The papers broadly examine why states choose to preempt local governments, and how local governments respond to their power being taken away. Paper one is an observational analysis of over 1,200 gubernatorial executive orders, examining what strategies governors used to preempt local governments during the COVID-19 pandemic. Paper two contains two survey experiments examining when and how U.S. local officials oppose and resist state preemption. Paper three contains a survey experiment examining whether Canadian municipal officials oppose intervention into their affairs at higher rates when it comes from an ideologically incongruent provincial government. Below I include a brief abstract of each. Chapter one, "Preemption in the Intergovernmental Trenches: Explaining Gubernatorial Preemption Style During the COVID-19 Pandemic," examines what institutional and political factors influenced governors' preemption style during the pandemic by analyzing a dataset of over 1,200 COVID-19 executive orders, classified by their style of preemption: ceiling, floor, or vacuum. Governors in states with high local autonomy, as well as Republican governors, rely on ceiling preemptions, which ban local governments from enacting any regulations stricter than their state. Governors in states with ideologically dissimilar local governments tend to issue vacuum preemptions, in which a state bans local governments from regulating a policy area, while also failing to set regulations of its own. When non-preempting provisions – which empower local governments – are dropped from the analysis, local autonomy does not significantly affect issuing one type of preemption over another. On the other hand, Republican governors are more likely to issue both ceiling and floor preemptions over vacuum preemptions. Governors in states with high ideological asymmetry are less likely to issue ceiling and floor preemptions over vacuum preemptions. Chapter two, "Concede or Resist Preemption? Experimental Evidence from U.S. Local Officials," examines whether partisanship and policy type affect local officials' opposition and resistance to state preemption. To do so, I conduct two original pre-post, between-subject survey experiments – one on environmental regulations and the other on traffic regulations – on over 1,000 local officials throughout the U.S. In both the environment and traffic experiments, I find that local officials are substantially more opposed to preemption from an out-party governor, while those in the in-party treatment are far more supportive of preemption. This paper incorporates a novel "pushback index," which asks local officials whether they are willing to fight state preemption through legal action, defiance, local legislation, and advocacy efforts. Here, in the environment experiment, local officials were more willing to resist preemption from an out-party and less willing to resist preemption from an in-party. A sentiment analysis of respondents' open-ended experiences with preemption corroborates the experimental results. Chapter three, "Are Municipal Politics Ideological? Experimental Evidence from Canadian Municipal Officials," examines whether ideology shapes Canadian municipal politics even in a non-partisan and ostensibly non-ideological context. Scholars continue to debate whether municipal politics are characterized by ideological battles, yielding mixed results. To test this argument further, I conducted a survey experiment on a representative sample of over 700 municipal officials through the Canadian Municipal Barometer. Based on their self-reported ideology on a ten-point scale, respondents were assigned to one of three groups: an ideologically congruent province, an ideologically incongruent province, and a control group in which the ideology of the provincial government is omitted. Respondents then read a hypothetical prompt explaining that a newly elected provincial government plans to pass a series of environmental laws prohibiting municipalities from passing their own. I find that municipal officials facing intervention from an ideologically incongruent province are more opposed to intervention, while those facing intervention from an ideologically congruent province were more supportive of intervention. Moreover, municipal officials were more likely to support being consulted – or being required to give their consent – when facing policy intervention from an ideologically incongruent province.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Political Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 11, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Amanda Driscoll, Professor Directing Dissertation; Frances Berry, University Representative; Lonna R. Atkeson, Committee Member; Hans Hassell, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104440">
      <topic>Political science</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Artiles_fsu_0071E_18924</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Political Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
