<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Valorization of Pelagic Sargassum Spp. to Study the Effect of Non-Thermal Processing on Extraction and Characteristics of Alginate</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0006-0473-5946</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Bingi</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Aravind Kumar</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2011191760">
      <namePart type="family">Rao</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Qinchun</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1974-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/psingh2">
      <namePart type="family">Singh</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Prashant</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lcui2">
      <namePart type="family">Cui</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Leqi</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Health, Nutrition, and Food Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (112 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Introduction: Pelagic Sargassum blooms have emerged as a global environmental concern, necessitating innovative approaches for their sustainable management. This thesis delves into the valorization of pelagic Sargassum by investigating the impact of non-thermal processing techniques on the extraction and characterization of alginate, a valuable biopolymer. The methodology encompasses acid and alkali treatments, varied heat applications, and a final step of ethanol precipitation. Characterization techniques such as FTIR, NMR, and rheometer analyses were employed to evaluate the properties of the extracted alginate. Methodology: This work seeks to optimize the extraction process (temperature 40 – 80 °C, alkali concentration 0.1 – 0.3 M, time of heat treatment 1 – 5 hours) using a Response Surface Methodology- Box-Behnken Design (RSM-BBD) to obtain higher product yield and combined it with bleaching with sodium hypochlorite, multistage extraction, and dialysis to obtain a more attractive and high-purity product, as well as giving insights into physicochemical properties of the extracted alginate from pelagic Sargassum biomass. Results: The optimization process revealed that the highest extraction yield of sodium alginate from pelagic Sargassum was achieved under specific conditions: a temperature of 80 °C, an alkali concentration of 0.3 M, and a heat treatment duration of 5 hours, resulting in an impressive 44% w/w crude yield. A second-order polynomial equation was developed, predicting the yield with a deviation of 2.4% from the experimental value. Furthermore, the bleaching process using sodium hypochlorite resulted in significant improvements in the characteristics of the extracted alginate by exhibiting a 49% increase in whiteness index compared to the control sample. Additionally, there was an 80% decrease in fluorescence intensity, indicating an enhancement in the purity of the alginate product. The effects of high-pressure processing (HPP) and sonication treatments on purified seaweed-extracted alginate were compared. The purified yield of alginate was not significantly affected by either treatment. However, the M/G ratio and viscosity showed considerable differences. HPP treatment decreased the M/G ratio at higher pressures, while sonication treatment increased the M/G ratio with longer treatment times. FTIR analysis showed decreased COO- peak intensity in both treatments, but sonication-treated samples had a higher carboxyl group content. HPP treatment resulted in a decrease in viscosity with an increase in pressure, while sonication treatment increased viscosity with longer treatment times. Conclusion: This research is paramount in addressing the environmental challenges of pelagic Sargassum blooms. By employing non-thermal processing techniques, the study demonstrates enhanced alginate extraction efficiency from pelagic Sargassum, presenting a sustainable solution for its valorization. In light of the results obtained, it can be concluded that both high-pressure processing (HPP) and sonication treatments exhibit unique impacts on the properties of alginate extracted from seaweed. The treatment selection, however, depends on the specific requirements of the intended application. If a higher Mannuronic (M) to Guluronic (G) ratio and increased viscosity are desired, sonication treatment for 30 minutes is likely to be more advantageous. Conversely, if a lower M/G ratio and a more Newtonian behavior are preferred, HPP treatment at 600 Mpa would be more conducive.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Health, Nutrition, and Food Sciences in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Science.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 20, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Qinchun Rao, Professor Directing Thesis; Prashant Singh, Committee Member; Leqi Cui, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184">
      <topic>Food</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Bingi_fsu_0071N_18849</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Science</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Nutrition, Food, and Exercise Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
