<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Interrelationships between Resilience, Early Life Contexts, and Health Inequalities in Adulthood</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-3776-7101</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Bruefach</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Tyler Lawrence</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2006097242">
      <namePart type="family">Carr</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Dawn C.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n99834877">
      <namePart type="family">Ralston</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Penny A.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jrreynolds">
      <namePart type="family">Reynolds</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">John R.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2005111038">
      <namePart type="family">Taylor</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Miles G.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1976-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/phoman">
      <namePart type="family">Homan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Patricia A.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Sociology</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (147 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Despite incremental improvements in racial health inequalities in previous decades, gaps in morbidity and mortality have expanded in the past 10 years (Curtin and Xu 2022; Xu et al. 2022). Growing racial inequalities are especially visible in patterns of chronic disease prevalence and mortality among adults approaching midlife (Curtin and Xu 2022). One resource that has garnered increasing attention in public discourse, clinical practice, programmatic interventions, and policy is "resilience." Resilience is generally understood as an adaptive capacity to handle stressors in ways that sustain or improve health and well-being (Manning 2013). Though originally grounded in individual, family, and community contexts (Luthar 2006; Rutter 1987), recent interventions grounded in resilience have increased their attention towards psychological resilience (hereafter "resilience") as a means to bolster health and well-being (Joyce et al. 2018). When measured as a psychological resource, resilience is generally shown to bolster physical and mental health. However, several knowledge gaps limit our understanding of the connections between resilience and racial health inequalities over the life course. Better understanding of how early life resources and contexts shape these trends is greatly needed to help reduce chronic disease prevalence and observed inequalities over the life course. This dissertation helps elucidate the linkages between resilience, physical health, and racialized health inequalities in adulthood. Few studies have been able to estimate relationships between resilience and physical health in early adulthood and midlife (Lehrer et al. 2020; Yi et al. 2008). This critical gap in resilience research limits understanding of how resilience shapes both physical health and racial health inequalities. Among scholars identifying racialized relationships between psychological resources and physical health, the consensus is that such patterns reflect racial stratification in stressors and resources over the life course (Erving, Satcher, and Chen 2020; James, Hartnett, and Kalsbeek 1983; Tobin et al. 2022). For this reason, some scholars point to discourse and interventions centered on individual-level sources of resilience as displacing the onus of social inequalities from institutions and policymakers to the communities and people experiencing them (Mahdiani and Ungar 2021; Suslovic and Lett 2023). But despite limited evidence of interrelationships between psychological resources, material resources, and health, few studies have been able to estimate how relationships between resilience and health are conditioned by the broad availability of material and social resources. Building on previous work, I examine how resilience shapes physical health and health inequalities across racialized groups as people approach midlife. I then incorporate novel measures of early life disadvantage to assess how such contexts and resilience in adulthood jointly shape health and health inequalities. This dissertation comprises 3 studies that assess the interrelationships between resilience, early life contexts, and health inequalities in adulthood. I leverage the National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent to Adult Health to measure early life exposure to stressors, resilience in adulthood, and physical health among non-Hispanic White ("White"), non-Hispanic Black ("Black"), and Hispanic/Latinx people (N=7,085). These data allowed me to build on previous research by developing a novel measure of resilience within a nationally representative sample and creating extensive measures of early life contexts that capture different dimensions of disadvantage within family, school, and neighborhood environments. Collectively, these studies illustrate the dynamic effects of resilience and early life contexts on health and health inequalities over the life course. Study 1 shows that associations between resilience and physical health vary among non-Hispanic White, non-Hispanic Black, and Hispanic/Latinx people. Measuring self-rated health and chronic conditions, analyses suggest that because the health benefits of resilience vary across racialized groups, health inequalities between Black respondents and their peers expand at higher levels of resilience. Studies 2 and 3 focus on chronic conditions and highlight 1) how different dimensions of early life disadvantage shape health and health inequalities; and 2) how early life exposures and resilience jointly inform chronic condition prevalence across racialized groups. Due to their unique effects on chronic conditions across racialized groups, resilience and early life disadvantage jointly foster dynamic patterns in chronic disease prevalence among Black, Hispanic/Latinx, and White respondents. This dissertation provides valuable contributions to how scholars conceptualize resilience and provides insights for future resilience-based interventions that are focused on bolstering physical health. I propose that future work examine resilience as a structural process, that as others have argued (Szanton, Gill, and Thorpe Jr. 2010), draws on resilience from individual, community, and society-level contexts. I find that associations between psychological resilience and physical health are contingent on broader contexts, suggesting that other mechanisms of resilience can modify the effectiveness of this individual-level resource for bolstering health and well-being. To my knowledge, this dissertation is the first to examine the conditional health impacts of psychological resilience and different dimensions of early life disadvantage across racialized groups. Implementing this framework can help future studies bridge together silos of resilience research, and thereby illuminate the joint impacts of resources across different domains of resilience. Organizations and policymakers can also leverage this framework to bolster health and reduce racial inequalities, by designing interventions that modify resilience mechanisms across domains beyond the individual level.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Sociology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">May 24, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Chronic Disease, Early Life Disadvantage, Life Course, Racial Stratification, Resilience</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Dawn C. Carr, Professor Directing Dissertation; Penny Ralston, University Representative; John R. Reynolds, Committee Member; Miles Taylor, Committee Member; Patricia Homan, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124200">
      <topic>Sociology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002201">
      <topic>Aging</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85083022">
      <topic>Medical sciences</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Bruefach_fsu_0071E_18055</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Sociology</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
