<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Translational Analysis of the Association between Binge Eating and Inflammation</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-1133-6007</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Campanile</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Alexis Ann</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/eckel">
      <namePart type="family">Eckel</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lisa A.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2009180254">
      <namePart type="family">Tang</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Hengli</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2004009588">
      <namePart type="family">Keel</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Pamela K.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1970-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lrinaman">
      <namePart type="family">Rinaman</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Linda</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/levenson">
      <namePart type="family">Levenson</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Cathy W.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Psychology</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (86 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >There is evidence to suggest that individuals with bulimic syndromes (i.e., eating disorders characterized by binge eating, including binge-purge anorexia nervosa, bulimia nervosa, and binge eating disorder) experience peripheral inflammation before and after the onset of eating pathology. However, the role that inflammation plays in the development and/or maintenance of these dysregulated eating behaviors is poorly understood. The goal of this dissertation was to examine immune alterations in response to binge-like eating in female rats, and bulimic syndromes in humans. Here, we investigated whether intermittent overconsumption of a high fat diet (HFD), in the form of a binge, could promote microglial reactivity in brain regions implicated in the neural control of food intake, including the arcuate nucleus of the hypothalamus (ARC) and the nucleus of the solitary tract (NTS). Our findings demonstrated that binge-like eating behavior occurs in female rats that are intermittently presented with a HFD, compared to female rats given either daily chow access only, or daily chow and HFD access. We found for the first time that both continuous and intermittent consumption of a HFD led to increased Iba1 expression (a cytoskeletal protein marker of microglia/macrophages) and decreased microglial branch length and number in the ARC and NTS compared to chow-fed controls. Additionally, we tested whether attenuating HFD-induced microglial reactivity using pharmacological manipulation would lead to a reduction in binge-like eating behavior in female rats. Minocycline is a broad-spectrum antibiotic that has been shown to cross the blood brain barrier readily and exhibits anti-inflammatory, neuroprotective effects that are ultimately mediated by its ability to inhibit microglial reactivity. Thus, using the same intermittent HFD access paradigm used in our first study, we gave female rats either minocycline (40 mg/kg) in their drinking water, or gave them tap water (control) for the duration of the 14-day paradigm. There was no effect of minocycline on total food intake, water intake, body weight, or body adiposity. While minocycline did not reduce binge-like eating behavior in female rats given intermittent HFD access, minocycline did attenuate HFD intake and increase chow intake in rats after 24 h of intermittent HFD access, relative to rats given intermittent HFD access and tap water. This suggests that minocycline may alter dietary preference in rats that display binge-like eating behavior. Minocycline did not reliably decrease microglial reactivity in the ARC or NTS across diet conditions. Separate from our studies in rodents, we examined peripheral immune alterations in women diagnosed with bulimic syndromes. The available literature suggests a relationship between bulimic syndromes and peripheral inflammation, but is limited by underpowered studies and a failure to control for confounding variables like body mass index (BMI), percentage of body fat, and comorbidities that could promote inflammation independent of engaging in binge eating. Thus, the goal of this project was to assess a marker of peripheral inflammation (plasma IL-6, a pro-inflammatory cytokine) in a large sample of women with bulimic syndromes and healthy controls across the entire BMI spectrum. We found that plasma concentrations of IL-6 were greater in women with bulimic syndromes, compared to women without eating disorder diagnoses, while controlling for both BMI and percentage of body fat. This demonstrates that there is something about eating pathology in the individuals with bulimic syndromes that is linked to peripheral inflammation. Secondary analyses unveiled that plasma IL-6 was positively correlated with scores on types of assessments that determine whether an individual meets diagnostic criterion for an eating disorder diagnosis, such as the Clinical Impairment Assessment (CIA) and the Global Eating Disorder Examination (EDE), confirming that our participants met eating disorder diagnostic criteria. Plasma IL-6 was also positively correlated with the largest eating episode and fasting leptin levels in all participants. We also found a trend level association between IL-6 and binge frequency in participants with bulimic syndromes. These data demonstrate that women with bulimic syndromes experience peripheral inflammation that occurs separate from elevated adiposity. Ultimately, these studies demonstrate that binge-like eating in female rats, and binge eating in women with bulimic syndromes, is associated with a degree of either central or peripheral inflammation.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Psychology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 7, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">binge eating, eating disorders, female rats, inflammation, microglia, women</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Lisa Eckel, Professor Directing Dissertation; Hengli Tang, University Representative; Pamela Keel, Committee Member; Linda Rinaman, Committee Member; Cathy Levenson, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91006099">
      <topic>Neurosciences</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85108459">
      <topic>Psychology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85108425">
      <topic>Psychobiology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Campanile_fsu_0071E_18186</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Psychology</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
