<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Computational Perspective on Important Energetics in the Ring Opening Metathesis Polymerization (ROMP) of Low and Medium Strained Cycloolefins</title>
      <nonSort>A</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-2745-3264</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Coia</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Brianna M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kennemur">
      <namePart type="family">Kennemur</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Justin Glenn</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dhallinan">
      <namePart type="family">Hallinan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Daniel T.</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">Jr.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rschurko">
      <namePart type="family">Schurko</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Robert W.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016054557">
      <namePart type="family">Alabugin</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Igor V.</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Professor)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (197 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Equilibrium ring opening metathesis polymerization (ROMP) of low-medium strained cycloolefins is opportunistic for the development of novel sustainable materials. While developing a greener future involves addressing several issues, this research aims to reduce the cost, energy, time, and waste involved in the development of new materials through the computational elucidation of key fundamental parameters that guide the olefin metathesis of low and medium strained cycloolefins using Density Functional Theory (DFT). Low strained rings, such as cyclopentenes, have demonstrated promise for materials capable of chemical recycling to monomer (CRM). A facile, quick monomer screening method for the CRM potential of monomers using DFT ring strain energy (RSE) calculations is improved herein while simultaneously addressing long-standing concerns regarding conformational issues. New homodesmotic equations are investigated to capture changes in olefin conformation upon polymerization improving CRM prediction. Similarly, RSEs were calculated using Boltzmann ensembles of monomers indicating negligible differences when compared to just using the lowest energy conformers. Cyclopentene derivatives also offer a unique opportunity to elucidate how substituent choice may influence the most understudied type of strain, torsional strain. Potential trends investigated include substituent location, size, electronegativity, hybridization, and steric bulk. Results show that the size and substitution (bulk) of the first atom within the substituent have the greatest influence on torsional dominated RSE. Different computational setups probed suggest that consideration of electron correlation in calculations increased RSEs by ~2-5 kcal mol-1. Further increasing computational accuracy does not significantly change RSEs and does not warrant the increased computational cost and time. Predominantly driven by RSE for small to medium sized cycloolefins, successful ROMP is also dependent on monomer-catalyst interactions. Steric and/or electronic factors can contribute to not only whether polymerization will occur, but also the relative level of control observed. Computational investigations of RSEs as well as catalytic behavior using DFT provide more wholistic insights for predicting and identifying ideal parameters to achieve customized polymers with targeted properties. Herein, the influences of monomer structure on reaction thermodynamics and kinetics are probed to provide and explicate more broadly applicable fundamental knowledge to olefin metatheses with common commercially available Grubbs catalysts. Medium strained monoterpenes derived from highly abundant and sustainable α-pinene have yielded exciting biomass sourced polyolefins via ROMP. The polymerization of apo-, α-, and δ- all wield notably different behaviors granting an unprecedented chance to study the ROMP mechanism of 3 similar hydrocarbon bicyclic monomers. DFT calculations have identified effective RSE (RSEE) of the pinenes concomitant to reaction coordinate diagrams (RCDs) for both proximal and distal pathways enabling a deeper understanding of the energetics that contribute to polymerization control. The notoriously challenging polymerization of α-pinene was corroborated by endergonic mechanisms with much higher activation energies than apo- and δ-pinene which undergo ROMP efficiently. The RCDs for α-pinene elucidated that the mechanism of inhibition is likely due to non-productive pathways, or the formation of the RuCB intermediate preferring torevert to monomer instead of propagating. Apopinene RCDs revealed a slight preference for the distal pathway thermodynamically and kinetically. Both mechanisms were very similar in energies, and therefore both feasible, which is reflective of the incomplete microstructural control experimentally observed for the ROMP of apopinene. δ-pinene has been reported to demonstrate excellent microstructural control as illustrated by a clear kinetic preference for the proximal pathway. Thermodynamically, both proximal and distal pathways are exergonic and differ by ~3.3 kcal mol-1, but the distal pathway has a particularly stable RuCB that creates an energy well between the 1st and 2nd transition states complicating successful propagation.1H NMR calculations were compared with experimental chemical shifts to further corroborate a clear preference for the ROMP of δ-pinene to undergo the proximal mechanism. The effect of chelation on polymerization control was also investigated for two cyclopentene derivatives that differ by one methylene unit in the side chain, α-BIB and MeBIB. Preliminary experimental results suggest that α-BIB has struggled to achieve high and targeted molecular weights (Mn) while MeBIB has shown promise. Calculations probing the monomer energetics, thermodynamics of chelate formation with the carbonyl and ester oxygens in various solvents, and origins of favorable chelation were performed. Overall, only the chelation of the carbonyl oxygen on α-BIB was found to be thermodynamically favorable (ΔG ≈ -2 to -11 kcal mol-1) supporting the observed challenge in polymerization control. No clear explanation was elucidated as differences in electronic stabilization to the catalysts, nor ring size provided sufficient support as to why the only favorable chelate calculated herein is OC on α-BIB, so further investigations are necessary.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Chemistry.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 22, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">chemical recycling to monomer (CRM), Density functional theory (DFT), Reaction coordinate diagram (RCD), ring strain energy (RSE), Ring-opening metathesis polymerization (ROMP)</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Justin G. Kennemur, Professor Directing Dissertation; Daniel Hallinan, University Representative; Robert Schurko, Committee Member; Igor Alabugin, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2020006312">
      <topic>Computational chemistry</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104660">
      <topic>Polymers</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022986">
      <topic>Chemistry</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Coia_fsu_0071E_18093</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
