<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Intonation of Spanish and Basque in Gipuzkoa and French and Basque in Labourd</title>
      <subTitle>An Exploratory Study</subTitle>
      <nonSort>The</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-4473-1465</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Delgado Fernández</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Nerea</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/cgonzalez3">
      <namePart type="family">González</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Carolina</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n94098012">
      <namePart type="family">Almond</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Russell G.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2015008326">
      <namePart type="family">Muntendam</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Antje</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2006124985">
      <namePart type="family">Reglero</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lara</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Modern Languages and Linguistics</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (260 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >This dissertation examines bilingual intonation of information-seeking yes-no questions and Wh-questions in under-investigated varieties of Spanish and Basque in Gipuzkoa (Spanish-Basque bilingualism) and French and Basque in Labourd (French-Basque bilingualism). A secondary goal of this study is to explore the effects of language dominance, linguistic attitudes, and gender on the intonation patterns of bilinguals with different sociolinguistic profiles. Previous research in either region is either limited or inexistent. In Gipuzkoa, yes-no questions in both Basque and Spanish have been described as ending in falling intonation with either a low (L%) or circumflex (HL%) boundary tone (for Spanish: Elordieta and Romera, 2020a; Romera and Elordieta, 2020; for Basque: Elordieta, 2003; Elordieta &amp; Hualde). This differs from Castilian Spanish, where yes-no questions are produced with a rise (Hualde &amp; Prieto, 2015; and references therein). For Wh-questions in Basque Spanish, the sole description available reports a higher prevalence of rising intonation (75% H%, 25% L%) (Gaminde et al., 2014), whereas in Basque there are mixed findings: Falling intonation (Elordieta, 2003; Elordieta &amp; Hualde, 2014) vs. rising (Gaminde et al., 2014) in areas where Basque is less widely spoken. In Labourd, research is much more limited. Duguine and Irurtzun (2020) report rising intonation for both yes-no and Wh-questions in Labourdin Basque. However, no descriptions have been proposed for the variety of French spoken in the region. Regarding the effects of sociolinguistic variables in the Basque Country, results have been mixed for language dominance (González &amp; Reglero, 2020; Elodieta &amp; Romera, 2020a), and some evidence is provided for an effect of linguistic attitudes (Elordieta &amp; Romera, 2020a). To date, no effects of gender have been reported (Elordieta &amp; Romera, 2020a). To expand on these limited findings, we analyzed data from 13 Spanish-Basque bilinguals from Irun (Gipuzkoa) and 11 French-Basque bilinguals from different towns in Labourd. All participants completed the Bilingual Language Profile (Birdsong et al. 2012), which gathered sociolinguistic data, and a contextualized reading task in their two languages (Spanish and Basque; French and Basque). This task elicited a total of 310 questions in Spanish (155 for each question type), 296 in Gipuzkoan Basque (150 yes-no questions, 146 Wh-questions), 249 in French (129 yes-no questions, 120 Wh-questions) and 255 in Labourdin Basque (129 yes-no questions, 126 Wh-questions), which were analyzed in Pratt (Boersma &amp; Weenink, 2021), following Spanish ToBI (Aguilar et al. 2009; Face &amp; Prieto, 2007) and French ToBI conventions (Delais-Roussarie et al., 2015), we report boundary tones and nuclear tones for both of the bilinguals' languages in each contact situation and consider the results by language dominance, linguistic attitudes and gender. For the statistical analysis, a multinomial logistic regression was conducted in R (R Core Team, 2023). Results for Gipuzkoan varieties confirm previous descriptions of yes-no questions in the region: A higher prevalence of falling contours (55% in Spanish and 62% in Basque). Nevertheless, rising contours still seemed to be quite common in both languages. Results for Wh-questions, in turn, reveal a high predominance of rising contours in both languages (67.8% in Spanish and 66.4% in Basque). These results fall in line with Gaminde et al.'s (2014) descriptions for Gipuzkoan varieties where bilingualism is less widespread. In effect, that is the reality of Irun, where 73% of the population have Spanish as their dominant language (Euskal Estatistika Erakundea/Instituto Vasco de Estadística, 2018). Results for Labourdin Basque also confirm Duguine and Irurtzun's (2020) description as rising intonation predominated in both sentence types (97.7% in yes-no questions, and 69.8% in Wh-questions). For French, similar findings were yielded (90% rising in yes-no questions and 75% in Wh-questions). A consideration of these results by sociolinguistic factor revealed variable effects. Overall, effects of language dominance and gender were reported for yes-no questions in Spanish, Gipuzkoan Basque and French, and Wh-questions in French and Labourdin Basque, while attitudes were only significant for Spanish and French yes-no questions. In sum, this study contributes to the documentation of these understudied varieties by expanding on previous findings of Gipuzkoan varieties of Spanish and Basque, and Labourdin Basque, and providing a novel description of Labourdin French. What is more, it affords valuable insights on the effects of sociolinguistic factors on different varieties and sentence types.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Modern Languages and Linguistics in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 30, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Carolina González, Professor Directing Dissertation; Russell Almond, University Representative; Antje Muntendam, Committee Member; Lara Reglero, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077222">
      <topic>Linguistics</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006100">
      <topic>Acoustics</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">DelgadoFernandez_fsu_0071E_18827</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Modern Languages and Linguistics</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
