<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Molecular Characterization of Polyfunctinal Heteroatom Compounds in Ultracomplex Mixtures by 21 Tesla Fourier Transform Ion Cyclotron Resonance Mass Spectrometry (21 T FT-ICR MS)</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-3618-8052</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Frye-Jones</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Joseph William</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n77017670">
      <namePart type="family">Marshall</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Alan G. (Alan George)</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1944-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n89605460">
      <namePart type="family">Chanton</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jeffrey P.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="viaf"
         authorityURI="http://viaf.org/viaf/"
         valueURI="http://viaf.org/viaf/35658877">
      <namePart type="family">Bleiholder</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Christian</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mroper">
      <namePart type="family">Roper</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michael Gabriel</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (158 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >The work described herein summarizes the molecular characterization across two categories of complex mixtures, petroleum photoproducts and non-terrestrial soluble organic material (SOM). Ultrahigh resolution Fourier transform ion cyclotron resonance mass spectrometry (FT-ICR MS) uniquely provides the resolving power and mass accuracy necessary for molecular formula assignments in a variety of complex mixtures. Over the years, FT-ICR MS has proven useful to petroleum characterization, but increased compositional complexity introduced through weathering processes after spills makes it essential. The weathering process of photooxidation has been identified as a primary factor in phototransformation reactions, resulting in increased complexity of the transformed products. Photooxidation generates new oil-soluble, interfacial, and water-soluble materials through increased oxygenation. Creation of these materials is detrimental to the environment and has been classified as an emerging contaminate. Increased understanding of how these materials interact with each other is necessary to combat the effects on the environment after oil spills. The complexity of organic material generated in space has proven just as complex as terrestrial dissolved organic material (DOM) or petroleum with tens of thousands of molecular formulas assigned for each spectrum. Therefore, FT-ICR MS is a necessity for characterization to increase the comprehensive knowledge of these types of samples, especially as the second space race begins. Most lunar research was conducted shortly after the first space race but used low resolution mass spectrometry instrumentation relative to techniques available today. Unlike lunar regolith research, meteorite characterization has continued throughout the years as new and more exciting samples landed. This provides a great starting point to begin lunar analysis and excellent test samples for the development of new techniques before astronauts return to the lunar surface within the decade. Chapter 1 introduces terrestrial and non-terrestrial complex mixtures along with how FT-ICR MS is utilized in molecular characterization. Separations often used in terrestrial complex mixtures such as petroleum and dissolved organic matter are also introduced. Chapter 2 explores the separations used on the photooxidized products generated through the irradiation of a heavy vacuum gas oil (HVGO). The oil-soluble and interfacial material is characterized to understand how the acidic species contribute to interfacial material formation. Chapter 3 continues analysis of the HVGO photoproducts with the investigation of the water-soluble material. Utilization of a new DOM separation provides the first separation of water-soluble material based off aromaticity and increased oxygenation. The results are then compared to the results obtained from Chapter 2. These two chapters provide a comprehensive analysis of photoproducts generated in the oil-soluble, interfacial, and water-soluble materials across a range of irradiation periods. Chapter 4 describes the development of a new sequential solvent extraction and analysis method for SOM from meteorites. This work focuses on the comprehensive molecular characterization to expand the knowledge of meteorite SOM. Chapter 5 utilizes the separation method created in Chapter 4 to extract and characterize SOM from lunar regolith returned by the Apollo 12 and 16 lander missions. This work is the first time ultra-high resolution mass spectrometry has been used for analysis of these materials. Collectively, Chapter 4 and 5 demonstrate the necessity of FT-ICR MS in organic characterization of these samples and specifically the 21 T FT-ICR MS at the National High Magnetic Field Laboratory.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">November 14, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">FT-ICR MS, Lunar regolith, Meteorites, Petroleum, Photooxidation, Soluble organic material</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Alan G. Marshall, Professor Directing Dissertation; Jeffery Chanton, University Representative; Christian Bleiholder, Committee Member; Michael G. Roper, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023011">
      <topic>Chemistry, Analytic</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">FryeJones_fsu_0071E_18339</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
