<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Stories to Read Aloud to Strangers on the Bus</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-1801-2395</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Galef</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Daniel</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n87872195">
      <namePart type="family">Winegardner</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Mark</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1961-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2008084444">
      <namePart type="family">Horack</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Skip</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n95035963">
      <namePart type="family">Hamby</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Barbara</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1952-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of English</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (154 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Stories to Read Aloud to Strangers on the Bus is a collection of published and unpublished short stories ranging from 100-word "flash fiction" to 10,000 words. The emphasis in this manuscript is on variety and eclecticism---of genre, of style, of voice, and even of form. I wanted to avoid a technically-proficient but dull Default Collection composed of a dozen ten-page stories that all read similarly. In keeping with the diversity of style and voice, these stories also range across multiple genres and hybrid genres. The majority are straightforward "literary fiction," whatever that means. Others are speculative fiction—itself a many-headed beast, this includes magical realism, Borges-inspired philosophical fiction, historical fiction, and even one whiz-bang sci-fi story in the vein of Isaac Asimov. As with the diversity of styles, it is my aim that these disparate genres complement each other rather than detract, and make for a reading experience that is more interesting and exciting for its variety, akin to eating a heart-shaped box of chocolates after you've lost the little leaflet they slip under the lid telling you which bonbons are coconut and which bonbons have explosives hidden underneath them. (The manuscript does not reveal in the table of contents which short stories have explosives hidden underneath them.) Despite this project of emphasizing disparity (disparate times call for disparate measures), the stories are still tied together in other ways, by recurring themes and threads. One unifying element across the stories is humor. Every story in the collection contains some comic element, even if not all are strictly comedies. Though I have published a handful of more serious solemn short stories, these have not been included. Likewise, though a small number of the stories are direct parodies or style imitations of some of my favorite authors, I have also not included anything that comes across more as a "humor piece" than a "story" in which the narrative is first and foremost. The stories are also united by recurring elements not of style but substance, the ideas I continually come back to as a writer and which are necessarily dealt with differently in different genres. For example, both "The False Law" and "Birth of Venus" are narratives concerned on some level with truth and falsehood and the relationship of representational art to the real world, but because one is gothic literary fiction and the other a campy sci-fi parable, they are able to do different things with the same subject matter—for example, the literary story is better equipped to follow the interior thoughts of an artist experiencing a crisis of faith, while the speculative story can better explore dramatic counterfactual premises which would be out of place or unbelievable in realist fiction ("What if a dictator obsessed with the truth prosecuted poets for perjury?"). Juxtaposing these different genres next to each other might, if successful, produce an effect like a cubist painting, whereby the same object is viewed from multiple angles at once. Likewise, both "Lie Lightly" and "Tall Tale" are stories in which the narrator is an inveterate liar, but one is told by a folksy 1800s raconteur and the other by a cynical Westchester stage magician. The dreamlike, impressionistic style of the first story creates a feeling of postmodern uncertainty and unreliability which mirrors the character's confusion, whereas the more comic, folkloric genre of the second more subtly deconstructs this deconstruction to demonstrate that this unreliability is not some modern innovation but rather the fundamental characteristic of fiction: All fiction is, by definition, lies.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of English in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Fine Arts.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 13, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">anthology, collection, fiction, lies</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Mark Winegardner, Professor Directing Thesis; Skip Horack, Committee Member; Barbara Hamby, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033847">
      <topic>Creative writing</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Galef_fsu_0071N_17986</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Fine Arts</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>English</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
