<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Stereoelectronic Effects of Oxygen</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-2257-6671</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Kuhn</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Leah</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016054557">
      <namePart type="family">Alabugin</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Igor V.</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Professor)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n84134993">
      <namePart type="family">Locke</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Bruce R.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/yang">
      <namePart type="family">Yang</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Wei</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kennemur">
      <namePart type="family">Kennemur</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Justin Glenn</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (629 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >The focus of this dissertation is exploring the role of stereoelectronic effects in organic chemistry. After a general introduction, seven research projects will be discussed in detail to illustrate how stereoelectronic effects can be used to control reactivity. Chapter One starts by introducing stereoelectronic effects. In this chapter the concept of 'classical' chemical bonding is expanded to include second-order (delocalizing) interactions. The different types of stereoelectronic interactions are classified by the types and locations of interacting orbitals. Finally, the factors controlling stereoelectronic effects are discussed. Chapter Two discusses the modeling and theoretical study of stereoelectronic effects. Studying stereoelectronic effects experimentally can be difficult due to the many layers of complexity in an organic reaction. Computational tools can be utilized to explore and isolate stereoelectronic effects. In this chapter the main quantitative tools for studying stereoelectronic effects are introduced, in addition to examples of their applications. The main tools discussed in this chapter include: conformational changes, bond breaking/bond forming equations, thermochemical equations, and wavefunction analysis methods. Chapter Three discloses two research projects which illustrate how stereoelectronic effects can be used to control reactivity. Stereoelectronic effects that are present in a reactant and become stronger in the transition state lead to an increase in reactivity. Therefore, deactivating the stereoelectronic effects in the reactant can help decrease the reactivity, making it possible to capture a previously elusive intermediate. Furthermore, activating stereoelectronic effects in the reactant that need to be forfeited in the transition state will further decrease reactivity. Both of these concepts are utilized to capture the Criegee Intermediate and to explore the layers of stereoelectronic protection which made this intermediate elusive for over seventy years. The second project in this chapter discusses the systematic modification of phenols in order to control their antioxidant activity. A primary role of antioxidants is to quench free radicals through mechanisms such as H-atom transfer. Therefore, the antioxidant ability can potentially be increased by introducing stereoelectronic effects which stabilize the phenol radical product. This hypothesis is explored in a series of pyrrolidone- and caprolactam-substituted phenols. Chapter Four discusses how to control the reactivity of carboxylate radicals using transition metals. Harnessing carboxylate radicals is difficult because of their propensity to undergo rapid decarboxylation. However, with certain transition metals the carboxylate radicals can coordinate to the metal center as a non-innocent L-ligand. When behaving as an L-ligand the radical character at the carboxylate is preserved while decarboxylation is avoided. Once these reactive radicals are trapped, they can be used for C-H activation on both activated and non-activated C-H bonds. In Chapter Five, the mechanisms of two reactions controlled by stereoelectronic effects are explored. First, the mechanism of metal-free C-H functionalization using a domino reaction of aerobic amine oxidation and a vinylogous Mannich reaction is discussed. Computations reveal the crucial role of the thiourea additive as an electron-transfer mediator and a scavenger of reactive oxygen species. Finally, in this chapter, three radical cascades are explored for the controlled termination of radical alkyne peri-annulations. The termination of the radical cascades is controlled by the pre-installation of a 'weak link' which undergoes C-O fragmentation in the final cascade step. Computations determined that the C-O fragmentation step can be assisted by entropy, a gain of conjugation in the product, and stabilization of the released radical fragment. The three unique radical cascades discussed include a reductive termination with re-entry pathway, an oxidative termination with re-entry pathway, and a dyotropic-like intermolecular disproportionation pathway. All three pathways are possible in the reaction conditions and contribute to both the necessity of excess radical precursors and a longer reaction time. In the final chapter, Chapter Six, the origin of the anomeric effect is explored using statistical analysis. The hyperconjugative model is generally the most popular explanation for the origin of the anomeric effect, however, several literature reports offer dissenting opinions and argue for the primary importance of other factors, such as, electrostatics and sterics. Due to the inherent complexity of molecules, in addition to the use of specific computational methods, confirmation bias can be introduced. In order to remove any potential bias a computer could be allowed to interpret the data. Therefore, statistical analysis was performed on a data set of fifty substituted 2-X tetrahydropyran molecules. Parameters measuring sterics, electrostatics, and stereoelectronic effects were included in order to allow the computer to decide the origin of the anomeric effect.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 23, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Igor V. Alabugin, Professor Directing Dissertation; Bruce Locke, University Representative; Wei Yang, Committee Member; Justin Kennemur, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023022">
      <topic>Chemistry, Organic</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Kuhn_fsu_0071E_18077</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
