<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>New Metrics of Surface Ocean Dissolved Organic Nutrient Cycling</title>
      <subTitle>Global Patterns of Production and Consumption</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-4999-7097</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Liang</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Zhou</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2006015588">
      <namePart type="family">Knapp</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Angela Noel</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1976-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2009143870">
      <namePart type="family">Speer</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kevin G. (Kevin George)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2004084871">
      <namePart type="family">Mason</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Olivia Underwood</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jdowens">
      <namePart type="family">Owens</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jeremy D.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/skranz">
      <namePart type="family">Kranz</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sven Alexander</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rletscher">
      <namePart type="family">Letscher</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Robert</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (163 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >The marine biological pump sequesters atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO2) in the ocean when phytoplankton convert CO2 to organic carbon in the surface ocean. Subsequent sinking of dead planktonic biomass to the deep ocean moves carbon from the atmosphere to the deep ocean on century to millennial timescales. Nutrients (e.g., nitrogen, phosphorus, and iron) are essential for phytoplankton growth and exert bottom-up control on the strength of the marine biological pump. In vast areas of the surface ocean, particularly in the subtropical gyres, inorganic nutrients like nitrate and phosphate are often near or below detection limits, limiting phytoplankton growth. However, rates of export production in these inorganic nutrient-depleted regions are comparable to more nutrient-replete regions. Identifying the nutrient sources and their supply mechanisms in the subtropical gyres has thus been a long-term goal of the oceanographic community. Potential nutrient sources fueling export in the subtropical gyres include the physical transport of subsurface nutrients to surface waters, vertical migration of phytoplankton to deeper, nutrient replete waters, atmospheric deposition, nitrogen fixation, and the consumption of dissolved organic nutrients. Recently, attention has focused on dissolved organic nutrients including dissolved organic nitrogen (DON) and phosphorus (DOP) because they are the quantitatively dominant forms of bioavailable nitrogen (N) and phosphorus (P) in subtropical surface waters, and because they can be utilized as a N and P source by diverse phytoplankton groups. However, our understanding of DON and DOP production and consumption patterns in the global ocean is still limited. In this dissertation, I take advantage of recently updated global marine dissolved organic carbon (DOC), DON, and DOP concentration datasets and use DOC:DON:DOP concentration stoichiometry as a geochemical tracer to illustrate the production and consumption patterns of surface ocean DON and DOP from basin to global scale. I find that ~15-20% of new production is released as DOC, DON, and DOP, and is produced in the surface ocean in concentration ratios near "Redfield" stoichiometry (C:N:P = 106:16:1), similar to their phytoplankton source. However, most surface ocean DOC:DON:DOP concentration ratios are elevated compared to Redfield stoichiometry, implying that loss of DOC, DON, and DOP occurs in non-Redfield proportions in the surface ocean. Additionally, I find that surface ocean DOC:DON, DON:DOP, and DOC:DOP concentration ratios vary across different geographic and biogeochemical regions. Surface ocean DOP concentrations exhibit a broader dynamic range in concentration than DOC or DON, which I attribute to preferential consumption of DOP by autotrophs compared to DOC and DON. I further link variations in surface DOC:DON:DOP concentration stoichiometry with basin-scale biogeochemical processes including elevated rates of water column denitrification in the Eastern Pacific Ocean and atmospheric dust depositions to the North Atlantic Ocean. The narrow range of DON concentration and DOC:DON concentration ratios in the surface ocean limit their use alone in identifying regions of DON production and consumption in the surface ocean. To address this, I further use the nitrogen isotopic composition of DON (DON δ15N) as a more sensitive geochemical tracer to study production and consumption patterns of marine DON. I report DON concentration and DON δ15N measurements from the upper 300 m along a &gt;10,000 km zonal transect (P06-2017) across the South Pacific from the Chilean coast to the Australian coast. Combining DON concentration and DON δ15N data, I find higher upper 50 m DON concentrations in the eastern portion of the P06-2017 transect associated with DON production in the region with elevated primary productivity, and inverse relationship between DON concentrations and DON δ15N associated with DON consumption in the western portion of the P06-2017 transect. Furthermore, I develop global ocean DOC and DON inverse models that simulate global ocean DOC and DON concentration fields conditional on their observations. Combining these fields with the output from our previous work on a global ocean inverse DOP model, I obtain a modeled, three-dimensional, DOC:DON:DOP concentration ratio field and calculate associated biogeochemical fluxes, including the rates of autotrophic DON uptake. I further quantify the lateral transport of DON and DOP to the subtropical gyres and find that their fluxes exceed the atmospheric deposition flux and can reach 17-90% of the nitrogen fixation flux in the subtropical gyres. I also investigate the preferential remineralization of DON and DOP relative to DOC in the shallow mesopelagic as another mechanism by which DON and DOP serve as organic nutrient sources to sustain productivity in the subtropical gyres. Together, this work provides new, quantitative metrics of the significance of DON and DOP production and consumption as autotrophic nutrients in oligotrophic gyres.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Earth, Ocean and Atmospheric Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">May 22, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Angela Knapp, Professor Directing Dissertation; Kevin Speer, University Representative; Olivia Mason, Committee Member; Jeremy Owens, Committee Member; Sven Kranz, Committee Member; Robert Letscher, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022928">
      <topic>Chemical oceanography</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Liang_fsu_0071E_18839</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
