<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Solid-State NMR of Quadrupolar Nuclei in Organic Solids</title>
      <subTitle>New Directions in Mechanochemical Synthesis and Crystal Structure Prediction</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-3857-5320</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Peach</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Austin Alain</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rschurko">
      <namePart type="family">Schurko</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Robert W.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/scgrant">
      <namePart type="family">Grant</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Samuel C.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/strouse">
      <namePart type="family">Strouse</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Geoffrey F.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/shatruk">
      <namePart type="family">Shatruk</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Mykhailo</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (326 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >The work presented in this dissertation focuses on (i) the use of mechanochemistry for the preparation of cocrystals of active pharmaceutical ingredients (APIs) and 17O-enrichment of carboxylic acids; (ii) the utility of multinuclear solid-state NMR (SSNMR) for the investigation of molecular-level structure and dynamics in crystalline organic solids; and (iii) the development of a new NMR crystallographic protocol for the prediction of crystal structures of hydrochloride (HCl) APIs. Herein, two solid forms of API are of interest HCl salts and cocrystals prepared with carboxylic acids. A major emphasis is placed upon the use of multinuclear SSNMR, with a special focus on quadrupolar nuclei, 35Cl and 17O, which provide invaluable information about intermolecular hydrogen bonding interactions in organic crystals. Information on 35Cl and 17O NMR interaction tensors extracted from NMR spectra are used alongside state-of-the-art plane-wave dispersion corrected density functional theory (DFT-D2*), which is employed for refinement of structural models and structural prediction using the 35Cl electric field gradient (EFG) tensors. Three of the projects in this dissertation describe the detailed characterization of the solid forms of fluoxetine HCl, which is marketed under the brand name Prozac®, and several of its cocrystals involving simple carboxylic acids (i.e., benzoic acid, fumaric acid, and succinic acid). First, the use of mechanochemical methods is demonstrated for the quantitative synthesis of fluoxetine HCl cocrystals with the three carboxylic acids. Ball milling reactions are shown to outperform analogous preparations from solution in terms of speed, efficiency, and purity. Cocrystals are thoroughly characterized with powder X-ray diffraction (pXRD), multinuclear SSNMR (with an emphasis on 35Cl SSNMR), and DFT-D2* calculations. Second, competitive milling (CM) and stability milling (SM) reactions are shown to be useful methods for assessing the affinities of the three carboxylic acids for forming cocrystals with fluoxetine HCl and the stabilities of these cocrystals under mechanochemical conditions. Products resulting from CM and SM reactions are often complex mixtures, and are therefore characterized using pXRD and SSNMR, which provide quantification of the products of these reactions, and even demonstrate the occurrence of solid-state extraction, whereby ball milling of a cocrystal (e.g., XA) comprised of fluoxetine HCl (X) and one coformer (A), with a new coformer, B, can lead to the extraction of A, and forming a new cocrystal with B (e.g., XB). Third, an original protocol featuring mechanochemical saponification for the isotopic 17O-enrichment of carboxylic acids is demonstrated to successfully provide high enrichment yields. This opens the door for characterization of the coformers and their associated cocrystals with 17O SSNMR, revealing fascinating molecular-level dynamics and furthering our knowledge of hydrogen-bonding in cocrystals. The final chapter in this dissertation covers the design, benchmarking, and application of a new quadrupolar NMR crystallography guided crystal structure prediction (QNMRX-CSP) protocol, which draws upon many of the experimental and computational aspects of the first three projects. The QNMRX-CSP protocol is demonstrated to have great potential for the prediction of crystal structures of HCl APIs. The protocol draws upon structural information derived from XRD and 35Cl EFG tensors obtained from 35Cl SSNMR spectra, and features the use of a Monte-Carlo simulated annealing algorithm to search the crystal packing spaces. DFT-D2* calculations are used for refining structures, computing 35Cl EFG tensors, and selecting the best candidate structural models. Thoroughly benchmarked metrics determined from experiments and computations are used to select the structural models that best match known crystal structure candidates, and are even used to successfully predict the crystal structures of two simple organic HCl salts in blind tests. It is hoped that the multifaceted solid-state characterization techniques outlined herein, along with the nascent QNMRX-CSP protocol, will provide new pathways for structural refinement and prediction, and ultimately, the prospect of rationally designing a wide range of hitherto unknown solid forms of APIs.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 10, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Robert W. Schurko, Professor Directing Dissertation; Samuel C. Grant, University Representative; Geoffrey F. Strouse, Committee Member; Mykhailo Shatruk, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022986">
      <topic>Chemistry</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Peach_fsu_0071E_17936</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
