<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Role for Sarcospan in NLRP-3 Inflammasome Activation</title>
      <nonSort>A</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-9668-4416</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Samarah</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Luaye</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mparvatiyar">
      <namePart type="family">Parvatiyar</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michelle</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/gsalazararanda">
      <namePart type="family">Salazar</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Gloria</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/bsgordon">
      <namePart type="family">Gordon</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Bradley S.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rhickner">
      <namePart type="family">Hickner</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Robert C.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1962-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jlaflavor">
      <namePart type="family">La Favor</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Justin</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Health, Nutrition, and Food Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (88 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Inflammation is an important component of the immune system, and its role in disease prevention and progression depends on the duration of its activation. Acute inflammation serves as a protective mechanism against stimulants and pathogenic invasions, where it aids in determining the site of infection and tissue damage, attracts different types of innate and adaptive immune cells to the site of injury, and induces cell death to prevent pathogen spreading. However, the prolonged presence and persistence of stimulants and pathogens is accompanied by a consistent activation of inflammatory pathways, thus leading to a chronic state of inflammation. This can cause tissue damage and the development of systemic inflammatory diseases. One important component of the innate immune system that has been associated with inflammation is the NLRP-3 inflammasome. Its acute activation prevents pathogen spreading, and its excessive activation damages surrounding cells and tissues and can cause systemic inflammatory diseases. Various regulators of innate immune pathways have been discovered. However, other regulators are yet to be identified. One protein that emerged as a promising regulator of innate immune pathways is sarcospan, a transmembrane protein that is a crucial member of the dystrophin-glycoprotein complex (DGC). Here, we aim to investigate the role of sarcospan in innate immunity and systemic inflammatory disease development. To examine sarcospan and innate immune activation global SSPN-deficient mice were utilized. Young (3-4 months old) mice were used with 12 wild type (WT) and 12 SSPN-/- young (3-4 months old), male C57BLJ mice were weighed, euthanized and their tissues were collected to explore potential phenotypical and morphological differences between the tissues of these mice. Tissues were weighed and adjusted to the body weight of each mouse. SSPN-/- mice had a greater average body weight than WT mice, which was accompanied by a higher mean white adipose tissue (WAT) weight. Phenotypical differences that can be attributed to pathology were observed in SSPN-/- kidneys and spleens, with no differences in their average weights. Darker pigmentation of SSPN-/- spleens were observed in 46% (5 out of 12 mice) of SSPN-/- mice, which can be associated with either melanosis or hemorrhage. None of these phenotypes were seen in WT mice. To assess immune system capacity, bone marrow derived macrophages (BMDMs) from both genotypes were isolated, cultured, and allowed to differentiate for seven days. Red bone marrow cells were isolated and SSPN-/- mice were found to have higher cell counts of these pluripotent cells. This suggests immune dysregulation in SSPN-/- mice and potential capacity to generate higher immune cell counts. This in turn may drive sustained inflammation in SSPN-/- mice. It was shown in previous studies that BMDMs from SSPN-/- mice exhibited heightened responsiveness to innate immune ligands including lipopolysaccharide (LPS), a cell wall component, leading to heightened expression of pro-inflammatory cytokines. To assess NLRP-3 activation through the canonical pathway, fully differentiated WT and SSPN-/- BMDM were treated with LPS and nigericin, and the extent of activation was assessed by readouts including imaging and immunoblotting. The results show a higher expression of NLRP-3 and IL-1β in SSPN-/- BMDMs independent of p-NF-kB activation. Confocal imaging of immunofluorescent stained BMDMs were used to characterize the expression of SSPN and compare the numbers of ASC specks formed in WT and SSPN-/- BMDMs without treatment, with LPS, LPS and nigericin, and nigericin alone. SSPN expression was assessed in WT BMDM (SSPN+/+, sarcospan abundant, SSPN-/-, sarcospan-deficient). A higher frequency of ASC speck formation was reported in SSPN-/- BMDMs when compared to WT BMDMs after LPS and nigericin treatment. In conclusion, the heightened inflammatory phenotype in SSPN-/- mice that is thought to be caused by dysregulation of innate immune pathways increases NLRP-3 activation, which was evidenced by higher incidence of ASC speck formation after LPS and nigericin treatment. This can explain the noticeable pathological phenotypes that was reported in SSPN-/- tissues.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Health, Nutrition and Food Sciences in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Science in Exercise Physiology.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">November 21, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Chronic Diseases, Inflammation, Innate Immunity, NLRP-3 Inflammasome, Sarcospan</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Michelle Parvatiyar, Professor Directing Thesis; Gloria Salazar, Professor Directing Thesis; Bradley Gordon, Committee Member; Robert Hickner, Committee Member; Justin La Favor, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989">
      <topic>Education</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Samarah_fsu_0071N_18464</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Science</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Nutrition, Food, and Exercise Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
