<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Comorbidity and Trauma Characteristics as a Function of Chronic and Remitted PTSD</title>
      <subTitle>A Population-Based Study Using the Hitop Classification of Mental Disorders</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0007-8809-1259</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Stentz</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lauren A.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jcougle">
      <namePart type="family">Cougle</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jesse R. (Jesse Ray)</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1975-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/deccles">
      <namePart type="family">Eccles</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">David W.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dsm6713">
      <namePart type="family">March</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">David Scott</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2005015125">
      <namePart type="family">Patrick</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Christopher J.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85213114">
      <namePart type="family">Wagner</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Richard K.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Psychology</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (85 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Globally, over 70% of adults are exposed to one or more potentially traumatic events over the course of their lifetime (Benjet et al., 2016). However, only a minority of individuals who experience a traumatic event will develop Posttraumatic Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD; Kilpatrick et al., 2013). PTSD as a diagnostic disorder is traditionally designated using a binary "diagnosis" or "no diagnosis" approach, and related conditions are evaluated in the same manner. This traditional "present" or "absent" approach to pathology fails to take into account PTSD symptom course beyond meeting threshold DSM-5 minimum diagnostic criteria and can be a limiting approach to pathology. In actuality, there are multiple discrete outcome trajectories that can result after exposure to a traumatic event that the DSM diagnosis vs. no diagnosis approach cannot adequately illustrate (Bonanno, 2004; Galatzer-Levy et al., 2018). Aside from a resilient response (i.e. no lifetime PTSD) the two most frequently observed response trajectories to trauma exposure that confer symptoms include recovery after a period of experiencing symptoms (i.e. remitted PTSD) and prolonged endurance of chronic symptoms (Galatzer-Levy et al., 2018). For the present study, we utilized the Epidemiologic Survey on Alcohol and Related Factors-III (NESARC-III), a large, nationally-representative sample, to investigate psychiatric comorbidities, socio-demographic determinants, trauma characteristics, and treatment-related behaviors as a function of PTSD chronicity. We divided the trauma exposed sample (N = 23,707) into three symptom trajectory path groups: Resilient (N = 21,488), Remitted (N = 560), and Chronic (N = 1,659) and examined group differences using both a traditional, categorical approach to psychopathology (diagnosis vs. no diagnosis) and a transdiagnostic, hierarchical framework constructed on a gradation of increased covariation; the recently-developed Hierarchical Taxonomy of Psychopathology (HiTOP; Kotov et al., 2017). Consistent with hypotheses, the traditional approach revealed that the Remitted group was more highly correlated with a greater number of comorbid disorders than the Resilient group, and Chronic PTSD was associated with a greater number of comorbid disorders than the Resilient trajectory path and the Remitted path when examined via discrete diagnoses. Participants who identified childhood sexual abuse as their worst trauma type were at significantly greater odds of developing chronic PTSD than never develop a threshold-level PTSD diagnosis over the course of their lifetime, and those with adult sexual assault as their worst trauma type also more likely to develop Chronic PTSD than belong to the Resilient group. Contrary to study hypotheses, neither childhood sexual abuse nor adult sexual assault were significantly differentiated odds between belonging to the Chronic PTSD vs. Remitted PTSD. In terms of HiTOP analyses, the Chronic group exhibited a greater number of psychiatric criteria per spectra and subfactor compared to the Remitted and Resilient groups. Additionally, the Chronic group exhibited a greater number psychiatric spectra in the fear, distress, and substance abuse subfactor, compared to the Remitted and Resilient groups. Taken altogether, the modern, HiTOP approach appeared to provide a more nuanced, comprehensive conceptualization of the differences between trajectory groups compared to the dichotomous diagnostic systems approach. Results from the present study uncovered comorbidities associated with PTSD using a chronicity-graded perspective and both traditional and transdiagnostic approaches. Downstream, study findings may help identify individuals at risk for greater levels of post-trauma clinical distress and impairment, and could ultimately aid in developing targeted treatment and prevention efforts. Future studies may wish to examine a longitudinal sample in order to explore the development of symptom trajectory paths over time and within the context of a timeline of co-occurring diagnoses and events.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Psychology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 29, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Chronic PTSD, HiTOP, PTSD, Remitted PTSD, Resilient, Trauma</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jesse R. Cougle, Professor Directing Dissertation; David W. Eccles, University Representative; David S. March, Committee Member; Christopher J. Patrick, Committee Member; Richard K. Wagner, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027067">
      <topic>Clinical psychology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Stentz_fsu_0071E_18135</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Psychology</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
