<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Adaptations of Arterial Function and Endothelial Glycocalyx to High-Sodium Diet in Mice</title>
      <nonSort>The</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-1761-2172</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Zheng</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Xiangyu</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dmachin">
      <namePart type="family">Machin</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Daniel</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/pchase">
      <namePart type="family">Chase</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">P. Bryant</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/bsgordon">
      <namePart type="family">Gordon</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Bradley S.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mparvatiyar">
      <namePart type="family">Parvatiyar</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michelle</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Health, Nutrition, and Food Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (121 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >INTRODUCTION: Cardiovascular disease (CVD) is the leading cause of death in the United States and excess sodium intake is a major contributor for CVD. A central feature of CVD is arterial dysfunction (i.e., elevated systolic blood pressure [BP], aortic stiffening, and endothelial dysfunction). Previously, we have shown that 12 weeks of high-sodium (HS) diet induces these arterial dysfunction phenotypes in genetically diverse, outbred UM-HET3 mice. Arterial dysfunction is suggested to be preceded by a deteriorated endothelial glycocalyx, which is a negatively charged gel-like structure bound to the luminal endothelium. Glycocalyx is hypothesized to buffer sodium cation in the blood stream, but excess blood sodium can in turn deteriorate endothelial glycocalyx. Indeed, we have previously shown that 12 weeks of HS diet deteriorates glycocalyx barrier function and decreases its thickness. However, the time course of HS diet-induced arterial dysfunction and glycocalyx deterioration remains elusive. Dietary sodium reduction has a well-established BP-lowering effect, but the reduction in BP is usually marginal. Other studies have also shown that HS-diet induced elevation in BP appears to be largely irreversible after HS diet withdrawal. It remains unknown whether the irreversibility exists in HS diet-induced arterial dysfunction and glycocalyx deterioration in UM-HET3 mice. In addition, we have previously shown that glycocalyx-targeted supplementation Endocalyx fully reverses age-related arterial dysfunction and glycocalyx deterioration in old mice, but the treatment effect of Endocalyx on HS diet-induced arterial dysfunction and glycocalyx deterioration remains unknown. PURPOSE: Therefore, we sought to determine the adaptations of arterial function and endothelial glycocalyx to HS diet consumption and withdrawal in UM-HET3 mice and explore the effect of Endocalyx as a potential therapeutic for HS diet-induced arterial dysfunction and glycocalyx deterioration. METHODS: Male and female UM-HET3 mice underwent 12 weeks of low-sodium (LS) or HS diet or 6 weeks of HS diet followed by 6 weeks of LS diet (HSLS) or 6 weeks of HS diet followed by 6 weeks of LS diet plus Endocalyx supplementation (HSLS+E). RESULTS: Firstly, we observed elevated urine concentration of sodium and potassium in HS compared to LS and HSLS mice (P&lt;0.05), and they were at similar level in HSLS compared to LS mice (P&gt;0.05). Systolic BP, diastolic BP, and heart rate as well as their respective diurnal variation, as measured by telemetry system, showed no difference between all group (P&gt;0.05). Aortic stiffness, determined by aortic pulse wave velocity (PWV), was increased in HS and HSLS mice after week 2 compared to respective baseline and continued to increase through week 8 in both groups (P&lt;0.05). Then, aortic PWV plateaued out after week 8 in HSLS group (P&gt;0.05) but continued to increase through week 12 in HS group (P&lt;0.05). Aortic PWV was higher in HS and HSLS compared to LS mice at weeks 4-12 and it became higher in HS compared to HSLS mice at week 12 (P&lt;0.05). From week 0-6, Δ systolic BP, as measured by tail-cuff method, was higher in HS, HSLS, and HSLS+E compared to LS mice (P&lt;0.05) but was similar between themselves (P&gt;0.05). From week 0-12, Δ systolic BP was higher in HS and HSLS compared to LS and HSLS mice (P&lt;0.05), but it was similar in HSLS+E compared to LS mice (P&gt;0.05). From week 0-6, Δ aortic PWV was higher in HS, HSLS, and HSLS+E compared to LS mice (P&lt;0.05) but was similar between themselves (P&gt;0.05). From week 0-12, Δ aortic PWV was higher in HS, HSLS, and HSLS+E compared to LS mice (P&lt;0.05), but it was lower in HSLS and HSLS+E compared to HS mice and lower in HSLS+E compared to HSLS mice (P&lt;0.05). Aortic histology revealed that collagen content was higher in HS and HSLS compared to LS mice (P&lt;0.05), but it was similar between HS and HSLS mice (P&gt;0.05). Carotid artery endothelium dependent dilation was lower in HS and HSLS compared to LS mice (P&lt;0.05), but it was similar in HSLS+E compared to LS mice (P&gt;0.05). Endothelium-independent dilation was similar between all groups (P&gt;0.05). Glycocalyx barrier function, as measured by perfused boundary region, was worse in HS compared to LS, HSLS, and HSLS+E mice (P&lt;0.05), but it was similar in HSLS and HSLS+E compared to LS mice (P&gt;0.05). Lastly, glycocalyx thickness was lower in HS mice (P&lt;0.05), similar in HSLS mice (P&gt;0.05), and higher in HSLS+E (P&lt;0.05) compared to LS mice. CONCLUSIONS: In summary, HS diet only partially reverses the arterial dysfunction despite of a fully reversed glycocalyx barrier function and thickness in genetically diverse, outbred UM-HET3 mice. When HS diet withdrawal was combined with glycocalyx-targeted supplementation Endocalyx supplementation, it further reversed the HS diet-induced arterial dysfunction and glycocalyx deterioration in these mice. Taken together, these findings provide evidence that dietary sodium reduction when combined with treatment like Endocalyx can largely reverse the adverse adaptations of HS diet consumption in arterial function and endothelial glycocalyx, which may be a novel strategy to lower the risk of CVD in humans that consume a HS diet.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Health, Nutrition, and Food Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 12, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Daniel R. Machin, Professor Directing Dissertation; Prescott B. Chase, University Representative; Bradley Gordon, Committee Member; Michelle Parvatiyar, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85101679">
      <topic>Physiology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Zheng_fsu_0071E_18822</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Nutrition, Food, and Exercise Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
