<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Degradation of Per- and Polyfluoroalkyl Substances with Nonthermal Plasma in a Gas-Liquid Film Reactor</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-7886-5552</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Gallan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Rachel O.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n84134993">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Locke</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Bruce R.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dhallinan">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hallinan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Daniel T.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="termsOfAddress">Jr.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ytang2">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Tang</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Youneng</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>FAMU-FSU College of Engineering</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Chemical and Biomedical Engineering</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (111 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Perfluorinated carbons are hazardous molecules that have contaminated ground water systems and become a prevalent environmental issue. One group of perfluorinated carbons is a class of molecules referred to as per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS), which have been used for decades in applications such as firefighting foams, waterproof coatings, nonstick cookware, carpets, and many others. The wide use of PFAS has led to their large accumulation in the environment. Due to this accumulation and the release into the aquifer, PFAS has become a concern in most water purification systems. Recently developed methods to degrade PFAS include advanced oxidation and reduction techniques such as photocatalysis, sonolysis, electrochemical reduction, and nonthermal plasma. Our work focuses on the degradation of PFAS with nonthermal plasma. Two example PFAS compounds, perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA) and perfluorooctanesulfonic acid (PFOS) are not only major pollutants but they are often used as model PFAS compounds, and they are the focus for this work. In this study, we use a nonthermal plasma reactor with flowing liquid and gas phases and a nanosecond pulsed power supply to degrade PFAS compounds in water. The plasma is generated with a pulsed power supply capable of variation of the input voltage, frequency, and pulse width. Through changing the input electrical pulse forming properties, we can change the plasma characteristics such as electron density, electron energy, and plasma gas temperature. The non-thermal plasma generates many different reactive chemical species such as ·OH, ·H, e-, and eaq- that may degrade PFOA and PFOS. This work shows that PFOA and PFOS are degraded into several daughter products of smaller carbon chains, and mineralization products including carbon dioxide and fluoride (F-). This work shows that PFOA and PFOS degradation are affected by concentration and pulse frequency. PFOA and PFOA are surfactants and have large surface activities. Higher surface activity leads to higher degradation and mineralization because of increased adsorption at the interface where the plasma occurs. The input frequency of the power supply changes the plasma properties and therefore PFOA and PFOS were shown to have maximum degradation percentages of 89.6% and 96%, respectively, at 2 kHz frequency. Because the degradation is dependent on initial concentration and the input frequency, these setting can be used to optimize the reactor. For comparison with other methods, the values of energy yield and EE/O are used to describe the system efficiency. Energy yield is the molar amount of the compound degraded or produced (depending on the target compound) per joule of energy. EE/O is the amount of energy used per volume per log order reduction of contaminant. The best-case energy yield and EE/O values are 6.61x10-10 mol/J and 2.5 kWh/m3(order) for PFOA and 6.691x10-10 mol/J and1.7 kWh/m3(order) for PFOS, which are better or comparable to the best reported methods for PFAS degradation. Ground water and leachate samples from field sites were treated to demonstrate the applicability of the reactor. The ground water towards the higher chain compounds, and will degrade them in order of decreasing chain length. PFOA mass transfer and reaction rates were modeled in the reactor to analyze the factors affecting the frequency and concentration effects. The model shows that the upper limit of PFOA degradation is likely mass transfer limited, but it fails to show the drop-in degradation with increasing frequency or the shift in optimal degradation with decreasing concentration. These results are encouraging for the practical application of this plasma reactor in real world remediation processes. This study furthers the understanding of non-thermal degradation of PFAS, and leads to its future use in water purification systems.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Chemical &amp; Biomedical Engineering in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Science.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 21, 2022.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Bruce R. Locke, Professor Directing Thesis; Daniel Hallinan, Committee Member; Youneng Tang, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85043176">
      <mods:topic>Engineering</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022900">
      <mods:topic>Chemical engineering</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044170">
      <mods:topic>Environmental engineering</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Summer 2022_Gallan_fsu_0071N_16954</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Science</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemical and Biomedical Engineering</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-01-27T10:52:08.836275-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
