<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>National Medievalism in Russia and Turkey</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-9634-7807</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Lanaghan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Nathaniel P.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nb2008002466">
      <namePart type="family">Romanchuk</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Robert</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr91045296">
      <namePart type="family">Johnson</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">David F. (David Frame)</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1956-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2009036864">
      <namePart type="family">Wakamiya</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lisa Ryoko</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1969-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (67 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>There is a growing trend of invoking the Middle Ages to ground modern identity in something familiar and historic (Utz, 2022). In an increasingly interconnected yet insecure world, Russia and Turkey have emerged as regional powers, or in the case of Russia, a great power with imperial aspirations, and are attempting to secure their place in the new multipolar world order. Dmitri Trenin (2013) suggests there is an "astonishing likeness" in the twenty-first century development of Russia and Turkey. These countries have adopted Western institutions and had, at one point, sought integration with the West. At present, however, disillusionment with the Western model and a desire to restore past glories of empire have encouraged the governments of these nations to distance themselves from Western influence, setting them down a path hostile to its values and concerns. This is compounded by what Russian author Eugene Vodolazkin (2016b) calls the "ever-present twofold issue of excessive individualization and the secularization of life" (p. 35) synonymous with liberal society that the ruling governments of Russia and Turkey present as detrimental to traditional culture and values underpinning their civilization-states. While a wide variety of positions exist within the respective cultural and political discourses in Russia and Turkey, the governments of Presidents Vladimir Putin and Recep Tayyip Erdogan have instrumentalized mythologized narratives of national identity, rooted in the Middle Ages, to decouple themselves from and "otherize" the West in pursuit of revanchist foreign policies and autocratic domestic policies. The result has been the top-down imposition of national identity founded on the myths of the glorious past. Reaching back to the Middle Ages, which is regarded as the era of "civilizational birth" for Russia and Turkey, myths, characters, symbols, and values of the imagined past are being reconstructed to question the "individualized and secularized" character of modern society. Governments and institutions have sponsored cultural medievalism in media, with TV and film being among the most popular and widespread. State-sponsored medievalism has become a silver screen staple in these countries, with shows like Sophia (София, 2016) in Russia and The Great Seljuk (Büyük Selçuklu, 2020) in Turkey being financed partly or entirely by their respective governments. Literature, or more specifically books by elite writers, however, remain outside of overt government control. In this study, I will consider/treat/examine Laurus¬ (published 2012, translated 2015) by Eugene Vodolazkin and ¬My Name Is Red (published 1998, translated 2001) by Orhan Pamuk – two titles with stories set in the Middle Ages and themes that relate to the questioning of national character, identity, and self. ¬My Name Is Red was written before neo-Ottoman medievalism in popular culture became a widespread, state-sanctioned phenomenon in Turkey. Laurus, conversely, was written when medievalism was instrumentalized by the state to legitimize concepts such as the "Russian world." I will determine how these works of medievalism summon the Middle Ages to respond to issues of national identity and provide insight on the author's positions vis-à-vis their respective government and institutions. This analysis seeks to identify and label a trend of invoking the Middle Ages in Russia and Turkey under the framework of what I propose to call "national medievalism." I will provide examples of national medievalism in context and explain how it is utilized in the interrogation and propagation of national identities. This study of medievalism will provide insight on how the Middle Ages are perceived and instrumentalized in Russia and Turkey and provide context to the rise of popular medievalism in their respective cultural discourses.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Modern Languages and Linguistics in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Arts.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 28, 2022.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">Erdogan, Identity, Medievalism, Putin, Russia, Turkey</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Robert L. Romanchuk, Professor Directing Thesis; David F. Johnson, Committee Member; Lisa Ryoko Wakamiya, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077534">
      <topic>Comparative literature</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85123354">
      <geographic>Slavic countries</geographic>
   </subject>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090514">
      <geographic>Middle East</geographic>
      <topic>Study and teaching</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2022_Lanaghan_fsu_0071N_17246</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Arts</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Modern Languages and Linguistics</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-10-10T17:55:50.20129-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
