<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Early Applicants</title>
      <subTitle>Does Timing of the Admissions Application Impact First-Time, 1st-Year Enrollment and Success in Open-Admissions Institutions</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-0986-8530</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">McCown</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Amber S.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2004141559">
      <namePart type="family">Cox</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Bradley E.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jpmyers">
      <namePart type="family">Myers</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">John P. (John Patrick)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/cmokher">
      <namePart type="family">Mokher</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Christine G.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lperezfelkner">
      <namePart type="family">Perez-Felkner</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lara</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (78 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>Two-year state and community colleges provide convenient and affordable educational opportunities with open admissions policies, which make them "value-added institutions that are uniquely different than traditional colleges and universities" (Grubbs, 2020, p. 205). Students across the nation enroll in 2-year colleges to pursue their academic goals because of distinct variations, which include flexible admissions and enrollment policies. However, the lack of deadlines at open-access institutions may contribute to entry and retention challenges for students who apply late, particularly for those who may be un- or under-prepared for college. Few studies have considered the relationship between admissions application timing, characteristics of traditional first-time in college students, and 1st-semester academic outcomes, which was the focus for this research. The study population was chosen because admissions offices have greater access to high school students through recruitment efforts such as college fairs and classroom visits. Central to this work were the hypotheses that applicants who apply early in their senior year tend to have higher high school GPAs, are more likely to enroll in the fall following high school graduation with better 1st-semester outcomes and are more inclined to return in the subsequent spring semester. The study involved an examination of admissions application data for 3,479 first-time, 1st-semester applicants who applied to a public college with open access policies requiring only a standard high school diploma or GED. Demographic data, high school academic performance, and factors related to college preparation were collected from the institution's student information system and the date the admissions application was submitted. The study population was limited to high school seniors who applied to the institution for the fall semester immediately following graduation. The hypotheses were analyzed using chi-square tests, ANOVA, and a series of regression models. Variables related to admissions application timing, which were segmented into distinct recruitment periods to include the fall prior to high school graduation, spring of high school graduation, and summer after high school graduation, were used across all models. These periods correspond to blocks of time representing opportunities for admissions offices to implement targeted and actionable strategies to influence first-time student enrollments. The analysis of the models suggested variations in student characteristics across the recruitment periods. Students who apply to an institution with open access policies in the fall prior to their high school graduation tend to enter with higher GPAs and although they enroll at a lower rate, they are more likely to attempt and earn more credit hours in their 1st semester. Additionally, earlier applicants tend to have higher 1st semester GPAs and yet are less likely to return for the subsequent spring semester. In contrast, applicants who apply to the institution in the summer after high school graduation have lower high school GPAs and 1st semester academic outcomes if they enrolled. The results of the study indicate applicant characteristics vary depending on when first-time, 1st-year students apply to the institution, and these findings may influence strategies admissions offices at open-access institutions employ to attract and enroll traditional high school students while also considering initiatives to increase first semester student outcomes.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Education.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 30, 2022.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">Admissions, Open Access, Student Recruitment</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Bradley Cox, Professor Directing Dissertation; John Myers, University Representative; Christine Mokher, Committee Member; Lara Perez-Felkner, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029211">
      <topic>Community colleges</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041065">
      <topic>Education, Higher</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009102068">
      <topic>Education, Higher</topic>
      <topic>Administration</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2022_McCown_fsu_0071E_17126</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Education</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-10-10T17:55:50.20129-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
