<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Bridging Communities and Scholars through CBPR</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>A Systematic Review of Communication and Participation Practices within Community-Based Participatory Research Teams</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-3705-565X</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Huse</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Laura-Kate Gonyea</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jwendorfmuhamad">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Muhamad</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jessica Wendorf</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ubunz">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Bunz</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Ulla</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2010074127">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Coutts</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Christopher</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/krdale">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Dale</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Katherine R.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Communication and Information</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>School of Communication</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (133 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Community-based participatory research (CBPR) is an approach to health research that prioritizes translation and community partner participation. The field of CBPR is multidisciplinary, so traditional definitions of communication within CBPR have focused on information transfer. However, communication is a dynamic and multifaceted process with multiple levels of influence. The goals of this dissertation are threefold: 1) to apply communication discipline's perspective of communication to better understand how CBPR teams communicate, 2) to examine the factors that affect communication and participation within CBPR teams, and 3) to identify patterns that will contribute to the development of a theory of CBPR team communication and participation. Through a systematic review study of N=105 articles, patterns of communication and participation were identified. Logistics can communicate equity between the scholars and the community partners and facilitate effective communication. Frequent meetings and communication strengthen the communication of the team. Information sharing is imperative for work to be completed on these research projects. However, there was little evidence that transformation through the process of CBPR was valued as a goal by the CBPR teams. Communication and not simply information transfer should be a priority and a goal for CBPR teams. When starting new CBPR partnerships, creating clear expectations and a shared language can reduce miscommunication. Not many CBPR teams explain how they continue to ensure effective communication after initially discussion boundaries and duties, however. These early findings suggest that throughout the CBPR process, the intercultural teams of CBPR might be forming a new group, however more research is needed to explore the impact of interdependence and time on group identity. Community members frequently participate in CBPR as an expert in their community and local knowledge. Having teams train both in research practices and in local knowledge ensures that the team is co-learning. Boundaries to participation include university IRB and conflicting goals between scholars and community partners. Having community members involved in the creation of research questions for the project is related to higher levels of involvement in other stages of research. Community participation in the research process does not seem to be hindered based purely on the research methodology chosen, but non-traditional research methodologies did have higher levels of community participation than other research methods within conducting the research. Finally, indigenous community populations were more involved in the ethical approval stages of research than any other target population. These findings do serve as the first step in applying communication and group theory to CBPR teams, and do help us to better understand how teams are communicating and ensuring participation. Kurt Lewin (1951) said, "there's nothing so practical as a good theory" (p. 169). The findings of this dissertation serve as the first step in attempting to understand the communication and participation practices within CBPR teams. A significant finding of this dissertation, however, is that the reporting methods for CBPR team communication and participation is lacking. Peterson (2010) argued that until CBPR scholars are able to define what true participation is, and change the perceptions of what rigorous research looks like, CBPR will continue to be used as a trendy term that will perpetuate the status quo of research practices. This will hurt the goal of CBPR, which is to create social change (through the reduction of health inequities) for marginalized. The field of CBPR should consider changing the reporting practices of CBPR reports to better facilitate reporting the process of CBPR.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the School of Communication in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">November 4, 2021.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Community health partnerships, community-academic collaboration, Community-based participatory research, inter-cultural communication, partnership process, team communication</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jessica Wendorf Muhamad, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Ulla Bunz, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Christopher Coutts, University Representative; Katherine Dale, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029027">
      <mods:topic>Communication</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85059537">
      <mods:topic>Health education</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">2021_Fall_Huse_fsu_0071E_16836</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Communication</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-05-23T16:09:53.352975-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
