<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Mercury Contamination and Its Relation to Trophic Ecology and Anthropogenic Pollution in Coastal and Deep Sea Shark Communities</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-9093-2973</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Imhoff</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Johanna Leigh</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dgrubbs2">
      <namePart type="family">Grubbs</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">R. Dean</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n89605460">
      <namePart type="family">Chanton</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jeffrey P.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/miller">
      <namePart type="family">Miller</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Thomas E.</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Professor of Biological Science)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86861195">
      <namePart type="family">Travis</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Joseph</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1953-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/winn">
      <namePart type="family">Winn</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Alice A.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Biological Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (89 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>The effect of changing anthropogenic mercury emissions on marine wildlife is of broad interest. Methylmercury can cause reproductive and neurological damage and biomagnifies in food webs. Mercury availability in the Pacific Ocean has been increasing and therefore could be expected to increase in marine fishes. In Hawaii, tunas have shown increases proportional to increasing oceanic mercury over several decades. Historical data on shark muscle mercury is also available for Hawaii, presenting an opportunity for comparison in a long-lived upper trophic level cartilaginous fish. Muscle samples were opportunistically collected from sandbar sharks in 2003-2005 for mercury analysis and comparison with published data from 1971. Mercury contamination was similar in sandbar sharks collected in the two time periods, in contrast to tunas. Sandbar sharks collected in 2003-2005 had a higher observed rate of stillborn embryos than previously documented. Since mercury can cause reproductive toxicity, muscle mercury contamination was quantified in available sandbar shark embryos. Contamination was similar in stillborn and viable embryos, indicating that mercury toxicity was likely not the cause of embryo death. Mercury does not appear to have changed in sandbar sharks and the observed frequency of stillborn sharks does not appear to be due to increasing mercury emissions over three decades. Deep sea chondricthyans comprise nearly half of global chondrichthyan fauna but have been researched relatively less than their coastal and pelagic counterparts. As long-lived mesopredators and apex predators in their food webs, deep sea shark can bioaccumulate high levels of mercury in their tissues. Mercury was measured in six species of relatively abundant deep sea sharks in the GOM that inhabit the continental shelf edge to the continental slope. To attempt to address whether the Deepwater Horizon oil spill indirectly affected bioavailability of methylmercury in GOM, the same or closely related species were also analyzed from regions not affected by the oil spill. Overall, Mustelus sinusmexicanus had the lowest mercury among the GOM sharks analyzed, and Squalus clarkae had the highest. The remaining four species were similar to one another in their mercury contamination. Regional comparisons revealed similar contamination between M. canis canis in the GOM and M. canis insularis in Eleuthera. Eleuthera S. cubensis had similar mercury contamination to GOM S. clarkae, to which they were closer in size than GOM S. cubensis. GOM Centrophorus granulosus had higher mercury contamination than Virginia C. granulosus but this was only marginally significant. There was a slight and non-significant increase in mercury with depth in the GOM. M. canis caught on the east side of De Soto Canyon had significantly higher mercury than those caught on the west side of De Soto Canyon. The opposite pattern was seen in C. uyato, with higher mercury concentrations on the west side of the canyon, but these results may be strongly influenced by sample size for both species. Since mercury bioaccumulation in organisms is tightly linked to biomagnification, mercury studies are often coupled with trophic ecology studies using light stable isotopes as tracers. Since animals vary in the quantity of lipids that they store in their tissues, and since the presence of lipids can affect δ¹³C signatures, it is necessary to explore these effects to correctly interpret δ¹³C results. A particular challenge for chondrichthyan fishes is that they store isotopically light nitrogenous wastes in their tissues for osmoregulation, and this can affect the interpretation of δ15N, sometimes leading to inaccurate interpretation of trophic level. The effects of lipids and nitrogenous wastes on stable isotope analysis of chondrichthyan fishes has been an important aspect of trophic ecology research on this group. The effects of lipid extraction, urea extraction, and combined lipid and urea extraction compared to bulk tissue were tested on a coastal and deep sea teleost and a coastal and deep sea elasmobranch as representatives that might be included in coast to deep sea food web studies. Since mercury analysis requires the same initial muscle tissue handling steps as stable isotope analysis (SIA), the effects of treatments on mercury quantification were also tested. The results suggest that chemical lipid extraction is necessary for accurate interpretation of SIA results in coastal and deep sea teleosts and elasmobranchs and that urea was extracted sufficiently during the lipid extraction, therefore additional urea extraction steps are not necessary. Additionally, it may be possible for researchers to use leftover treated muscle from SIA to obtain accurate mercury results. Future research on trophic ecology including SIA informed by this research may help to provide context for mercury findings in GOM deep sea sharks.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Biological Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 2, 2021.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">deep sea, elasmobranch, mercury, shark, trophic ecology</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">R. Dean Grubbs, Professor Directing Dissertation; Jeffrey P. Chanton, University Representative; Thomas E. Miller, Committee Member; Joseph Travis, Committee Member; Alice A. Winn, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040752">
      <topic>Ecology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136331">
      <topic>Toxicology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2021_Summer_Imhoff_fsu_0071E_16699</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Biological Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-01-31T17:03:20.741646-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
