<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Sisterhood, Safe Spaces and Self-Affirmations</title>
      <subTitle>How Black Women Practice Self-Care in Response to Racism and Discrimination</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <namePart type="family">Jackson</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Taylor</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016023092">
      <namePart type="family">Davis</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Katrinell</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2013023462">
      <namePart type="family">Plant</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ashby</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nb2012016923">
      <namePart type="family">Rohlinger</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Deana A.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/sbuggs">
      <namePart type="family">Buggs</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Shantel</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Sociology</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (206 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>This dissertation examines how Black women cope with the negative psychological impacts of racism and discrimination in their everyday lives. Black women experience specific forms of stress due to their identities as both racial and gender minorities. Experiencing discrimination leads to feelings of hopelessness, depression, anxiety, and PTSD. These negative emotions are difficult to manage, especially given the stigma related to mental health treatment among Black women, a lack of culturally competent mental healthcare, and the high costs of therapy. Scholars have discussed a variety of coping strategies, such as spirituality, relying on social support, and adopting individual personality traits to alleviate negative stressors from racism and discrimination. The purpose of this dissertation is to develop a better understanding of how Black women define and engage in self-care to mitigate negative psychological outcomes from racism and discrimination. I utilize relational cultural theory as my primary framework to demonstrate Black women receive an increased desire for connection, resources, and knowledge, as well as experience psychological growth through relational resilience. I contribute to scholarship focused on how Black women manage social inequality by investigating how Black women construct counternarratives against controlling images by discussing how they care for themselves online. I conducted 25 in-depth interviews with Black women between the ages of 18 and 35 to examine how they engage in self-care in their daily lives, as well as their digital habits. I also performed a content analysis of a total of 415 blog entries and 3,300 tweets from two platforms, Black Girl in Om and Women's Health, to analyze differences in self-care advice based on race and type of platform. Interviews demonstrate that, although Black women participants gain access to resources and community on social media, the overall toxicity of the internet hinders Black women from taking full advantage of the benefits digital platforms have to offer. Harassment, ridicule, and disrespect unrelated to self-care on social media prompted Black women in the study to take a break from these platforms. Through the content analysis, I find Black women share resources and personal experiences about how discrimination negatively impacts their mental health through blog posts and user comments. Through primary themes of self-affirmations, introspection, and sisterhood, I find self-care on digital platforms catered to Black women emphasizes group-based coping. In contrast, on Women's Health self-care content is rooted in individualism and capitalism. Mainstream conceptualizations of self-care on Women's Health do not promote relational bonds and mutual empowerment in similar ways because the social context of negative psychological outcomes are not explicitly outlined in the advice offered. As a result, users on the Women's Health platform receive messages that emphasize autonomy, self-discipline, and internal control, which does little to promote connection in order to heal. Overall, Black women engage in relational resilience, online and offline, to take care of themselves and cope with racism and discrimination.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Sociology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 25, 2021.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Katrinell Davis, Professor Directing Dissertation; Ashby Plant, University Representative; Deana Rohlinger, Committee Member; Shantel Buggs, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124200">
      <topic>Sociology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2021_Summer_Jackson_fsu_0071E_16617</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Sociology</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-01-31T17:03:20.741646-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
