<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Generating and Evaluating Camouflage Patterns for Littoral Environments of Northwest Florida</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-3571-5850</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Jermyn</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jacqueline</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/foo">
      <namePart type="family">Foo</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Simon Y.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2003129868">
      <namePart type="family">Meyer-Bäse</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Anke</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/oanubi">
      <namePart type="family">Anubi</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Olugbenga Moses</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2002042562">
      <namePart type="family">Kwan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Bing Woon</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1953-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>FAMU-FSU College of Engineering</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (237 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Historically, soldiers wore decorative uniforms to distinguish between friend and foe on the battlefield. During World War I, heavy casualties caused the French Army to recruit artists to develop camouflage patterns for their battlefield uniforms. Since then, military camouflage uniforms have been universally implemented for forest, desert, grassland, ocean, and snowy environments. Although many nations have international boundaries that border a large body of water, very limited research has been conducted to develop camouflage patterns for littoral environments. Currently, camouflage pattern effectiveness are evaluated by using the camouflage similarity index (CSI). This technique, however, has drawbacks due to the heterogeneity of camouflage designs and the under-representation of environmental features. Hence, the two overall goals for this research are to (i) create novel littoral camouflage patterns for Northwest Florida's coastal environments, and to (ii) develop new camouflage assessment procedures. In the first goal, new littoral camouflage patterns were modeled after eight variations of military camouflage designs. These patterns were created by inserting dominant environmental colors for Northwest Florida's littoral environments into eight custom-built digital camouflage templates. The dominant colors were extracted from three custom-built images datasets for Northwest Florida's estuarine, sandy, and combination estuarine-sandy coastlines. Twenty-four new littoral camouflage patterns were created by using these custom-made templates. These camouflage patterns were then used to produce the 64x64-pixel camouflage swatches, the 128x128-pixel camouflage patterns, and the 256x256-pixel camouflage patterns training datasets. Each training dataset had three variations for Northwest Florida's three types of shorelines. As a result, nine custom-made training datasets were produced to train generative models to output novel littoral camouflage patterns. These generative models included a variational autoencoder (VAE), a generative adversarial network (GAN), and a deep convolutional generative adversarial network (DCGAN). The second research goal was to develop new camouflage pattern evaluation procedures. A novel camouflage assessment method (NCAM) was created. It overcame the CSI drawbacks by achieving a better representation of a camouflage design and a natural environment. The NCAMs for each novel camouflage pattern were sorted in ascending order. The most effective pattern had the lowest NCAM and a ranking of one. The least effective pattern had a NCAM of one and a ranking of 81. A new camouflage pattern rating system that uses a holistic approach for assessing camouflage patterns was then developed. It was based on NCAMs, runtimes, absence or presence of unusual features, and design appearances. This rating system could be adapted to incorporate other camouflage assessment methods to rank patterns. It has seven categories ranging from "best" to "worst". Each novel camouflage pattern was assessed by using this rating system. The impact of hyperparameters on pattern effectiveness was analyzed. The overall effectiveness of camouflage patterns, generative models, the impact of training dataset pixel size on pattern ratings, and the effect of training epochs on pattern appearances were also addressed. There were eight contributions for this investigation, and they were grouped into five categories. The first area was to develop a glossary of littoral terms that provided definitions and locations of Northwest Florida coastal features. It could be used for educational purposes and for other types of littoral research to include beach re-nourishment, wildlife biology, and ecological research. The second involved developing two types of custom-built datasets because they are unavailable in the public domain. The littoral images and camouflage training datasets were required for creating and evaluating new camouflage patterns. The third contribution involved creating digital camouflage templates to facilitate creating new patterns. These templates are also not available in the public domain. The fourth involved creating new littoral camouflage patterns by using two different procedures. The first was to insert extracted colors from the littoral images datasets into the digital templates. The second was to create novel camouflage patterns by training generative models on the custom-built camouflage training datasets. Currently, littoral camouflage patterns are unavailable for use by militaries. The fifth contribution area involved developing two camouflage pattern evaluation procedures: NCAM and camouflage pattern rating system. The NCAM overcomes CSI drawbacks to achieve a better representation of a camouflage pattern and an environment. The camouflage pattern rating system is a holistic approach developed to evaluate camouflage pattern effectiveness. It takes into account NCAMs, runtimes, design artifacts, and design appearances. This rating system could be adapted to incorporate other camouflage assessment methods, such as the combined NCAM-SSIM procedure.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">October 12, 2022.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Camouflage Assessment, Camouflage Patterns, Color Extraction, Generative Models, Littoral Environment, Machine Learning</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Simon Foo, Professor Directing Dissertation; Anke Meyer-Baese, University Representative; Olugbenga Anubi, Committee Member; Bing Kwan, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041666">
      <topic>Electrical engineering</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Jermyn_fsu_0071E_17509</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Electrical and Computer Engineering</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
