<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Well-Defined Lignin-Based Biodegradable Polymer</title>
      <subTitle>Synthesis and Precise Control of Properties</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-5355-4953</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Kim</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sundol</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/hchung">
      <namePart type="family">Chung</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Hoyong</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kennemur">
      <namePart type="family">Kennemur</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Justin Glenn</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jguan">
      <namePart type="family">Guan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jingjiao</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jali">
      <namePart type="family">Ali</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jamel</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>FAMU-FSU College of Engineering</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemical and Biomedical Engineering</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (165 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >The issue of non-degradable petroleum-based plastics waste is a global challenge that requires urgent attention due to its harmful impact on humans and the environment. To overcome this challenge, biomass-based materials have received great attention these days. Lignin is not only one of the important biomasses due to its abundance, low price, and rich aromatic group, but also an important material that can be used as a raw material to produce biodegradable polymers. However, lignin modification is not well understood or characterized due to its complex chemical structure, limiting the use of lignin. Especially, poorly defined excessive reaction sites of lignin cause uncontrolled crosslinking in lignin to make thermoset polymers. This dissertation presents novel methods to achieve the advanced biodegradable lignin-based polyesters with covalent bond via 1) precise and well-defined chemical modification of natural lignin and 2) controlling the crosslinking density of lignin. Then, by combining the methods of 1) and 2), we can develop 100 % biomass-based biodegradable polymer. First, we developed a new and precisely defined synthetic protocol which integrates lignin and poly(ethylene brassylate) (PEB) to make a lignin-graft-PEB. The lignin was chemically modified by sebacic acid to introduce a carboxylic acid functionality. Abundant hydroxyl groups on lignin were used for its modification. A relatively unexplored and inexpensive castor oil-derived polymer, PEB was prepared by ring-opening polymerization of ethylene brassylate in the presence of a catalyst, 1,5,7-triazabicyclo[4.4.0]dec-5-ene. The prepared PEB was graft copolymerization onto modified lignin through an acid anhydride bond. The new polymer shows optimal melting temperature (78 ℃) that enables an easy thermal process. Mechanical properties of the new lignin-graft-PEB can be changed by altering the molecular weight (Mn) of PEB and mass ratios of lignin and PEB. The highest modulus is 471.99 MPa, which is 3-folds higher than low-density polyethylene. However, blended polymer without covalent linkage shows poor mechanical properties (220.7 Mpa of young's modulus) due to the microlevel phase separations within the polymer matrix. Second, we developed a highly efficient crosslinking control method by using a capping agent, acetic acid. Acetic acid capped the hydroxyl group to reduce the number of excessive reaction sites in the lignin, and succinic acid is used to introduce carboxylic acid functionality. Using this method, we prepared succinic acid-modified lignin-graft-poly(ethylene glycol) with different amounts of a capping agent. The lignin-based polymer synthesis has two steps: 1) lignin modification with succinic acid and capping agent and 2) graft copolymerization of PEG-OH onto the modified lignin. Thermal properties of prepared succinic acid-modified lignin-graft-PEGs were investigated to study the relation between the amount of capping agent and crosslinking density. Lignin-graft-PEG showed a clear trend to lower Tm and Tg at lower crosslinking (large amount of capping agent). Tg of the lignin graft-PEG decreased from 2.6 °C to 27.5 °C by increasing the capping agent from 6 % to 59 %. The precise control of available reaction sites on lignin using a capping agent resulted in a convenient way to adjust the degree of crosslinking. Third, we have synthesized a fully biomass-based polyester, capped lignin-graft-castor oil. The lignin was chemically modified by succinic acid and capping agent, acetic acid. The other biomass of the copolymer was castor oil. The castor oil was used in its pristine form without any modification. These two biomasses are linked with covalent bonding through esterification in the presence of carbodiimide. This new method could be easily scalable in the industry due to its convenient synthesis procedure, fewer reaction step and moderate reaction conditions. The synthesized copolymer showed decent melting temperature and glass transition temperature to enable thermal processing. The mechanical properties of new capped lignin-graft-castor oil can be controlled by changing the crosslinking density and the mass ratio of capped lignin to castor oil. The highest modulus is 228.43 MPa, which is higher than that of low-density polyethylene (LDPE). In addition, a structure-property relationship of capped lignin-graft-castor oil was confirmed by controlling the crosslinking density and weight % of capped lignin and castor oil. Overall, this dissertation demonstrates novel synthetic methods for advanced biomass-based biodegradable polymer. Our new lignin modification methods would increase the value of lignin as a raw material of biodegradable polymers. These methods can significantly change polymer properties while improving mechanical properties and enabling thermal processing. In addition, the synthesized 100 % biomass-based biodegradable can be expected to have great advantages in terms of cost and mass production. The demonstrated approaches and synthesized lignin-based biodegradable polyester in the dissertation can be important discoveries in the global trend to replace petroleum-based non-degradable plastics with biodegradable polymers.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemical and Biomedical Engineering in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">November 8, 2022.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Biodegradable polymer, Biomass-based polymer, Lignin, Lignin-based polymer, Polyester</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Hoyong Chung, Professor Directing Dissertation; Justin Kennemur, University Representative; Jingjiao Guan, Committee Member; Jamel Ali, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022900">
      <topic>Chemical engineering</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104660">
      <topic>Polymers</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022986">
      <topic>Chemistry</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Kim_fsu_0071E_17521</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemical and Biomedical Engineering</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
