<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Flux Growth of Lanthanide Intermetallics Containing Interstitials</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0009-1306-025X</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Larson</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">James T.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/latturne">
      <namePart type="family">Latturner</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Susan</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/tsiegrist">
      <namePart type="family">Siegrist</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Theo</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/shatruk">
      <namePart type="family">Shatruk</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Mykhailo</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/stiegman">
      <namePart type="family">Stiegman</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Albert E.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1953-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >This work explored the modification of interstitial sites in lanthanide intermetallics grown from metal flux synthesis. Hydrocarbons and fluorocarbons were used as sources of carbon and either hydrogen or fluorine and were reacted with other reactants in Ln/T fluxes. Fluorine interstitial sites were identified by single crystal X-ray diffraction while hydride sites were identified with neutron diffraction. Anthracene was previously used as a hydride source in the flux growth of La15(FeC6)4H and Ce4B2C2H2.4. Fluorinated analogs were targeted by using decafluorobiphenyl (C12F10) as a reactant, which acts as both a carbon and fluorine source. This mild fluorinating technique enables the isolation of an intermetallic product containing fluoride interstitials, as opposed to forming ionic metal fluorides. La15(FeC6)4F2 was grown as large crystals by reacting iron in a La/Ni eutectic flux in the presence of C12F10. The compound adopts a structure in the hexagonal crystal system with space group P6 ̅ which features FeC6 units composed of a central iron atom coordinated by three ethylenide units in a trigonal planar configuration. The structure is related to the previously reported La15(FeC6)4H, but with fluoride fully occupying the interstitial hydride positions, which induces partial occupancies and site splitting disorder in the adjacent layers of lanthanide ions. Decafluorobiphenyl and anthracene were reacted with boron in a melt comprised of cerium and copper, yielding crystals of Ce4B2C2F0.14H2.26, a fluorinated analog of previously reported Ce4B2C2H2.42. The siting and occupancies of the fluoride and hydride interstitials were confirmed using both single crystal X-ray and neutron diffraction. The fluoride mixes with hydride in an octahedral interstitial site surrounded by cerium cations; additional hydride ions occupy tetrahedral sites. Magnetic susceptibility shows a change from canted antiferromagnetic ordering reported for the hydride to paramagnetic behavior upon fluorine substitution. New stuffed lanthanide borocarbides were grown from reactions in lanthanide-rich eutectic melts, exploring the use of C14H10 (anthracene) and C12F10 (decafluorobiphenyl) as sources of interstitial hydride and fluoride ions. Ln3BC2Xn (Ln = La, Ce, Pr; X = H, F) are analogs of the orthorhombic Ca3C3Cl2 structure type, featuring borocarbide units in place of the allenylide anions and small anions (X = H and F) in place of the chloride anions, partially occupying octahedral and tetrahedral interstitial sites surrounded by lanthanide cations. Single crystal neutron diffraction data for La3BC2H1.69 confirm hydrogen is present in both interstitial sites, with site-splitting in the octahedral site. Magnetic studies indicate that La3BC2H1.69 is a superconductor with a Tc at around 3 K. Pr3BC2Hx shows antiferromagnetic behavior below 55 K while Pr3BC2F0.54 is paramagnetic. New lanthanum borocarbide chlorides were grown from La/Fe flux. La3BC2Cl1.01 crystallizes in space group Cmcm and has the same structure as La3BC2H1.69, with chlorine substituting into the hydride sites. Chlorine is located in an octahedral site and a tetrahedral site with occupancies of 85(6)% and 17(8)% respectively. Reactions with higher chloride content yield La3BC2Cl2 which has the La3BC2Br2 structure in Pnma; this structure has larger coordination environments for the chloride ions, allowing full occupancy. Density of state calculations show La3BC2Cl1.01 is metallic and the Fermi level falls in a stabilizing pseudogap. La3BC2Cl2 is a semiconductor with a bandgap of 0.1eV. Reactions of anthracene in Ln/T eutectic mixtures (Ln = La, Yb; T = Ni, Cu) have produced crystals of new complex lanthanide carbide hydride phases. The thermal decomposition of anthracene provides a source of both carbon and hydrogen. LaCHx forms in space group Pnma with unit cell parameters a = 7.2736(4) b = 3.7218(2) c = 13.0727(7) Å; Yb2CHx forms in space group P321 with unit cell parameters a = 3.5659(4) and c = 5.8000(8) Å. LaCHx contains an empty tetrahedral site that closely matches the size of the hydride site in LaH2. Yb2CHx contains two empty interstitial sites that may be filled with hydrogen. DOS calculations show that filling the tetrahedral site in LaCHx with hydrogen increases metallic behavior, while adding hydrogen into the two sites in Yb2CHx progressively lower the number of states at the Fermi level.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 3, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Susan E. Latturner, Professor Directing Dissertation; Theo Siegrist, University Representative; Mykhailo Shatruk, Committee Member; Albert E. Stiegman, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023017">
      <topic>Chemistry, Inorganic</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Larson_fsu_0071E_17796</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
