<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Experimental Study of Shock Wave Boundary Layer Interactions on an Axisymmetric Body</title>
      <nonSort>An</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-7385-4320</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Mason</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Fraeman</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/drrajank">
      <namePart type="family">Kumar</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Rajan</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Professor of Mechanical Engineering)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/falvi">
      <namePart type="family">Alvi</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Farrukh S.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/camoore">
      <namePart type="family">Moore</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Carl A.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/zeng">
      <namePart type="family">Zeng</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Changchun (Chad)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>FAMU-FSU College of Engineering</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Mechanical Engineering</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (111 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >The continual study of shock wave boundary layer interactions (SBLIs) is driven by their presence on the internal and external surfaces of transonic, supersonic, and hypersonic flight vehicles. SBLIs manifest in a myriad of practical high-speed flight scenarios, such as supersonic engine inlets, launch vehicle booster separation, transonic wings, and aircraft-store interactions during carriage and release. These interactions incite numerous consequences to the operation of high-speed vehicles and their components. They cause highly unsteady mechanical-thermal loads that threaten the aerostructural integrity, cause flow separation that increases drag, and induce pitching moments causing undesirable changes to the vehicle trajectory. Current strategies to address the SBLI related issues have led to flight envelope reduction and over-design of the aircraft components. Study of SBLIs have been the focus of numerous experimental and computational investigations using canonical geometries that simplify the complex real-flow configurations. Analysis of two-dimensional (2-D) canonical SBLIs has laid a strong foundation on which advanced three-dimensional (3-D) interaction studies have continued to build. However, the same cannot be said for axisymmetric SBLIs, which have received little attention compared to their 2-D and 3-D counterparts. The present work investigates the flowfield of an inviscid-viscous interaction between a planar oblique shock wave, generated by an off-body wedge, and the turbulent boundary layer on an ogive nose-cone cylinder (axisymmetric) body. Investigating SBLIs on curved surfaces is pertinent to the evolution of high-speed flight, because they simulate real-flight bodies and interactions that many traditional 2-D and 3-D configurations do not. Literature has yet to bridge the gap between 2-D, 3-D and axisymmetric SBLIs, as the few axisymmetric SBLI studies that do exist only offer a glance at the flow topology and mean flow behavior with limited analysis. A comprehensive understanding of axisymmetric SBLIs requires that a few core questions be answered. 1) Are the SBLI flow features on axisymmetric bodies the same or different from the well-studied 2-D/3-D canonical flows? 2) Are the scaling (spatial/temporal) parameters identified for 2-D or 3-D SBLI flows valid for curved surface interactions? 3) How do key flow parameters, such as interaction strength, Mach number, and Reynolds number affect the axisymmetric SBLI flow physics? The present research was conducted at the Florida State University Polysonic Wind Tunnel located at the Florida Center for Advanced Aero-Propulsion. Advanced flow diagnostics were carried out with an aim to characterize the principal off-body flow features and on-surface interactions from an incident-reflection shock wave on an ogive-nose cylinder body. Measurements involved mean flow topology from oil-based paint and high-speed shadowgraph, time-averaged surface pressures using an electronic pressure scanner (ESP), and pressure sensitive paint (PSP), and unsteady pressures using fast-response Kulite pressure sensors. Flow conditions were established at various Mach number (M∞ = 2–4) and wedge deflection angle (δ = 10◦ – 25◦) combinations at a constant Reynolds number (Re ≈ 9.09x105). Body forces were also measured at a few selected conditions using an internal six-component strain gauge balance. Shadowgraph images revealed a diverse mean flowfield with several shock-based interactions. At lower Mach numbers the separation shock was observed having an unsteady component as it oscillated along the ϕ = 0◦ meridian. Oil flow visualizations showed that the surface flow is windward symmetric and highly three-dimensional, as the flow topology varies significantly based on the streamwise and azimuthal positioning. The number of separation lines present on the surface is a result of the SBLI strength. Primary separation lines wrap nonlinearly around the model surface independently of flow conditions, and secondary separation lines are decoupled in interactions with small wedge angles. A region of vortices (VR) exists between the primary and secondary separation lines. Results of the mean pressure distributions complimented by surface flow streamlines indicate that the region of vortical flow is open-type and develops on the curved surface, similar to the separation region seen in single blunt-fin SBLI flows. The VR grows non-linearly in size with the smallest in length along the windward meridian (the side facing the shock generator). A length-scale suitable for defining shock induced interactions for axisymmetric bodies still remains unknown, but similarities between the axisymmetric windward plane flow and 2-D SBLI show potential adaptation. Mean surface pressures from ESP and PSP match very well, provide quantitative pressure maps, and support the flow features observed using flow visualization. Flow separation on the surface is driven by pressure gradients caused by both the impingement of the oblique shock and the curvature of the body. Unlike 2-D and 3-D SBLI the separation region is only detected in the windward plane, as the nature of its three-dimensionality remains unclear. Unsteady pressure measurements reveal that the SBLI features broadband pressure fluctuations beneath the separation shock foot and flow reattachment regions. Pressure fluctuations indicate that the flow is most energized near the separation shock foot and the isotropic node, and loses energy nonlinearly with distance from the interaction regions. As with 2-D SBLI, the windward flow is largely influenced by low frequency energy content. Both the distribution and magnitude of flow energy are significantly affected by proximity to the SBLI region location and length scales. Spectral analysis shows that although the wedge angle and Mach number influence the energy magnitude in a single flow region, the energy distribution remains unchanged. It also shows that the overall energy levels decrease at higher Mach numbers, and increase with the wedge angle. This dissertation offers a significant contribution to the understanding of the underlying flow physics associated with incident-reflection SBLI on an axisymmetric body. It has answered a few fundamental questions, provided new insights into the introductory flow dynamics, and established key parametric relationships. Although the continuation of this work remains challenging, the use of high-fidelity experimental techniques, along with validated numerical tools, will expand the understanding of 3-D flow complexities, and move towards future designs of high-speed flight control mechanisms.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Mechanical Engineering in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">September 6, 2022.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Aerospace, Fluids, Shock Wave, Shock Wave Boundary Layer</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Rajan Kumar, Professor Directing Dissertation; Farrukh Alvi, Committee Member; Carl Moore, Committee Member; Changchun Zeng, University Representative.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082757">
      <topic>Mechanical engineering</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95007821">
      <topic>Aerospace engineering</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85049383">
      <topic>Fluid mechanics</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Mason_fsu_0071E_17505</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Mechanical Engineering</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
