<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Tongueless Mourning</title>
      <subTitle>Visual-Material Rhetoric in Victorian Grief Rituals</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0002-6725-8594</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Morley</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Carmen Renee</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2001108549">
      <namePart type="family">Fleckenstein</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kristie S.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2015038714">
      <namePart type="family">Lathan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Rhea Estelle</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1961-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jfiscus">
      <namePart type="family">Fiscus-Cannaday</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jaclyn</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of English</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Despite the prevalence of mourning rituals across cultures and time, not much work focusing on the visual-material practices has been done within the field of rhetorical studies, which, up until the 1970s, focused almost entirely on the discursive. This limited scope overlooks the importance of nondiscursive expressions of sorrow. This thesis sheds light on the underserved visual-material mourning rhetorics through analysis of three different mourning photographs from the Victorian era: a daguerreotype, an ambrotype, and a silver gelatin print. The research questions guiding this inquiry include the following: first, how did photography operate as a visual expression of grief in the Victorian era, and second, how did photography function as a material expression of grief? In addressing these questions, this research uncovered the varied ways the photographs functioned rhetorically during the Victorian Era in the United States to assuage pain through visual and material strategies. To begin, one photograph relied on visually eulogizing the deceased's character through phrenological and physiognomic display; another invited the viewer into doubly perceiving a child in his final portrait as both alive and dead; and, finally, a third evoked Christian iconography of angels and the Madonna to portray the deceased as peacefully existing in heaven. Each palliated grief through specific configurations of image content. Second, insights derived from an analysis of the photographs' materiality included the unique way the mirror-like surface of a daguerreotype reflects a mourner's likeness alongside the image of their loved one while the small size of the photograph promoted mobile use; the ambrotype featured the haptic sensation that accompanies holding a physical object that represents a deceased loved one and thus fostered the ability to pick up or set down the memory and pain associated with it; the silver gelatin print from 1910 crafted a familial and communal memory by emphasizing display of the departed, a materiality informed by the universal trauma and mass death experienced in the American Civil War. Finally, the study uncovered the inextricable link between the visual and material in mourning rhetorics, illuminating the difficulty of separating the visual elements from the material elements when analyzing these photographic objects. The visual and the material features of these photographs inform and are informed by one another, providing important context, and increasing the impact of both elements. If the two were divorced, a deceased woman would be without her name or relationship to the mourner, information provided by the note pinned to the padded case housing her photograph; a mother would be unable to hold her child's photograph in her hands while studying a face she would otherwise never be able to look upon again; and a visually stunning image showcasing a child's celestial journey might be overlooked as just a pretty picture of individual sorrow. Ultimately, this study illuminated the immense influence of visual-material rhetorics of mourning in the Victorian era in the United States, highlighting the importance of such rhetorics to the discipline and thus the need to expand study beyond the three images featured in this work.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of English in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Arts.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 3, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Grief, Material, Mourning, Photography, Victorian, Visual</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Kristie Fleckenstein, Professor Directing Thesis; Rhea Lathan, Committee Member; Jaclyn Fiscus-Cannaday, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113628">
      <topic>Rhetoric</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85140130">
      <geographic>United States</geographic>
      <topic>History</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Morley_fsu_0071N_18003</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Arts</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>English</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
