<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Relationship between Reminding and Integration The Relationship between Reminding and Integration</title>
      <nonSort>The</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-8384-9258</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Rawlinson Rawlinson</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Heather C. Heather C.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Psychology Department of Psychology</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022 2022</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (153 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Information that changes is often recalled worse than information that does not change, such that memory interference is observed (Anderson &amp; Neely, 1996). However, studies using the A-B, A-D paradigm have revealed that when reminding occurs during the encoding of changed information and is recollected at test, it can result in memory facilitation, such that changed information is recalled better than control information that is only presented once (Wahlheim &amp; Jacoby, 2013). One possibility is that reminding allows for memory integration, which in turn produces the facilitation observed in prior work. Memory integration allows us to make sense of new information in our daily lives, and has significant implications for the field of education (Bauer, Esposito, &amp; Daly, 2020). Although reminding appears necessary for memory integration to occur, reminding alone does not appear sufficient. The aim of the present studies was to better understand the factors and mechanisms underpinning the relationship between reminding and integration. Although animacy status has appeared to be an important factor for integration in previous studies (Schreiner, Meiser, &amp; Bröder, 2022), Experiment 1 found that animate and inanimate cue words did not differ in reminding during encoding, reminding recollection at test, nor in evidence of integration. Experiment 2 suggested that measuring reminding through mental imagery reports better captured integration relative to asking a direct question about reminding, and provided a new method of investigating the relationship between reminding and integration. Experiments 3 and 4 found that reminding occurred in an open-loop paradigm, but critically, found that an increased rate of reminding in that paradigm did not predict increased evidence for memory integration, and provided mixed evidence for a correlation between event structure awareness and memory integration. Taken together, the results of these experiments deepen the current understanding of the human memory system by providing support for the notion that reminding is necessary but not sufficient for memory integration, and providing new methods for investigating reminding and integration that can be used in new paradigms.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Psychology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Psychology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">October 26, 2022 October 26, 2022.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Animacy, Integration, Memory Facilitation, Memory for Change, Reminding</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Colleen M. Kelley, Professor Directing Dissertation; Michael A. Bishop, University Representative; Michael Kaschak, Committee Member; Chris B. Martin, Committee Member; Aaron A. Wilber, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87007652">
      <topic>Cognitive psychology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Rawlinson_fsu_0071E_17532</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Psychology</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
