<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>On the Natchez Confederate Pageant</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0000-1097-7155</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Simone</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Teresa</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2017067051">
      <namePart type="family">Thomas</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Aaron C.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2008105762">
      <namePart type="family">Atkins</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jennifer</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2010074779">
      <namePart type="family">Osborne</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Elizabeth A.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1977-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2021122893">
      <namePart type="family">Della Gatta</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Carla</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Fine Arts</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Theatre</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Each Spring since 1932 residents of Natchez, Mississippi have performed a Confederate Pageant. Natchez was once the wealthiest city in the nation due to its slave trade and cotton plantations, and it has more extant antebellum architecture than any other US city. Since the Great Depression Natchez has capitalized on Lost Cause nostalgia, promoting Confederate history through tourism romantically glorifying Natchez as "where the Old South still lives." Ladies dress in hoop skirts, offer tours of plantations, and direct youth to perform in the annual Confederate Pageant as part of "Spring Pilgrimage," a lucrative tourist event. Climaxing with a procession by the Confederate Queen and General, the pageant reimagines the past and future nation. I use the Confederate Pageant to argue that performance sustains nationalism, that women and children are critical to the production of nationalism, and that ideologies are embedded in material practices. Performance, nationalism, and memory are interrelated embodied processes; the Confederate Pageant is a node where they intersect. The Confederate Pageant is a ritual of surrogation that uses ideals of reproductive futurity to resurrect the Confederacy. Teleological ideals of national progress link an idealized past to an imagined future. Illustrating Lee Edelman's concept of "reproductive futurism" the figure of the child functions politically as an idealized representation of the nation's future. Children represent nationalist ideals of reproductive futurism in rituals of surrogation, which Joseph Roach describes as rituals where one body replaces another, in attempts to fill perceived social voids. Performances of surrogation reiterate and alter what came before: the performance is doubled yet dislocated, alike, but not identical. Surrogation functions similarly to Jacques Derrida's supplément as an addition and replacement both extending and displacing. Performance reanimates the nation, not only as symbolic resurrection, but also evoking affect and sensation to create lived, shared experiences that create feelings of national belonging. In Chapter One, I offer thick description detailing my observations of the performance in April 2019, then use these observations to illustrate my theoretical framework about how performance and memory, women and children, and affect and sensation function to produce nationalism. Then to provide dramaturgical context for that performance iteration, in Chapter 2 I pan to a very broad perspective situating Natchez within deep time. I offer geologic and historic context for how Natchez became the hub of plantation cotton farming, and how this impacted the US's early development as a nation. Highlighting Mississippi authors, I note how fictional literature influenced historical narratives and memory of the past. In chapter three I use diffractive reading to discuss representations of Natchez history and the Old South. I illustrate how attitudes about race and nation linked to Natchez circulated via marketing materials, souvenirs, etc. as well as through performance. I analyze objects as performative, illustrating how they circulate ideologies, and how many forms/bodies may hold or perform memory. I highlight themes of the gestures curtsey and bow, panoramic theatrical techniques related to animation, and representations of steamboats/showboats. I also focus on silhouettes. I follow a logo that I call the "Natchez Lady Silhouette" used in tourism materials for almost a century, and relate this to developments in mass-circulated media. Finally, in chapter four, I discuss how African American residents have resisted and countered Natchez's confederate heritage tourism by creating performances, museums, and heritage sites emphasizing their perspectives. I take the pageant's aesthetics as inspiration. The pageant presents the story of Natchez in vignettes of tableaux and dance, with occasional placards, minimal dialogue, and plenty of romantic, flowery imagery. I use these aesthetics (recall: aesthetic means sensation) as formal/stylistic inspiration, writing about theatre theatrically. Like the pageant, I present the story of Natchez in vignettes, silhouetted tableaux, and looping dances. While I make an academically sound argument supported by evidence, I deploy the tone of the novelist or poet. Mississippi authors have been key not just in US literature but ultimately to shaping our ideals of the nation. From William Faulkner's Yoknapatawpha County to Jesmyn Ward's Bois Sauvage, many cherished Mississippi authors stage their stories in imagined places, finding the essential truth of the past better remembered in fiction. Natchez offers a unique example of a place that lives materially, imaginatively, and metaphorically. I treat this text like a story, like theatre, to capture that.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Theatre in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Theatre and Performance Research.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 11, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Aaron C. Thomas, Professor Directing Dissertation; Jennifer Atkins, University Representative; Elizabeth Osborne, Committee Member; Carla Della Gatta, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134522">
      <topic>Theater</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Simone_fsu_0071E_17942</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Theatre</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
