<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Impact of Increasing the Resolution of Sea Surface Temperatures on a Numerical Model at Kennedy Space Center</mods:title>
      <mods:nonSort>The</mods:nonSort>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-8241-8237</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Mersiovsky</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Haiden</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n81021102">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Fuelberg</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Henry E.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jchagnon">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Chagnon</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jeffrey M.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rhart">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hart</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Robert E. (Robert Edward)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1972-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/awing">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Wing</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Allison</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (65 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>The impact of including Sea Surface Temperatures (SSTs) of differing horizontal grid spacings in simulations of river and sea breeze related weather has not been studied extensively in the Cape Canaveral area of Florida. This study assesses whether simulations using a 1 km SST product, which better captures the complexity of the region's coastal geography, improves simulations incorporating a 6 km SST product that does not define the geography of the region as well. The Weather Research and Forecasting model (WRF) was used to simulate days with river and sea breeze development around Cape Canaveral during the warm season. Simulations utilized two-way nesting with horizontal grid spacings of 3 and 1 km. Output from the 0900 UTC run of the High-Resolution Rapid Refresh (HRRR) model was used to initialize the WRF model. SSTs of 1 or 6 km grid spacing also were used in initializing the WRF model. The impact of using the higher resolution SST dataset is presented by analyzing simulations of 2 m temperature and convective initiation, which is an important factor for operational planning at Kennedy Space Center. In addition, dynamic and kinematic properties of the thermal circulations simulated using the two SST products are presented. The analyzed characteristics include the location and timing of river and sea breeze passages, which are also important for planning operations at Kennedy Space Center. Observations of water temperatures from buoys in the Atlantic Ocean near Florida's Space Coast and water temperature sensors in the Banana and Indian Rivers were compared to those depicted in the two SST products. Somewhat surprisingly, results show that the water temperatures of the Banana and Indian Rivers, as well as the SSTs in the Atlantic Ocean, were better represented by the 6 km SST product rather than the 1 km product. Additionally, simulated 2 m temperatures were closer to observed 2 m temperatures in simulations using the lower resolution SST data. Mean absolute error (MAE) and root mean square error (RMSE) between the two SST products were calculated for the water temperatures of the two inland rivers and Atlantic Ocean. The same metrics were determined onshore for the simulated 2 m temperature based on the two SST runs. MAE and RMSE values for depictions of the SSTs and river temperatures were found to not improve in the 1 km SST product. For simulations of onshore 2 m temperatures, MAE and RMSE were also found to not improve when using 1 km SSTs in simulations. The differences in MAE and RMSE values between both SST runs for both the depictions of the water temperatures and simulated onshore 2 m temperatures were found to be significant at the 95% confidence interval. Improved simulation of convective initiation was found when increasing the SST resolution. The amount of improvement depended on the flow regime. The greatest improvement occurred during the onshore flow regime when using the higher resolution SSTs. Inconsistent improvements were found using 1 km SSTs when observed single cell convection develops over Merritt Island. Simulations of the dynamical and kinematic aspects of the Banana and Indian River breeze generally were improved when using the 1 km SSTs. The return flow of the three local breezes was successfully simulated and generally found to be stronger when using 1 km SSTs. Simulations using 1 km SSTs also were found to better locate the Banana and Indian River breezes. In addition, the use of both SST resolutions simulated stronger maximum ascents for all three breezes than found in previous studies, along with slightly greater simulated depths of the sea and two river breezes.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Science.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 10, 2022.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">numerical weather prediction, river breeze, sea breeze</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Henry E. Fuelberg, Professor Directing Thesis; Jeffrey Chagnon, Committee Member; Robert Hart, Committee Member; Allison Wing, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85084334">
      <mods:topic>Meteorology</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">2022_Mersiovsky_fsu_0071N_17025</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Science</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-10-10T17:55:50.20129-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
