<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-4.xsd"
           version="3.4">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>N-Heterocyclic Carbene Copper Complexes</title>
      <subTitle>Catalysis and Coordination Chemistry</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <namePart type="family">Jo</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Minyoung</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/shatruk">
      <namePart type="family">Shatruk</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Mykhailo</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Professor Directing Dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n84134993">
      <namePart type="family">Locke</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Bruce R.</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">University Representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/bgmiller">
      <namePart type="family">Miller</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Brian G.</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kghanson">
      <namePart type="family">Hanson</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kenneth G.</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (150 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >N-heterocyclic carbene (NHC) transition metal complexes have emerged as an important class of compounds in catalysis and coordination chemistry. As shown in Chapter 1 of this thesis, the strong σ-donating and weak π-accepting ability of NHC ligands, combined with sterically demanding substituents, enable the NHC-metal complexes to exhibit high chemical and thermal stability, consequently leading to good catalytic activity. NHCs with expanded rings, in particular, have been found to exhibit distinct electronic and steric character, which contributes to improving the catalytic efficiencies in the transition metal system. Ring-expanded NHCs are considered to be stronger electron donors and more sterically demanding ligands as compared to the classical 5-membered NHCs. These changes in the ligand’s character are caused by the additional methylene groups on the ring backbone and the enlarged N-C-N angle at the carbene center. Taking into account such appealing properties of the 6-membered NHCs, we have developed Cu(I) complexes bearing fused cyclic 6-membered NHC rings which exhibit superior activities in asymmetric allylic substitutions, which are described in Chapter 3. The highest regio- and enantioselectivity were achieved especially when the unusual aryl ether substrates were involved in the reactions mediated by the 6-NHC-Cu(I) catalysts. To find a rationale for such unconventional reactivities and better discern the reaction pathway, the systematic investigation has been conducted with complexes incorporating varied NHC ligands, substrates with different leaving groups, and various alcohol additives, all of which are expected to have a substantial impact in the catalytic cycle. Variation of the NHC ligands in the Cu-catalyzed allylic borylation with the aryl ether substrate showed different reaction rates depending on the NHC structure, where 6-NHC led to the full conversion within 9 h, as opposed to 5- and 7-membered NHCs which showed incomplete reactions even after 48 h. The leaving group of the substrate was significantly related to the product selectivity, as poor leaving groups, such as aryl ether and carbonate, induced high regio- and enantioselectivity compared to the good leaving groups, like bromide and mesylate, which gave rise to reduced selectivities. Recognizing the increased reaction rate by using alcohol additives, methanol and ethanol were found to promote the highest rates in our 6-NHC-Cu-catalyzed reactions, in contrast to bulky alcohols, which showed slower reaction rates. This result supports our hypothesis of the rate-determining 6-membered alcohol-involving transition state, the formation of which is sensitive to steric congestion. This study demonstrates that matching leaving group and catalyst is important to design the reaction, and when it comes to our NHC-Cu catalysts, the perfect paring of the extended aromatic 6-NHC ligand with the aromatic leaving groups provides an optimal catalytic system to reach the highest reaction rate and stereochemical outcomes. In terms of the coordination chemistry of NHC-Cu(I) complexes, these closed-shell Lewis-acidic moieties are considered to be suitable for reactions with main-group clusters to provide exceptional stability and increased solubility to the resulting assemblies, allowing their further modification through the solution chemistry. With this point in mind, in Chapter 4 we demonstrate the use of polyphosphide clusters as ligands in NHC-Cu complexes. Treatment of (TMS)3P7 (TMS = trimethylsilyl) with the NHC-CuCl gave rise to the large anionic bimetallic cluster, [NHC-Cu-P7(TMS)]–, crystalized as the [NHC-Cu-NHC]+ salt. Its crystal structure reveals that [(TMS)P7]2– is bound to the Cu(I) center via the η4 coordination mode, which leads to a slight distortion from the original nortricyclane-like structure. The reaction with the gold analogue delivered the fully-substituted neutral molecule, (NHC-Au)3P7, retaining the geometry and symmetry of the initial cage. In contrast to the original (TMS)3P7 cluster, these complexes show improved stability and solubility, being soluble in less polar solvents. Finally, in Chapter 5, we demonstrate a new solution-phase methodology to convert the elemental red phosphorus into polyphosphide clusters, which indeed prompted the investigation of their reactivities described in the preceding chapter. A reaction between red phosphorus and potassium ethoxide in THF/DME yielded a mixture of soluble polyphosphide species containing P162–, P213–, and P5–. The use of such mild reactants offers the ease of red phosphorus activation to improve the accessibility to the polyphosphide species, which was not readily achieved by the conventional methods using strongly reducing reactants. The reaction outcome is governed by the choice of solvent, particularly by the boiling points and polarity, since the boiling point determines the activation temperature, and the polarity seems to be related to the stabilization of the resulting polyphosphide clusters. Other potential activators such as thiolates were examined, giving rise to only P162– species selectively, which suggests that the activation proceeds via a redox mechanism, in contrast to the nucleophilic activation with alkali metal alkoxides.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Spring Semester 2019.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 11, 2019.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">asymmetric reaction, catalyst, copper, N-heterocyclic carbene, phosphorus, polyphosphide</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Michael Shatruk, Professor Directing Dissertation; Bruce Locke, University Representative; Brian G. Miller, Committee Member; Kenneth G. Hanson, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022986">
      <topic>Chemistry</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">2019_Spring_Jo_fsu_0071E_15114</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2019-10-14T16:36:31.241-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
