<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-4.xsd"
           version="3.4">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Integrated Experimental and Numerical Study of Compliant Floating Offshore Wind Turbines</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <namePart type="family">Kopperstad</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Karsten Mikal</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kshoele">
      <namePart type="family">Koroush</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Shoele</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Professor Co-Directing Thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/drrajank">
      <namePart type="family">Kumar</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Rajan</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Professor Co-Directing Thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/woates">
      <namePart type="family">Oates</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">William</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>FAMU-FSU College of Engineering</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Mechanical Engineering</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (89 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Wind-based renewable energies are among the fastest growing within the energy sector, with the vast majority of wind power generated from onshore wind farms. Floating offshore wind turbines (FOWT) have been proposed as alternative to the conventional onshore systems. Compared with their land-based counterparts, FOWT possess clear advantage in their easy access to stronger and steadier wind and their mitigated impact on human society. Several concepts of FOWT have been proposed. Among them, the so called barge type and spar type floating structures. Experimental and numerical studies were conducted in order to investigate the fluid dynamics associated with these compliant structures and what additional consideration future offshore wind farm designers need to consider in the initial planning phase of a wind farm configuration. Based on disk actuator theory, a series of computational fluid dynamics and experimental studies were conducted on a actuator disk model as a cost effective simulation tool for these types of turbines. For the computational efforts, the actuator disk model was represented by a circular actuator disk that was discretized with an unstructured two-dimensional triangular mesh in a structured three-dimensional fluid domain. For experimental studies, the actuator disk model was represented by an additive manufactured, uniform, and porous disk designed to apply decelerating forces on the incoming fluid. From force measurements conducted in an open-loop, low-speed wind tunnel facility, a drag coefficient was derived. The drag coefficient was then implemented into a computation flow solver. Using stereo particle imaging velocimetry, results from the computational studies were verified by means of average velocity deficit. Once validation was obtained, calculations of the motion based on three different sea states that the floating structures would be subjected to were carried out. The resulting motion was implemented into the flow solver and the resulting wake and time histories of power and drag force were analyzed. CFD results were obtained using laminar and turbulent inflow conditions. The results from the study suggest that the effect of the oscillation of the wind turbine seems to be overpowered by the inflow conditions. For the barge type floating platform, slight improvements in wake recovery is observed at a cost of higher standard deviation of power and lower mean power values. Mean power values for the spar type floating structure remains constant with increasing sea states. Both floating platforms is observed to increase overall turbulent mixing in the far wake regime.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Mechanical Engineering in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Science.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Spring Semester 2019.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">January 25, 2019.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Cable dynamics, Floating Offshore Wind Turbine, Hywind OC3, ITI Barge, Wake, Wave/platform interaction</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Shoele Koroush, Professor Co-Directing Thesis; Rajan Kumar, Professor Co-Directing Thesis; William Oates, Committee Member.</note>
   <identifier  type="IID">2019_Spring_Kopperstad_fsu_0071N_14973</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Science</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Mechanical Engineering</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2019-10-14T16:36:31.241-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
