<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Xenophon and the Sophistic Movement</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-8109-6718</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Lee</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Alex</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2008040982">
      <namePart type="family">Slaveva-Griffin</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Svetla</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n96043208">
      <namePart type="family">Marincola</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">John</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/nstein2">
      <namePart type="family">Stein</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Nathanael</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n82200535">
      <namePart type="family">Lewis</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Virginia M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2011129850">
      <namePart type="family">Moore</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Christopher</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1965-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Classics</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (241 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >This dissertation studies Xenophon's engagement with fifth-century intellectual culture. In particular, it examines the ways in which Xenophon situates Socrates within and in relation to the sophistic movement. I demonstrate that the sophistic movement is not only essential for understanding Xenophon's intellectual project and his portrayal of Socrates, but also that Xenophon himself is an overlooked but valuable source for the intellectual history of the fifth century. The introduction explains the motivation for the project and situates it within the bourgeoning fields of study on Xenophon and on the sophistic movement, respectively. The second chapter studies Xenophon's diverse rhetorical strategies of demarcating intellectuals. The terms sophistēs and philosophos, my analysis shows, display significant semantic overlap in Xenophon's corpus. Consequently, attending to Xenophon's lexical choices, I argue, allows us to rethink several prevalent assumptions about Xenophon's views of the sophists. It also indicates that, if we are to understand his views of fifth-century intellectual culture, we must look beyond his lexical choices. The remainder of the dissertation examines how Xenophon presents Socrates vis-à-vis four topics or debates that were central to the sophistic movement and intellectual culture in his time: natural philosophy, the use of poetry in education, the teachability of virtue and the moral responsibility that attends education, and the question of self-interest. The third chapter turns to Xenophon's Socrates as both a critic and reformer of natural philosophy and argues that Xenophon presents Socrates' innovative natural theological views as a response to Anaxagorean physics. Xenophon's defense of Socrates, my examination reveals, is programmatic for Xenophon's own views on the intellectual and educational marketplace in the fifth century BCE. The following three chapters all study Xenophon's presentation of Socrates qua teacher, and ask how Xenophon portrays Socrates as similar to and yet different from other fifth-century educators like Protagoras, Prodicus, Gorgias, and Antiphon. The fourth chapter focuses on the role of poetry in Socrates' (and other sophists') pedagogy, and demonstrates that Socrates was deeply embedded in (and critical of) the educational practices of his day. In turn, the fifth chapter takes up a debate on the responsibility teachers bear for the behavior of their students. I argue that, in the Anabasis, Xenophon's presentation of Gorgias as the teacher of Proxenus and Meno engages intertextually with Plato's Meno and Gorgias concerning debates about pedagogical responsibility. I compare Xenophon's treatment of Gorgias with his handling of Socrates' responsibility for Critias and Alcibiades, and demonstrate that Xenophon (and his Socrates) are critical of teachers like Gorgias who neglect to care for the moral character of their pupils. At the end, the sixth chapter considers how Xenophon situates Socrates within a live fifth-century debate about self-interest. While drawing on the work of other sophists, like Prodicus, to make his case, Xenophon opposes Socrates to advocates of a civically-harmful form of self-interest, like Antiphon. The centerpiece of this debate, a conversation between Socrates and his companion Aristippus, highlights the moral urgency and pedagogical importance of the debate. The findings of this and the preceding chapters demonstrate that Xenophon's Socrates and thereby Xenophon himself were fully engaged in the intellectual culture of the sophistic movement. The seventh chapter offers a brief conclusion and directions for developing this project further.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Classics in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 28, 2022.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Education, Ethics, Intellectual History, Socrates, Sophists, Xenophon</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Svetla Slaveva-Griffin, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; John Marincola, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Nathanael Stein, University Representative; Virginia Lewis, Committee Member; Christopher Moore, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026706">
      <topic>Classical literature</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026454">
      <topic>Civilization, Greco-Roman</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100849">
      <topic>Philosophy</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Summer 2022_Lee_fsu_0071E_17250</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Classics</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-01-27T10:52:08.836275-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
