<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Relationships between Music Experience and Steady Beat Performance in Wind Instrumentalists</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-1137-4046</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Boswell</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Matthew A.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jgeringer">
      <namePart type="family">Geringer</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">John M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/bholzman">
      <namePart type="family">Holzman</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Bruce</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n99036353">
      <namePart type="family">Dunnigan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Patrick</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1957-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dgspringer">
      <namePart type="family">Springer</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">D. Gregory  (Douglas Gregory)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Music</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Music</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (102 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Of the fundamental elements of Western music, tempo could be considered among the most vital because of its outsized impact on the remaining elements. The performance and maintenance of tempo in musical context requires precise timing and correction at multiple neurological levels. For well over 100 years psychologists have used tempo-related timing tasks, most frequently in the form of synchronization or self-paced tapping tasks, to explore the neurological underpinnings of the unique human timing system. Yet, despite the importance of tempo and timekeeping to music, music researchers have not often explored the performance of steady beats among live musicians. Therefore, the purpose of this dissertation was to investigate the temporal consistency of different experience groups of university-aged wind instrumentalists in both a continuation tapping task and a short playing task. Participants (N = 80) were undergraduate non-music majors, undergraduate music majors, and graduate wind performance majors. The three distinct groups had different musical backgrounds—such as the number of years playing their instrument or studying their instrument privately—and reported different amounts of independent metronome use. The participants engaged in a synchronization-continuation tapping task using a drum stick at two different tempos and the amount of interval-to-interval variability as well as drift from metronomic time were considered. The variability of intervals in the tapping task were not significantly different between the three groups; however, the amount of drift was significantly different between the groups. The least experienced musicians typically exhibited greater drift—both positive and negative—than the more experienced musicians. Further, both the tempo and the order of the tapping tasks impacted performance. Last, repeated performance of the tasks showed some evidence of improvement especially for the less-experienced participants. Participants performed a modified version of the melody from Beethoven's Ode to Joy on their primary instrument after listening to a metronome in the playing task. The same dependent measures as the tapping task were calculated. There were significant differences between the three groups for both variability and drift. Correlations between participant tapping and playing performance, however, were weak suggesting that tapping and playing performance were based on different skills—at least in this investigation. Potential reasons for this lack of relationship are discussed including the possibility of residual expressive timing playing a role. Secondary research questions were also addressed in the context of these results. First, participants were asked to self-assess their own temporal performance in both the tapping and playing task (i.e., rushing, dragging, or staying in time). Participants' assessments were correct at chance levels suggesting an inability to accurately assess their own performance. Second, participants were asked about the specific strategies they had employed to complete the tasks. Strategies like "internalizing the pulse" or "subdividing" were often listed by participants yet mentions of these strategies were sometimes paired with inconsistent tempo performance. Thus, the impact of such strategies remains to be tested. Suggestions for future music research in this area as well as potential impacts in music education are discussed.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the College of Music in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 28, 2022.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">continuation tapping, musical timing, steady beat, synchronization tapping, tapping, tempo performance</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">John M. Geringer, Professor Directing Dissertation; Bruce Holzman, University Representative; Patrick Dunnigan, Committee Member; D. Gregory Springer, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85088796">
      <topic>Music</topic>
      <topic>Instruction and study</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85088762">
      <topic>Music</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">2022_Summer_Boswell_fsu_0071E_17252</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Music</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-01-27T10:52:08.836275-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
