<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<documents>
        <document>
         <title>LMX Revisited: A Woman Superintendent Leading through Dyadic Relationships</title>
         <publication-date>2007-03-14T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hodgins</lname>
               <fname>Diane</fname>
               <mname>Weaver</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Women Administrators</keyword>
            <keyword>Ethnographic Study</keyword>
            <keyword>Case Study</keyword>
            <keyword>Leader-Member Exchange Theory</keyword>
            <keyword>Organizational Theory</keyword>
            <keyword>Women Superintendents</keyword>
            <keyword>Leadership Theory</keyword>
            <keyword>PK-12 Superintendents</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Education</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this case study was to examine how a woman superintendent led her school district in the state of Florida. The approach I used to study
            her leadership was informed by the Leader Member Exchange (LMX) theory. At the base of this theory rests the fundamental premise that a leader forms different types of
            relationships with members and thus influences the outcomes of the organization (Sparrowe &amp; Liden, 1997). Critics argued this theory was not fully developed in
            considering how gender may or may not influence the structure of understanding between each leader-member relationship. In this study, I examined how dyadic
            relationships were negotiated over time through a series of exchanges between a woman superintendent and individual members of her district.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Support
            for this approach was found in research on the K-12 public superintendency. Examination of this research revealed a shift in the demands on the officeholders of the
            superintendency, which led to a reconception of the position. This reconception meant superintendents must now effect change in their districts through the influence
            and critical awareness of work activities. At the base of this influence and awareness are the relationships negotiated between the leader and individual members of the
            district. This study contributed to the understanding of the superintendency by examining how a woman superintendentâ&#x80;&#x99;s relationships with members of her
            district allowed her to reconceptualize the position.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A second area of support for the use of this theory was found in the research on women
            superintendents. Research on these administrators was limited in the past due to the small number of women in the position. As more women entered the superintendency,
            there was more opportunity to gather comprehensive data. One area of limited research was how a woman superintendentâ&#x80;&#x99;s experience as a leader may challenge
            what is known about leadership theory. This study contributed to this area of research by examining a woman superintendentâ&#x80;&#x99;s leadership through LMX
            theory.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This case study utilized an ethnographic approach to research this woman superintendentâ&#x80;&#x99;s leadership. I conducted multiple
            interviews with the superintendent, as well as with site-level personnel in her district. In addition, I collected extensive observation data in naturalistic settings
            such as board meetings, planning sessions, and other district functions. Interviews and observations were triangulated with the collection and analysis of
            documents.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Conclusions drawn from the data indicated this womanâ&#x80;&#x99;s leadership challenged what is known about LMX theory. Specifically she
            challenged existing notions of leadership within a hierarchical system and ultimately created a shift in the leadership paradigm from the â&#x80;&#x9c;good old
            boyâ&#x80;&#x9d; network to the â&#x80;&#x9c;new womanâ&#x80;&#x9d; way of leading. Her commitment to equality meant she managed relationships through transparent
            leadership, which resulted in the creation of system-wide out-groups. Data supported gender may have been at the base of this change and thus a challenge to what is
            known about LMX.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4001</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2040&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4001</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2040</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T10:00:19-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2353055</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4001</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Jeffrey S. Brooks&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Jeffrey A. Milligan&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Lynn A.
                  Wicker&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Sherry Southerland&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2007-03-14T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Writing from the Inside Out: Connecting Self and Community in the First-Year Writing Classroom</title>
         <publication-date>2005-04-28T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hodges Hamilton</lname>
               <fname>Amy</fname>
               <mname>Leigh</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Writing And Psychology</keyword>
            <keyword>Writing And Healing</keyword>
            <keyword>First-Year Writing</keyword>
            <keyword>Composition Pedagogy</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation explores questions about how writing about life, loss, and experience leads to growth in students as both writers and thinkers.
            Through a qualitative teacher research study, Hodges Hamilton examines how a writing pedagogy focused on the interface between writing and psychology influences
            studentsâ&#x80;&#x99; growth as writers, critical thinkers, and active participants in their communities. As a result of this study, Hodges Hamilton proposes a writing
            and healing pedagogical framework which seeks to bridge the divide between pedagogical approaches that separate personal and academic writing.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4002</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2039&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4002</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2039</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T09:56:59-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2353045</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4002</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Wendy Bishop&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Co-Chair - Deborah Coxwell Teague&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Anne
                  Rowe&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Bruce Bickley&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Lad Tobin&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Nicholas
                  Mazza&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of English</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2005-04-28T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Study of the Practice of Family Mediation</title>
         <publication-date>2007-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Centrone</lname>
               <fname>Talia</fname>
               <mname>Joyce</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Mediators' Practices</keyword>
            <keyword>Family Mediation</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examined the practice of family mediation reported by 305 mediators in the United States, as well as trends in practice according to
            professional affiliation, mainly, law, mental health, social work and other. Data for this study were from a national survey of practicing family mediators of the then
            Academy of Family Mediators (Pasley &amp; Hinkle, 2000), originally collected with the intention of replicating the Kruk (1998) study of Canadian mediators.
            Mediatorsâ&#x80;&#x99; demographic characteristics, practice characteristics, issues, beliefs, and models guiding their work were examined, with a specific focus on
            differences between mediatorsâ&#x80;&#x99; professional affiliation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Results showed that overall there were differences by professional affiliation
            in respondents regarding practice characteristics, but there were more similarities than differences regarding issues, beliefs and models used. Significantly more
            lawyer mediators had completed a doctoral degree, practiced in a private practice setting, and had a greater proportion of their clients who were voluntary (not
            mandated), compared to the other three groups (mental heath, social work, and â&#x80;&#x9c;otherâ&#x80;&#x9d;). Also, mediators in the law group were more likely than
            all other groups to charge fees, as well as charge a significantly higher amount in fees. Mediators affiliated with the law group reported mediating property issues
            significantly more frequently than did mediators affiliated with mental health, social work, or â&#x80;&#x9c;otherâ&#x80;&#x9d;. Similar results were also found their
            frequency of mediating child support issues and spousal support issues. Parenting (custody) was the only divorce-related issue where the groups did not differ. Further,
            mediators affiliated with law less frequently included meeting with children in mediation practice than did all other groups. Mediators in the social work group spent
            less overall time addressing financial issues than did those in the law and mental health groups. Other differences between the law group and the
            â&#x80;&#x9c;otherâ&#x80;&#x9d; group were found for professional identity, percent of clients that are Caucasian, and type of mediation practiced.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Out of the 30 items mediators addressed on beliefs and issues in the field, group differences were found for only three items. The law group reported less
            agreement than did those in the â&#x80;&#x9c;otherâ&#x80;&#x9d; group regarding the belief that mediators should be neutral and that children should be included in
            mediation. Also, in beliefs about the importance of factors influencing positive child outcomes, the law group assigned less importance to shared parent agreements than
            did those in the â&#x80;&#x9c;otherâ&#x80;&#x9d; group.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Although those affiliated with law appear to be different from all other groups on the
            majority of questions regarding practice characteristics, such differences were not found for items assessing practice beliefs and issues. This may suggest that, in
            terms of beliefs and issues, mediators regardless of their professional affiliation have similar beliefs and issues regarding mediation practice. Moreover, most
            mediators reported using structured negotiation predominantly.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4003</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2038&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4003</label>
         <document-type>open_thesis</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2038</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T09:56:49-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2353027</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4003</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Kay Pasley&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Elizabeth Goldsmith&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Robert E
                  Lee&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>MS, Master of Science</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Family and Child Sciences</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2007-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Evidence for a solar influence on U.S.-affecting hurricanes</title>
         <publication-date>2009-07-02T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hodges</lname>
               <fname>Robert</fname>
               <mname>Edward</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Bayesian Statistics</keyword>
            <keyword>Hurricanes</keyword>
            <keyword>Sunspots</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Geography</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examines the robustness of the proposed modern solar activity / hurricane frequency relationship in light of recently compiled Atlantic
            hurricane records made available for the period 1700-1850. Constructing a thermodynamic efficiency for hurricanes utilizing mean monthly sunspot numbers (SSN), a
            Bayesian model that incorporates HURDAT (1851-2008) and Chenoweth archive (1700-1850) datasets is employed to maximize the information about the sun-hurricane
            relationship through the centuries. The information contained within the Chenoweth archive adds support to the hypothesis that solar variation influences hurricane
            activity. Results have impacts for U.S. seasonal hurricane science, as well as life and property for coastal and near-coastal populations.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4005</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2036&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4005</label>
         <document-type>open_thesis</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2036</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T09:52:19-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2353033</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4005</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - James B. Elsner&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - J. Anthony Stallins&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Lisa
                  Jordan&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Thomas H. Jagger&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>MS, Master of Science</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Geography</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2009-07-02T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>The Impact of Collaborative Tools on Digital Reference Users: An Exploratory Study</title>
         <publication-date>2006-09-08T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hodges</lname>
               <fname>Ruth</fname>
               <mname>A.</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Information Retrieval</keyword>
            <keyword>Computer Supported Cooperative Work</keyword>
            <keyword>Collaborative Tools</keyword>
            <keyword>Collaborative Cooperative Work</keyword>
            <keyword>Digital Reference</keyword>
            <keyword>CMC</keyword>
            <keyword>Computer-Mediated Communication</keyword>
            <keyword>Virtual Reference</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;Digital reference is a library question and answering service available via the Internet. Digital reference services provide information seekers access
            to a variety of resources and services to better facilitate information seekers in meeting their needs. In many services librarians interact with users synchronously
            using chat communication technologies, which incorporate co-browsing/escorting, and Web page pushing features. These collaborative features enable participants to see
            each otherâ&#x80;&#x99;s desktops and engage in more personalized and interactive information seeking activities. User-librarian interactions are captured by computer
            server logs, stored, and retrieved as digital transcripts. Currently, there is little research on how information seekers benefit from collaborative digital reference
            encounters. To fill this gap, this dissertation aims to better understand information seekers participating in collaborative digital reference activities such as
            cobrowsing/ escorting and Web page pushing as reflected in the transcripts. This is a case study designed to explore and understand information seekers interacting in a
            digital reference environment. The research assesses transactional and narrative data involving digital reference users affiliated with a large university library in
            the United States. The study was conducted in four phases. Phase I consisted of document analysis, including a review of the host libraryâ&#x80;&#x99;s Web site and
            related documents pertaining to the chat digital reference service. Phase II consisted of chat transcript collection, isolation, and preparation of the study sample.
            Phase III consisted of pilot testing and final analysis of chat digital reference transcripts. Phase IV of the study consisted of standardized opened-ended interviews
            of users who participated in co-browsing/escorting related activities during their chat digital reference encounter. This study is significant because transcripts can
            be reused to unobtrusively assess digital reference transactions in order to gain knowledge about users and their service needs. It is possible that transactional and
            narrative data might be used to derive a cognitive model of digital reference users. Knowledge gained can be used to better inform the digital reference service
            providers, which may enable them to design a more user-oriented digital reference service.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4006</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2035&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4006</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2035</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T09:47:58-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2353017</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4006</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Gary Burnett&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Corinne Jorgensen&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Rodney Roberts&lt;/p&gt;
                  &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Thomas L. Hart&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>School of Library and Information Studies</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2006-09-08T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>"How We Got Ovah": Afrocentric Spirituality in Black Art's Movement Women's Poetry</title>
         <publication-date>2007-06-25T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Green</lname>
               <fname>Dara</fname>
               <mname>Tafakari</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Black Arts Movement</keyword>
            <keyword>Women's Poetry</keyword>
            <keyword>Spirituality</keyword>
            <keyword>Afrocentricity</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study, using poetry by Carolyn Rodgers, Sarah Webster Fabio, Sonia Sanchez, Sharon Bourke, Ntozake Shange and Jayne Cortez, examines the
            manifestations of Afrocentric spirituality in womenâ&#x80;&#x99;s writing during the Black Arts Movement. Until recently, there has been a paucity of scholarship on the
            movement. When studying the BAM, critics have heretofore concentrated on sexism, homophobia, nationalism, and racism as its most prominent aspects. However, BAM writers
            also have a marked concern with spirituality from an African epistemological standpoint, which brings new possibilities for critical analysis to the forefront.
            Theorists such as Larry Neal furthermore termed the movement as a spiritual sister to the Black Power Movement. This project contributes to the burgeoning conversation
            on BAM womenâ&#x80;&#x99;s poetry by evaluating the ways in which they deem spirituality as essential for agency as women and as black citizens. I identify three major
            themes in which womenâ&#x80;&#x99;s spirituality serves as a prerequisite for or an enabler of black liberation and revolution. Chapter One explains how Carolyn
            Rodgers, in her books Songs of a Blackbird and How I Got Ovah, creates personas that initially reject Christianity as a Eurocentric religious construction, but
            subsequently acknowledge the Afrocentric spirituality of the black church and ascribe to it a revolutionary blackness. Chapter Two demonstrates, through Ntozake
            Shangeâ&#x80;&#x99;s for colored girls who have considered suicide / when the rainbow is enuf and Sonia Sanchezâ&#x80;&#x99;s Iâ&#x80;&#x99;ve Been a Woman, that women
            must first give birth to themselves spiritually before they can successfully accomplish the birth of the black nation. Chapter Three examines five poems by Carolyn
            Rodgers, Jayne Cortez, Sonia Sanchez, Sarah Webster Fabio, and Sharon Bourke, arguing that black women poets activate nommo, the power of words to influence action,
            when they write jazz poetry; as cultural and spiritual leaders in their own rights, they serve as a type of co-priestess to the black community when they recognize the
            jazz artist as a spiritual priest. Conclusively, I determine that there is indeed space for the recognition of the intended spiritual goals and accomplishments of the
            Black Arts Movement, and especially of marginalized black womenâ&#x80;&#x99;s poetry.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4007</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2034&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4007</label>
         <document-type>open_thesis</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2034</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T09:47:13-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2353000</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4007</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Jerrilyn McGregory&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Dennis Moore&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Maxine L.
                  Montgomery&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>MA, Master of Arts</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of English</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2007-06-25T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Understanding Developmental Students' Constructions of Personal Vision and Experiences with Community College</title>
         <publication-date>2005-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hodges</lname>
               <fname>Kelley</fname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Vision</keyword>
            <keyword>Experiences</keyword>
            <keyword>Personal Mastery</keyword>
            <keyword>Community College</keyword>
            <keyword>Developmental Students</keyword>
            <keyword>Mathematics</keyword>
            <keyword>Science</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Education</discipline>
            <discipline>Higher Education and Teaching</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis uses a qualitative action research design involving developmental mathematics students at a community college. The students are first
            generation, low income, and they are enrolled in developmental mathematics. The heart of this research is about helping students who are at risk for failure. The
            research questions focus on how developmental mathematics students construct a vision for their lives, and how that vision fits into community college, and how they
            experience current reality. The results of the study convey the vulnerabilities of the developmental learners. They experience feelings of being powerless, low
            self-image, multiple responsibilities, conflict and confusion. The results also highlight the strengths of developmental learners. They experience transformation of
            thought and desire for self-actualization&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4009</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2032&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4009</label>
         <document-type>open_thesis</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2032</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T09:41:35-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2353003</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4009</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Nancy T. Davis&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Ken Shaw&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Penny Gilmer&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>MS, Master of Science</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Middle and Secondary Education</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2005-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Meanings and Experiences of Parent Intuition and Competence</title>
         <publication-date>2004-01-29T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Green</lname>
               <fname>Stefanie</fname>
               <mname>Jill</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Intuition</keyword>
            <keyword>Parent Competence</keyword>
            <keyword>Parenting</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Social Work</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;This research study sought to understand parents? use of intuition in their parenting and how its use affects their sense of competence as a parent.
            Systems Theory and Phenomenology provided the foundation for this study. Metaphors were created for each participant to enhance the understanding of intuition. In-depth
            interviews were used to gather the data. Results indicated that parents use their intuition to help them make decisions in their parenting. The most common time for the
            parents to use their intuition involved the safety and well-being of their child(ren). Overall, the parents of this study agreed that intuition does help them in their
            parenting. Intuition as a process is discussed. As one acquires more experience and history, and becomes more adept at picking up subtle clues, one is able to build
            upon that foundation, which may lead to a spontaneous knowing. Intuition is also discussed as an internal safety system of the parent. Subsystems from this study
            included past experiences and/or history, subtle clues found in the environment, and emotional and mental thoughts. Subsystems from the literature included the physical
            level of intuition, and spiritual beliefs and thoughts. Suggestions for further research are made, including the idea for a study to create a concrete operationalized
            definition of intuition. A cross-cultural study might yield more information on how other cultures utilize their intuition. Suggestions for practice include the
            teaching of intuition at all levels of education.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4011</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2030&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4011</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2030</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T09:35:38-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352989</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4011</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Marsha Rehm&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Barbara Allison&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Charles Figley&lt;/p&gt;
                  &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Leo Rotan&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Family and Child Sciences</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2004-01-29T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Identification and Characterization of Cellular Titin</title>
         <publication-date>2008-05-28T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Cavnar</lname>
               <fname>Peter</fname>
               <mname>James</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Myosin</keyword>
            <keyword>Titin</keyword>
            <keyword>Cellular Titin</keyword>
            <keyword>Stress Fibers</keyword>
            <keyword>Alpha-Actinin</keyword>
            <keyword>Muscle</keyword>
            <keyword>Kinase</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Biology</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;We previously discovered a large titin-like protein - c-titin - in chicken epithelial brush border and human blood platelet extracts that binds
            alpha-actinin and organizes arrays of myosin II bipolar filaments in vitro. RT-PCR analysis of total RNA from human megakaryoblastic (CHRF-288-11) and mouse fibroblast
            (3T3) nonmuscle cells have revealed sequences identical to known titin gene exon sequences that encode parts of the Z-line, I-band, PEVK domain, A-band, and M-line
            regions of striated muscle titins. These sequences are differentially spliced in patterns not reported for any striated muscle titin isoform. Rabbit polyclonal
            antibodies raised against expressed protein fragments encoded by the Z-repeat and kinase domain regions react with the c-titin band in Western blot analysis of platelet
            extracts and immunoprecipitate c-titin in whole platelet extracts. Immunofluorescent localization reveals the majority of the c-titin colocalizes with alpha-actinin and
            actin in 3T3 and Indian Muntjac deer skin fibroblast stress fibers. Our results suggest that differential expression of titin gene exons in nonmuscle cells yields
            multiple novel isoforms of the protein c-titin which are incorporated with the actin stress fiber structures.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Titin contains a dually regulated
            serine/threonine kinase domain belonging to the myosin light chain kinase family localized in the M-line region of titin. Titin kinase has a direct effect on
            myofibrillogenesis and protein turnover. Our lab has previously reported the identification of a novel nonmuscle titin isoform, cellular titin. Cellular titin localizes
            to the stress fibers of spread fibroblast and epithelial cells and contains sequence identical to the skeletal titin kinase domain. Expression of the cellular titin
            kinase domain in epithelial cells localize in a punctate manner previously reported, followed by a breakdown of stress fiber architecture resulting in cell rounding and
            eventual loss of adhesion to the substratum. Yeast two-hybrid analysis of the titin kinase domain has identified a novel binding partner HS1 associated protein X-1
            (Hax-1). Previously identified as anti-apoptotic; its interaction with cortactin, Rac, and Gï&#x81;¡13 illustrates Hax-1 as a mediator in stress fiber regulation and
            organization. Taken together our results suggest a novel role for cellular titin kinase in stress fiber integrity and regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4012</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2029&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4012</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2029</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T09:35:08-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352978</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4012</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Thomas C.S. Keller, III&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Outside Committee Member - Charles Ouimet&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Thomas
                  M. Roberts&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Robert H. Reeves&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Laura R. Keller&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Biological Science</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2008-05-28T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>The King of Love</title>
         <publication-date>2004-05-06T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hobbs</lname>
               <fname>Willie</fname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Tallahassee</keyword>
            <keyword>C.K. Steele</keyword>
            <keyword>Frenchtown</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;â&#x80;&#x9c;The King of Loveâ&#x80;&#x9d; is a creative dissertation. It is a novel focusing on the struggles of the African-American community to
            bridge gulfs and divides within itself. The location and setting of the story are in the present day and revolve heavily around the historical black community of
            Tallahassee, Florida known as Frenchtown.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the tradition of Randolph Fisherâ&#x80;&#x99;s â&#x80;&#x9c;Walls of Jerichoâ&#x80;&#x9d;, the novel is
            primarily steeped in the genre of the detective mystery and offers elements of satire throughout its narrative. As with Walter Moseleyâ&#x80;&#x99;s highly influential
            Easy Rawlins detective series, issues of class, race, culture and heritage are at the forefront of the story. This lead to the employment of the first person point of
            view, which best captured the humor, flavor and idiosyncrasies of the Frenchtown inhabitants as well as its supporting characters.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4013</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2028&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4013</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2028</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T09:33:23-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352987</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4013</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Virgil Suarez&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Darryl Dickson-Carr&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Elizabeth
                  Stuckey-French&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Maria Del C Martinez&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of English</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2004-05-06T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>"Hitler is Here": Lynching in Florida During the Era of World War II</title>
         <publication-date>2004-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hobbs</lname>
               <fname>Tameka</fname>
               <mname>Bradley</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Willie James Howard</keyword>
            <keyword>A.C. Williams</keyword>
            <keyword>Jesse James Payne</keyword>
            <keyword>African Americans in Florida</keyword>
            <keyword>Lynching</keyword>
            <keyword>Cellos Harrison</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>History</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;This historical study will examine four lynchings that took place in Florida during the 1940s. The investigations include the lynching of A. C. Williams
            in Gadsden County in 1941; Cellos Harrison in Jackson County in 1943; Willie James Howard in Suwannee County in 1944; and Jesse James Payne in Madison County in 1945.
            In addition to describing the circumstances surrounding each incident, this study also discusses the reaction of local law enforcement, Florida state public officials,
            the federal government, and the press. To tell these stories, the study relied on records from local and state governments, investigative records of the U. S.
            Department of Justice and the Federal Bureau of Investigation and, oral history from family members and residents of the communities in which these lynchings
            occurred.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The study gives these incidents further exploration, in attempting to fit them into the chronology of the lynching phenomenon in the United
            States by extracting similarities as well as changes in the practice of lynching itself. These lynchings also indicate an increasingly negative reaction but segments of
            the American public against such acts of violence. This was due in part to U. S. participation in World War II and the governmentâ&#x80;&#x99;s increasing concern about
            the nationâ&#x80;&#x99;s international reputation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4014</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2027&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4014</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2027</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T09:29:29-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352981</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4014</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Maxine D. Jones&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Darryl Carr&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - James P. Jones&lt;/p&gt;
                  &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Joe M. Richardson&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Matt D. Childs&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of History</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2004-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Development Of A DNA Probe Assay For Rare Transfer RNAs And Its Use In Measuring The Expression Of The ArgX Gene In Escherichia Coli</title>
         <publication-date>2004-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <lname>Cavnar</lname>
               <fname>Katie</fname>
               <mname>M</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Rare tRNAs</keyword>
            <keyword>Sandwich Hybridization Assay</keyword>
            <keyword>ArgX Gene</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Biology</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;In Escherichia coli, the argX gene is the first gene in a cluster with three other tRNA genes. The tRNA products of the three downstream genes, hisR,
            leuT and proM are abundant in E. coli, and all four of the tRNAs are processed from the same precursor RNA transcript. The argX promotor appears to be a strong promotor
            and is preceded by an Up element. By all accounts, the gene product of argX, tRNAarg3 should be a major tRNA. Like the three downstream genes in this cluster, argX must
            be transcribed at a high level because of its location at the beginning of the gene cluster. However, tRNAarg3 is considered a rare tRNA in E. coli. Its low level is
            correlated with the low codon usage of its corresponding codon, CGG. It appears that the nucleotide sequence just upstream of argX can base pair with the
            5â&#x80;&#x99;- end of the tRNA. This alternative secondary structure in the precursor RNA transcript may prevent the maturation of the tRNAarg3 by disrupting the base
            pairing of the aminoacyl-tRNA stem. This structure is required by ribonuclease P for maturation of the 5'-ends of all tRNAs and also prevents the 3'-exonucleases from
            digesting into the tRNA from the CCA (3'-) end. Different constructs of the argX gene have been cloned into high copy number plasmids. These constructs differ in the
            nucleotides just upstream of the argX gene. Deletion of nucleotides results in higher expression of tRNAarg3 and the loss of an alternative secondary structure
            involving the 5â&#x80;&#x99;â&#x80;&#x93;end of the tRNA. The data suggests alternative secondary structure formation during transcription may in part be responsible
            for tRNAarg3 abundance in E. coli. A tRNA assay has been developed to measure the levels of rare tRNAs from extracts. This assay is both sensitive and specific and
            demonstrates its ability to detect low levels of tRNAs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4015</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2026&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4015</label>
         <document-type>open_thesis</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2026</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T09:24:43-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352964</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4015</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Robert H. Reeves&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Thomas Keller&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Lloyd
                  Epstein&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>MS, Master of Science</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Biological Science</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2004-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Developing Technological Pedagogical Content Knowledge in Preservice Teachers through Microteaching Lesson Study</title>
         <publication-date>2007-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Cavin</lname>
               <fname>Rose</fname>
               <mname>Mobley</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Preservice Teachers</keyword>
            <keyword>Technology</keyword>
            <keyword>Teacher Education</keyword>
            <keyword>tpck</keyword>
            <keyword>Technological Pedagogical Content Knowledge</keyword>
            <keyword>Microteaching Lesson Study</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Education</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;This research study was conducted to explore the development of technological pedagogical content knowledge (TPCK) in preservice teachers as they
            participated in microteaching lesson study (MLS). Participants were six preservice teachers enrolled in the required technology course for mathematics and science
            teacher education at a small rural college. The researcher was also the instructor for the course.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The TPCK framework, modeled by Mishra and Koehler
            (2006) as three overlapping circles, focuses on the interrelationships between the three components of technology, pedagogy and content, and involves an awareness of
            the effectiveness of incorporating a technological tool in a content lesson. In microteaching lesson study (M. FernÃ¡ndez, 2005), preservice teachers worked in small
            groups through repetitive cycles of teaching, reflecting, and modifying a group lesson. Teaching to a group of students enrolled in a college mathematics class provided
            a situated learning environment for the preservice teachers to experience teaching with technology.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Data were collected qualitatively via audio and
            video recordings, observations, interviews, and course documents. Data analysis was conducted using the TPCK framework in conjunction with various state and national
            standards related to the three components of TPCK. Findings indicate that the preservice teachers developed an awareness of the nuances of teaching with technology in a
            student-centered learning environment, recognizing that traditional "methods" of teaching such as sequencing, pacing and written directions took on special
            characteristics when technology was involved. Factors seen to have an influence on the preservice teachers' decisions related to the use of a technological tool
            included participation as students in modeled lessons, comfort level, and the preservice teachers' beliefs related to learning and teaching with technology.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Preservice teachers also expanded their views on mathematical knowledge. Prior to the MLS process, the preservice teachers focused on technology used at a
            procedural level to "do the math faster," while post MLS data indicated a shift towards a more conceptual view of technology enhanced mathematics. One fringe benefit
            recognized by the preservice teachers was the experience of working with their peers in fine-tuning a lesson to maximize student learning, gaining practical experience
            applicable toward future school-based instruction.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4017</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2024&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4017</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2024</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T09:16:16-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352952</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4017</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Co-Chair - Kenneth L. Shaw&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Co-Chair - Maria L. FernÃ¡ndez&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Outside Committee Member - Alysia
                  D. Roehrig&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Elizabeth M. Jakubowski&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Leslie N. Aspinwall&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Middle and Secondary Education</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2007-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Historical and Performance Perspectives for OBOE from selected Chamber Repertoire</title>
         <publication-date>2005-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Caulder</lname>
               <fname>Stephanie</fname>
               <mname>B</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Woodwind Pedagogy</keyword>
            <keyword>Wind Octets</keyword>
            <keyword>Wind Chamber Music</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Music</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;This treatise identifies significant passages for oboe from eight standard chamber works: Mozartâ&#x80;&#x99;s Serenade No.10 in B-flat Major, K.361 and
            Serenade No.12 in C Minor, K.388, Beethovenâ&#x80;&#x99;s Octet in E-flat Major, Op.103, Dvorakâ&#x80;&#x99;s Serenade in D Minor, Op.44, Straussâ&#x80;&#x99;s Serenade
            for Wind Instruments, Op.7, Gounodâ&#x80;&#x99;s Petite Symphonie, Op.90, Hindemithâ&#x80;&#x99;s Septet for Wind Instruments, and Vareseâ&#x80;&#x99;s Octandre. Each
            excerpt is presented in single part form.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Extensive program notes for each piece including historical background of the composer and composition are
            provided. In addition, performance and practice suggestions are included for elements such as phrasing, intonation, dynamics, fingerings, and articulation. This study
            is intended to be a collection of excerpts and a reference guide in preparation for rehearsals and performances for professional, student, or amateur oboists, as well
            as a pedagogical tool for instructors.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4019</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2022&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4019</label>
         <document-type>open_treatise</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2022</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T09:08:41-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352890</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4019</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Eric Ohlsson&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Frank Kowalsky&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Jeffrey Keesecker&lt;/p&gt;
                  &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Patrick Dunnigan&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>DM, Doctor of Music</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>College of Music</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2005-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Investigations Into Civil War Medicine Through Some Artifacts Recovered From The U.S. Army Transport Maple Leaf</title>
         <publication-date>2004-04-06T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Grayson</lname>
               <fname>Ronald</fname>
               <mname>Ira</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>sanitary commission</keyword>
            <keyword>shipwreck</keyword>
            <keyword>maple leaf</keyword>
            <keyword>civil war medicine</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis examines an assemblage of artifacts recovered from the U.S. Army Transport Maple Leaf. This assemblage was part of a cargo of baggage from
            three regiments of Union Army troops sent to Florida in 1864. The U.S. Sanitary Commission, a civilian aid organization, likely distributed the assemblage studied to
            one or all of these regiments. It consists of non-military equipment likely used for medical practices. The assemblage is examined in context of the emergence of
            sanitary medical practices and the emergence of sanitation in the medical community during the Civil War. This thesis argues that newly introduced, more effective
            sanitary practices of the Civil War were not adopted after the war because the underlying cause of infection and disease was not understood. It was only after the
            advent of germ theory in the 1890â&#x80;&#x99;s that the medical community adopted sanitation practices first recommended in the early
            1860â&#x80;&#x99;s.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4021</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2019&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4021</label>
         <document-type>open_thesis</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2019</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T09:02:20-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352885</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4021</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Dr. Cheryl Ward&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Dr. Clarence Gravlee&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Dr. Michael
                  Faught&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>MA, Master of Arts</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Anthropology</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2004-04-06T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>An Archaeological Study of Glamis: The Role of a 19th-Century Iron Barque</title>
         <publication-date>2004-03-25T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Ho</lname>
               <fname>Bert</fname>
               <mname>Shiping</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Cayman Islands</keyword>
            <keyword>Norwegian Shipping</keyword>
            <keyword>Barques</keyword>
            <keyword>Iron Barque</keyword>
            <keyword>Anthropology</keyword>
            <keyword>Archaeology</keyword>
            <keyword>Maritime History</keyword>
            <keyword>Shipwrecks</keyword>
            <keyword>Maritime Archaeology</keyword>
            <keyword>Shipwreck Archaeology</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;The late 19th and early 20th -century shipping industry experienced a transition in ship technology from sail to steam propulsion. This thesis examines
            the continued use of iron-hulled barques during this transitional period, with a discussion of previously studied examples of the remains of iron-hulled, sailing
            barques from the 19th century. Archaeological and archival research gathered on Glamis strongly supports the hypothesis that the shipwreck site GC013 is the iron-hulled
            barque, Glamis, wrecked in 1913 off the coast of Grand Cayman, Cayman Islands, B.W.I. Despite the advances of steamship technology, some countries not only continued
            but also expanded their use of sailing ships. I describe and explain this practice using Norway as a paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4022</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2018&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4022</label>
         <document-type>open_thesis</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2018</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T08:57:31-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352866</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4022</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Cheryl Ward&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Margaret Leshikar-Denton&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Michael
                  Faught&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>MS, Master of Science</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Anthropology</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2004-03-25T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Birthing The New Birth: The Natural Philosophy Of Childbirth In The Theology Of Jonathan Edwards</title>
         <publication-date>2009-05-14T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Gray</lname>
               <fname>Lauren</fname>
               <mname>Davis</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Natural Philosopher</keyword>
            <keyword>Theologian</keyword>
            <keyword>Ova</keyword>
            <keyword>Nicolas Malebranche</keyword>
            <keyword>Revivalism</keyword>
            <keyword>First Great Awakening</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Religion</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;â&#x80;&#x9c;It may be in the new birth as it is in the first birth.â&#x80;&#x9d; So wrote theologian Jonathan Edwards in his
            â&#x80;&#x9c;Miscellaniesâ&#x80;&#x9d; note numbered 241, named â&#x80;&#x9c;Regenerationâ&#x80;&#x9d;. The â&#x80;&#x9c;new birthâ&#x80;&#x9d; that he spoke of was the
            process of religious conversion whereby God takes away oneâ&#x80;&#x99;s sinful nature and instills a new, regenerate nature. The process of the new birth is
            intricately linked to the â&#x80;&#x9c;first birth,â&#x80;&#x9d; which refers to physical childbirth. This thesis explores the ways in which eighteenth-century
            conceptions of childbirth helped to shape the new birth theology of Edwards. While historians have tended to portray Edwards, the revivals that he spawned, and new
            birth theology as erasing the distinctions of gender, this thesis will argue that Edwardsian evangelicalism actually highlighted the sinfulness of
            women.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4024</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2016&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4024</label>
         <document-type>open_thesis</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2016</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T08:53:43-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352864</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4024</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Amanda Porterfield&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Amy Koehlinger&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - John
                  Corrigan&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>MA, Master of Arts</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Religion</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2009-05-14T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>The Lieder of Paul Dessau</title>
         <publication-date>2006-10-19T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hix</lname>
               <fname>Michael</fname>
               <mname>Thomas</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Socialist Realism</keyword>
            <keyword>German Democratic Republic</keyword>
            <keyword>Deutsche Demokratische Republik</keyword>
            <keyword>Ddr</keyword>
            <keyword>Art Song</keyword>
            <keyword>Music History</keyword>
            <keyword>Twentieth-Century</keyword>
            <keyword>Lieder</keyword>
            <keyword>Dessau</keyword>
            <keyword>Maurer</keyword>
            <keyword>Brecht</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Music</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;The composer Paul Dessau (1894-1979) was arguably one of the most significant composers of the Deutsche Demokratische Republik (German Democratic
            Republic) yet a large portion of his music remains unperformed and unknown. This treatise will examine Paul Dessauâ&#x80;&#x99;s lieder and will provide a reference
            guide for musicians interested not only in Dessauâ&#x80;&#x99;s music, but also the evolution of German lieder through the mid-twentieth century. This treatise will
            survey examples of Dessauâ&#x80;&#x99;s lieder with the intent of exploring his compositional style, aesthetic, political philosophy, and his approach to varying song
            styles and poets. Special attention will be directed to placing Dessauâ&#x80;&#x99;s output within its historical, political, and cultural context.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4025</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2015&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4025</label>
         <document-type>open_treatise</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2015</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T08:49:50-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352857</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4025</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Timothy Hoekman&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Denise Von Glahn&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - MarcÃ­a
                  Porter&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Roy Delp&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>DM, Doctor of Music</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>College of Music</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2006-10-19T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>The Lee Erwin Collection: The Music of Silent Film Composer and Theater Organist Lee Erwin</title>
         <publication-date>2003-10-23T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hix</lname>
               <fname>Michael</fname>
               <mname>Thomas</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>ATOS</keyword>
            <keyword>Cincinnati</keyword>
            <keyword>Twentieth Century</keyword>
            <keyword>American Music</keyword>
            <keyword>Film Music</keyword>
            <keyword>Cinema Organ</keyword>
            <keyword>Theatre Organ</keyword>
            <keyword>Theater Organ</keyword>
            <keyword>Lee Erwin</keyword>
            <keyword>Silent Film Music</keyword>
            <keyword>Marchal</keyword>
            <keyword>Arthur Godfrey</keyword>
            <keyword>WLW</keyword>
            <keyword>American Theater Organ Society</keyword>
            <keyword>Gaylord Carter</keyword>
            <keyword>Wurlitzer</keyword>
            <keyword>Gloria Swanson</keyword>
            <keyword>Organ</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Music</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;From the 1960s until his death in September of 2000, Lee Erwin championed silent films, silent film music, and the theater organ. Growing up in
            Huntsville, Alabama during the first quarter of the twentieth century, Lee Erwin (1908 â&#x80;&#x93; 2000) was an organist for several of the countryâ&#x80;&#x99;s
            great movie palaces during the silent film era. From 1930 until 1931 Erwin studied in France with organist AndrÃ© Marchal and with Nadia Boulanger. Upon returning to
            the United States, Erwin began his lengthy career in radio and television working with Arthur Godfrey. In 1967, Erwin was commissioned by the American Theater Organ
            Society to compose organ music for the Gloria Swanson film Queen Kelly. It was this film that led his career back into the consoles of the great American theater
            organs. He toured extensively playing thousands of concerts of organ music during silent film showings. Erwin, believing that cue sheets originally compiled for these
            films during the silent film era were â&#x80;&#x9c;full of the musical clichÃ©â&#x80;&#x99;s of the 1920s,â&#x80;&#x9d; composed new scores to over 100 silent films. In
            addition to preserving this unique art form through his performing and composing, Erwin also worked with several pupils. These pupils, including Jeff Weiller and Ben
            Model, work full time composing and performing, striving to keep this genre of art music alive.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This thesis discusses the life and music of Lee
            Erwin, with emphasis on the film music he composed after 1967 and his role in preserving the art of silent film accompanying. His educational background will be
            examined as well as his compositional style and aesthetic. The body of this thesis serves as an introduction and index to the Lee Erwin Collection, an archive of
            documents pertaining to the life and compositions of Lee Erwin. The Lee Erwin Collection will be housed at the Library of the College Conservatory of Music at the
            University of Cincinnati.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4026</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2014&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4026</label>
         <document-type>open_thesis</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2014</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T08:46:03-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352855</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4026</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Denise Von Glahn&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Michael B. Bakan&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Michael
                  Corzine&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>MM, Master of Music</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>College of Music</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2003-10-23T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Vorticity-Based Detection of Tropical Cyclogenesis</title>
         <publication-date>2005-11-21T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hite</lname>
               <fname>Michelle</fname>
               <mname>Marie</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Quikscat</keyword>
            <keyword>Seawinds</keyword>
            <keyword>Tropical Disturbance</keyword>
            <keyword>Tropical Cyclogenesis</keyword>
            <keyword>Vorticity</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Meteorology</discipline>
            <discipline>Oceanography and Atmospheric Sciences and Meteorology</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;Ocean wind vectors from the SeaWinds scatterometer on QuikSCAT and GOES imagery are used to develop an objective technique that can detect and monitor
            tropical disturbances associated with the early stages of tropical cyclogenesis in the Atlantic basin. The technique is based on identification of surface vorticity and
            wind speed signatures that exceed certain threshold magnitudes, with vorticity averaged over an appropriate spatial scale. The threshold values applied herein are
            determined from the precursors of 15 tropical cyclones during the 1999-2004 Atlantic hurricane seasons using research-quality QuikSCAT data. Tropical disturbances are
            found for these cases within a range of 19 hours to 101 hours before classification as tropical cyclones by the National Hurricane Center (NHC).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The
            15 cases are further subdivided based upon their origination source (i.e., easterly wave, upper-level cut-off low, stagnant frontal zone, etc). Primary focus centers on
            the cases associated with tropical waves, since these waves account for approximately 63% of all Atlantic tropical cyclones. The detection technique illustrates the
            ability to track these tropical disturbances from near the coast of Africa. Analysis of the pre-tropical cyclone (TC) tracks for these cases depict stages, related to
            wind speed and precipitation, in the evolution of an easterly wave to tropical cyclone.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4027</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2013&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4027</label>
         <document-type>open_thesis</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2013</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T08:42:26-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352838</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4027</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - James J. O'Brien&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Mark A. Bourassa&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Paul D.
                  Reasor&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>MS, Master of Science</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Earth, Ocean and Atmospheric Sciences</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2005-11-21T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Weight Status and Decision Making in a Food Selection Task</title>
         <publication-date>2006-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Gray</lname>
               <fname>Brian</fname>
               <mname>C.</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Decision Making</keyword>
            <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
            <keyword>Protocol Analysis</keyword>
            <keyword>Sequential Analysis</keyword>
            <keyword>Chi Square</keyword>
            <keyword>Weight Status</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Educational Psychology</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;Americans are the most overweight and obese individuals in the world, and these conditions are associated with many negative physical and psychological
            conditions. Health psychology research has adequately explained intention and initiation of weight-loss behaviors, but has had less success with their long term
            maintenance. Additionally, the psycho-social mechanisms that translate intention into action remain hidden and health psychology research relies on time-general designs
            relating baseline construct assessments to later behavioral performance. The purpose of this study was to examine the relationships among weight status,
            decision-making, and nutritional outcomes in an immediate, in-the-moment food selection task to determine whether obese and normal weight individuals make food-related
            decisions in fundamentally different ways.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Twenty-four obese and 23 normal weight participants received instructions about verbalizing decisions and,
            after two practice tasks, asked to talk aloud as they selected dinner items from a simulated menu from a well-known fast food restaurant. Following protocol analysis
            guidelines, the verbalizations were recorded, transcribed, and segmented into discrete â&#x80;&#x9c;thought unitsâ&#x80;&#x9d;, which were coded as one of six possible
            decision processes. Group differences in the proportions these single units comprised of group totals and, following sequential analysis guidelines, proportional
            distributions of conditional two-unit sequences were analyzed using chi-square analyses. Results indicated significant differences between the groups in terms of their
            use of â&#x80;&#x9c;opposing argumentsâ&#x80;&#x9d; in their decision process. Results also indicated significant differences between the groups in terms of two-thought
            sequences. After proposing an item for consideration, normal weight participants offered more supporting and opposing arguments while obese participants delayed
            decision making and rejected items.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Results indicated that normal weight and obese participants made food-related decisions differently. These
            findings shed light on cognitive processes involved when individuals decide among food items. Future research can build upon this topic and these methods to eventually
            develop a thorough understanding of in-the-moment food selection. These findings have clinical relevance as they may be used to help obese individuals make food
            decisions differently. Clinicians may help clients understand how they make food decisions and help them change their food decisions style in order to increase their
            chances of long term weight loss success.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4028</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2012&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4028</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2012</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T08:39:48-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352552</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4028</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - F. Donald Kelly&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Allan Jeong&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Gary Peterson&lt;/p&gt;
                  &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Gershon Tenenbaum&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Richard Tate&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Educational Psychology and Learning Systems</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2006-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>The Influences of Environment on the Music Preferences of Children with and without Disabilities</title>
         <publication-date>2010-10-28T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hirano</lname>
               <fname>Madoka</fname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Music Preference Children Disabilities</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Music</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purposes of the study were to: (1) to investigate the musical preferences of children with and without disabilities, (2) to better understand the
            musical environments in which children with and without disabilities listen to music, (3) to determine the extent to which children with and without disabilities
            participate in different music activities in or outside of school, and (4) to determine whether parents of children with disabilities identify the musical preferences
            of their children differently than their children do. Participants (N = 497) in the study included parents of children who attend a regular school in Japan (n = 382),
            children who attend a special education school in Japan (n = 107), and their parents (n = 107). Two survey questionnaires addressing the purposes of the study were
            administered to participants. Results indicate that Japanese children with disabilities prefer to listen to songs from TV shows for children, nursery rhymes, Enka, and
            jazz significantly more than children without disabilities, while children without disabilities prefer to listen to cartoon songs and Japanese Pop music. The study
            revealed that more than one third of children with and without disabilities listen to music with either parent(s) or grandparent(s). Additionally, children without
            disabilities are more likely to listen to music with a sibling(s) and/or friend(s) than are children with disabilitiesâ&#x80;&#x94;a result perhaps of their social
            isolation. There were no significant differences between children with and without disabilities and the musical activities in which they engage. Results also indicated
            that children with disabilities prefer Japanese Pop music more than their parents realize. Clinical implications for the study are the need for music therapists: (1) to
            attend to the musical differences between children with and without disabilities, (2) to be attune to the musical preferences of children with disabilities, and (3) to
            not rely on parental reports of childrenâ&#x80;&#x99;s musical preferences, but rather, to attend to verbal expressions, or when necessaryâ&#x80;&#x94;nonverbal
            indicators of childrenâ&#x80;&#x99;s musical preferences.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4029</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2011&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4029</label>
         <document-type>open_thesis</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2011</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T08:38:11-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352834</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4029</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Alice-Ann Darrow&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Dianne Gregory&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Jayne
                  Standlley&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>MM, Master of Music</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>College of Music</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2010-10-28T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>El Lenguaje EcolÃ³gico de Manuel Rivas: Retranca, Resiliencia y Reexistencia</title>
         <publication-date>2004-04-30T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Castro-VÃ¡zquez</lname>
               <fname>Isabel</fname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Essay</keyword>
            <keyword>EcologÃ­a del Lenguaje</keyword>
            <keyword>Accented Cinema</keyword>
            <keyword>GlobalizaciÃ³n EcolÃ³gica</keyword>
            <keyword>Galicia</keyword>
            <keyword>Spain</keyword>
            <keyword>Colonial</keyword>
            <keyword>Postcolonial</keyword>
            <keyword>Gnosis Espiral</keyword>
            <keyword>Journalism</keyword>
            <keyword>Poetry</keyword>
            <keyword>Resistencia</keyword>
            <keyword>Novel</keyword>
            <keyword>Polivalencia</keyword>
            <keyword>Culture</keyword>
            <keyword>Literary Theory</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Arts and Humanities</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;The ecology of language aims at the preservation of biodiversity in nature, language and culture which would result into an ecological form of
            globalization. This task has been undertaken by Manuel Rivas (b. 1957), a contemporary Galician writer who is also an internationally renowned poet, novelist, short
            story writer, essayist and journalist and writes mainly in a peripheral language. His ecological use of language is better perceived in his representation of
            â&#x80;&#x9c;the other,â&#x80;&#x9d; in his creation of a Galician social imaginary and in his global approach. By means of different postcolonial theories, I have
            explained and theorized Rivasâ&#x80;&#x99;s use of Galician tradition in his ecological globalization process. The author is aware of a particular Galician way of
            thinking and relating to the world (gnosis) that reconciles opposites thus allowing for self-expression while acknowledging official discourse. Throughout centuries of
            colonialisms, this gnosis has sustained an attitude that is at once a form of resilience and reexistence perceived in what is traditionally called retranca. Rivas
            captures this Derridean, though constructive, gnosis and uses it, including retranca, as a literary technique to avoid the contamination of language and the
            fossilization of meanings that impose on us to fixed categories without allowing for plurality. As a result biodiversity is preserved and Galicia recreated in a most
            contemporary way while, at the same time, an ecological form of globalization is generated.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4031</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2009&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4031</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2009</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T08:32:27-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352566</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4031</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Brenda Cappuccio&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Outside Committee Member - David Kirby&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Delia
                  Poey&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Jean Graham-Jones&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Modern Languages and Linguistics</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2004-04-30T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Negative Information Action: Assaulting Citizen Choice by Subverting the Democratic Process</title>
         <publication-date>2007-10-29T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hinson</lname>
               <fname>Christopher</fname>
               <mname>L.</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>National Security</keyword>
            <keyword>Information</keyword>
            <keyword>Covert Programs</keyword>
            <keyword>Democracy</keyword>
            <keyword>Conspiracy</keyword>
            <keyword>Secrecy</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation explores evidence and provides insight to secrecy-related information actions that can and are sometimes used as a method to
            circumvent established government policy and law. These information actions may also be used to cover up such circumventions after the fact. To better understand
            secrecy as a negative information action and its impact on democracy, secrecy-related information actions are described according to objectives, methods, the use of
            information technology and knowledge support. Negative information actions are willful and deliberate acts designed to keep government information from those in
            government and the public entitled to it Negative information actions are not in accordance with either the rule of law or the system of checks and balances. Negative
            information actions used by government officials to violate policies and laws during the Iran-Contra Affair are identified, analyzed and categorized by type. The impact
            of negative information actions on enlightened citizen understanding are demonstrated using the Negative Information Action Model by assigning a location according to
            type on a continuum of enlightened citizen understanding. Findings are compared with democratic theory, conspiracy doctrine and conspiracy theory. Conclusions and
            recommendations relating the legal environment as an impediment to information flow as it relates to public accountability and the rule of law are
            made&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4032</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2007&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4032</label>
         <document-type>restricted_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2007</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T08:31:12-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352585</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4032</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Corinne Jorgensen&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Michelle Kazmer&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Paul Marty&lt;/p&gt;
                  &lt;p&gt;Outside Committee Member - Lance deHaven-Smith&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Campus-Only Restricted</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>School of Library and Information Studies</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2007-10-29T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>A Survey of Florida High School Instrumental Music Programs: Rationale for the Inclusion of Jazz Ensemble Experience in Music Teacher Training</title>
         <publication-date>2011-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hinkle</lname>
               <fname>Jonathan</fname>
               <mname>Rhame</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>jazz</keyword>
            <keyword>dissertations</keyword>
            <keyword>music education</keyword>
            <keyword>florida high school</keyword>
            <keyword>teacher training</keyword>
            <keyword>jazz ensemble</keyword>
            <keyword>survey</keyword>
            <keyword>instrumental</keyword>
            <keyword>music programs</keyword>
            <keyword>inclusion</keyword>
            <keyword>florida</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Music</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;During the past 60 years, jazz music has slowly become recognized as a genre worthy of study in high school music programs throughout the United States.
            Only a few researchers have analyzed large samples of jazz-related instruction in instrumental music programs, and of these studies no data were collected to
            investigate the inclusion of jazz in Florida high school instrumental programs or the background in jazz of directors in these programs. Therefore, the purpose of this
            study was to gather data on high school-level instrumental music programs in Florida and the band directors associated with these programs in an attempt to answer the
            following research questions: (1) What is the current status of instrumental jazz course offerings in Florida high schools? (2) Is there a relationship between the
            status of jazz course offerings in Florida high schools and demographic data of the programs or the directors who teach in these programs? (3) Is there a relationship
            between the status of jazz course offerings in Florida high schools and the band directorsâ&#x80;&#x99; experience with and training in jazz? Florida high school band
            directors (N = 239), representing a response rate of 46.5%, replied to an online survey instrument containing 21 comprehensive questions. Demographic data of
            participants and the programs they were directing, as well as questions associated with their training, experience, opinions, and attitudes toward jazz-related
            instruction were cross-analyzed quantitatively. The findings of this study revealed that many Florida high school music programs (38.5%) do not offer students
            opportunities in jazz music and that these programs parallel deficiencies found in schools in other states. The data gathered from Florida high school directors and
            programs suggest that a teacherâ&#x80;&#x99;s actual or perceived level of training in jazz genres, most notably through performance experience, is the greatest factor
            in the presence of jazz-related courses in high school music programs. Additionally, teachersâ&#x80;&#x99; degree of jazz performance experience or training may have a
            considerable influence on their level of anxiety and comfort with jazz genres. Directorsâ&#x80;&#x99; lack of background in jazz inhibits the potential for jazz-related
            courses to be included in high school programs; thus, limiting the musical experiences of the students they teach. Data also suggest that teachers may be more willing
            to initiate courses in jazz if they were required to or were offered the opportunity to participate in jazz ensembles during their teacher preparation. To facilitate
            such participation, a college-level jazz ensemble that is specifically designed for the experience and pedagogical needs of future music teachers, in a non-intimidating
            and positive atmosphere where appropriate literature is performed at a high level, may be helpful to music education majors. Additionally, jazz may be more widely
            understood and appreciated if current and future school instrumental music teachers strive to provide opportunities in jazz instruction and performance to as many
            students as possible. Such an endeavor can be accomplished by incorporating an appropriate balance of ensembles and courses in their program.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4034</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2005&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4034</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2005</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T08:21:41-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352559</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4034</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Clifford K. Madsen&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Alice-Ann Darrow&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - William
                  Fredrickson&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Outside Committee Member - William Landing&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>College of Music</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Revisiting the Sex-differentiation Hypothesis: A Refinement and Examination of Lilienfeld's (1992) Hypotheses</title>
         <publication-date>2008-08-06T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Castro</lname>
               <fname>Yessenia</fname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Antisocial Personality</keyword>
            <keyword>Somatization</keyword>
            <keyword>Gender Differences</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Psychology</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;The current study investigated Lilienfeldâ&#x80;&#x99;s (1992) sex differentiation hypothesis. Modifications were made to highlight the importance of
            examining social expectations of acceptable behavior for women and men. Modifications were also made to move away from broad constructs (i.e. negative emotionality and
            behavioral disinhibition) and instead examine narrower constructs (i.e., anxiety and impulsivity) with more explanatory utility. Results support the utility gender role
            in predicting antisocial symptoms, but not somatic symptoms. Some support for a relationship between somatization and impulsivity as predicted by the behavioral
            disinhibition hypothesis was found, but results indicate that the relationship between somatization and antisociality is better accounted for by anxiety, and this is
            consistent with the negative emotionality model. The sex-differentiation aspect of Lilienfeldâ&#x80;&#x99;s hypotheses was largely unsupported. Future research in the
            area can benefit from attending to the cautions presented in this paper, as well as the limitations noted.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4035</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2004&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4035</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>2004</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T08:17:31-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352540</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4035</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Joyce Carbonell&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Outside Committee Member - Kevin Beaver&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Ashby
                  Plant&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Ellen Berler&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Jeanette Taylor&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Psychology</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2008-08-06T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>The Perceptions, Behaviors, and Experiences of Extended Persisters in the Florida Community College System</title>
         <publication-date>2005-02-23T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Graunke</lname>
               <fname>Connie</fname>
               <mname>Washburn</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Extenders</keyword>
            <keyword>Persisters</keyword>
            <keyword>Excess Hours</keyword>
            <keyword>Completers</keyword>
            <keyword>Persistence</keyword>
            <keyword>Time to Degree</keyword>
            <keyword>Credit Hours to Degree</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Education</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to explore the perceptions, behaviors, and experiences of student who persisted in the Florida Community College system
            and accumulated credit hours beyond those required for graduation. The study was a theory-guided study utilizing qualitative methods associated with orientational
            qualitative inquiry, intended to clarify and elucidate Beanâ&#x80;&#x99;s Theory of Student Attrition. The data collection consisted of interviewing 18 students using a
            semi-structured interviewed based on variables derived from Beanâ&#x80;&#x99;s theory. The purposeful sample of respondents was selected from students who had earned an
            A.A. degree and accumulated excess hours. The excess hours ranged from 5 to 212 beyond the 60 required for an associate in arts degree. The sample was further striated
            by the size of the community colleges from which the students were selected.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A cross-case analysis was done using the constant comparative analysis
            of data. The analysis found little difference among the respondents from different size community colleges. However, significant differences were found when a
            cross-case analysis was made based on the number of accumulated excess hours.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Family background was found to be a significant factor in influencing
            the accumulation of excess hours, in that students who expressed that they were â&#x80;&#x9c;expected to go on to collegeâ&#x80;&#x9d; by their families were more
            strongly goal directed and as a consequence earned fewer excess hours. Students that had family responsibilities also tended to stop out, withdraw, and fail courses
            more due to those responsibilities than students who did not have families. Finally, two other themes emerged as major findings that contributed to the accumulation of
            excess hours: Changing majors and earning more than one degree. The students that changed majors more often had the greatest number of excess hours. In addition, some
            students whose ultimate goal was a bachelors degree, would first complete an associate in science degree to provide them with employment options and then go back and
            complete an associate in arts in order to transfer into a bachelor program, thereby accumulating excess hours. The major variables that influenced the accumulation of
            excess hours were: strong goal commitment, family responsibilities, major certainty and earning more than one degree.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4041</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1998&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4041</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>1998</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T08:04:26-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352502</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4041</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Beverly Bower&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Joseph C. Beckham&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Ralph Brower&lt;/p&gt;
                  &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Robert Schwartz&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>EDD, Doctor of Education</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2005-02-23T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>The Interaction Between The Reader And The Reading Situation: The Roles Of Text Cues, Reading Tasks, And Individual Differences In Reading Ability</title>
         <publication-date>2003-08-02T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hilliard</lname>
               <fname>Amy</fname>
               <mname>E.</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Interactive Readers</keyword>
            <keyword>Passive/Active Readers</keyword>
            <keyword>Text Cues</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Psychology</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;Text cues indicate to the reader where and how to direct his or her reading-related processing. Findings in the text cue literature are mixed. The
            reading task and individual differences in reading ability might account for these results. A dichotomous view of the readerâ&#x80;&#x99;s ability to actively process
            text has been prevalent for many years. Some researchers see the reader as passive and some see the reader as active. A new view has emerged in the last few years: the
            view of the reader as interactive. Proponents of this view think that all aspects of the reader, such as individual differences, and the reading situation, including
            the reading task, influence text processing. The present experiment examined these three views using the methodology of the text cue literature, as well as an on-line
            measure of text processing. If readers are interactive, then they should process target information according to the presence of cues, the type of information contained
            within the target sentence, and aspects of the reading task, such as comprehension question type. College students read experimental texts and answered comprehension
            questions after each text. Embedded within the texts were summary target sentences and importance target sentences from which reading time data was collected. These
            sentences contained information that was conceptually important to the texts. There were two versions of each text. In one version of a text half the target sentences
            were preceded ix by a text cue sentence and half were not. In the other version of the same text, the text cue sentences were placed before the target sentences that
            had not been preceded by text cue sentences in the other version. Only one type of text cue sentence ever preceded a target sentence. Importance text cue sentences
            preceded importance target sentences, and summary text cue sentences preceded summary target sentences. What made a sentence important or a summary was the type of
            information contained with in the sentence. After reading each text the participantsâ&#x80;&#x99; task was to answer either summary comprehension questions or
            importance comprehension questions. The type of comprehension question participants answered was the aspect of reading task manipulated. Participants answered only one
            type of question throughout the experiment. How the quantity of a participantâ&#x80;&#x99;s reading situation knowledge influenced their cognitive processing was
            assessed by comparing the reading times and comprehension question from the first text participants read to the second text they read. During the first text
            participants had no idea what type of comprehension question they were to answer, so they only had previous experience with comprehension questions to guide their
            processing decisions. During the second text, participants had knowledge of the type of question that they were most likely going to be asked. This variable was titled
            text presentation order. Finally, an aspect of the reader was measured. Participants were grouped by Individual differences in reading comprehension. The participants
            were divided into two reading level groups, good and poor readers, by use of the VSAT test. The results of this study support the view of the reader as interactive. For
            the first x text, the type of target sentence and the presence or absence of text cue sentences did not make a significant difference. However, after having answered
            comprehension questions for the first task, participants knew what to expect of from their reading task and could use this information to guide their cognitive
            processing while reading the second text. Results from the second text show that there were processing differences between participants in the importance question
            condition and participants in the summary question condition. Surprisingly, there was no effect of individual differences in reading ability, and only one variable was
            significant for the comprehension question data. These findings could be due to the measure of individual differences in reading ability chosen for this experiment.
            Question type was the only variable that influence the number of correct comprehension questions. No differences in the total number of correct answers to comprehension
            questions fits with some text cue research that has found no general differences in the remembrance of text cued and non text cued information. These results indicate a
            complex interaction between the reader, the reading situation, and the reading task.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4042</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1997&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4042</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>1997</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T08:02:05-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352493</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4042</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Rick Wagner&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Colleen Kelley&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Joe Torgesson&lt;/p&gt;
                  &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Robert Contreras&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Vivian Fueyo&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Psychology</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2003-08-02T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Who Writes the Family History, Anyway? A Look At Adoption Within Wise Children And Oranges Are Not The Only Fruit</title>
         <publication-date>2010-04-23T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Grantham</lname>
               <fname>Mariann</fname>
               <mname>Leigh</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Adoption</keyword>
            <keyword>Adoption Studies</keyword>
            <keyword>Linda Hutcheon</keyword>
            <keyword>Marianne Novy</keyword>
            <keyword>Margot Gayle Backus</keyword>
            <keyword>Oranges Are Not The Only Fruit</keyword>
            <keyword>Wise Children</keyword>
            <keyword>Angela Carter</keyword>
            <keyword>Jeanette Winterson</keyword>
            <keyword>Sexing the Cherry</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis shows the different ways the tension between the societal ideal of the family (something that is in and of itself a construct) and the
            constructed family plays out in two 20th century British novels, Oranges Are Not the Only Fruit and Wise Children. This tension is brought into focus in part by the
            form the novel itself takes, that of historiographic metafiction, a sort of self-aware fiction that explores historical personages or the definition of what history
            really is. The different ways in which the novels play with history (the documented means by which events, which have no meaning, turn into fact, which is ascribed a
            meaning) is explored as a way of examining adoption within these two novels.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4043</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1996&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4043</label>
         <document-type>open_thesis</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>1996</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T07:58:07-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352479</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4043</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Barry Faulk&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Eric Walker&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Maxine
                  Montgomery&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>MA, Master of Arts</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of English</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2010-04-23T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Mental Representation Mediation in Expert Golf Putting</title>
         <publication-date>2007-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hill</lname>
               <fname>Leonard</fname>
               <mname>A.</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Mediation</keyword>
            <keyword>Deliberate Practice</keyword>
            <keyword>Motor Control</keyword>
            <keyword>Problem Analysis</keyword>
            <keyword>Planning</keyword>
            <keyword>Mental Representation</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Psychology</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;The current study is an initial investigation of expert performance theory in golf putting. According to Ericsson and colleagues (Ericsson &amp; Smith,
            1991; Ericsson, Krampe &amp; Tesch-RÃ¶mer, 1993), a performerâ&#x80;&#x99;s mental representations are the primary mediator of performance and the degree of refinement
            of those representations determine the level of performance in a domain. This studyâ&#x80;&#x99;s purpose is to investigate golf putting performance in situations that
            require representational guidance to analyze, plan and execute putts in various putting situations. Using a screen to block visual access to the putting situation
            (occluded condition), this study examined expert and novice golfers in various putting situations to determine their ability to perform using only their mental
            representations to establish direction and distance when putting to targets of different lengths and over different terrain. Results showed that on a level putt from 23
            feet, both experts and novices averaged within just over two feet laterally from the target (direction) and overall 3.5 to 5.5 feet from the target. This represents
            general competence in putting under occluded conditions, though none were trained in this condition. On substantially more difficult occluded putts, all golfers
            averaged within 10 feet of the target, on targets where they averaged more than 8 feet in the visible condition. Having acquired more refined representations, the
            experts, on the 23 foot occluded single target, were 35% more accurate than the less skilled golfers, and in the most complex putting situation (multi-breaking 28 foot
            putt), experts were 37% more accurate. These results support Ericsson and colleagues expert performance theories in mental representation mediation of performance and
            representational refinement mediation of levels of performance.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4045</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1994&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4045</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>1994</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T07:54:48-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352472</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4045</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - K. Anders Ericsson&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - E. Ashby Plant&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Gershon
                  Tenenbaum&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - J. Franklyn Johnson&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Neil Charness&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Psychology</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2007-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>An Examination of Racial Differences on the MMPI-2 Profiles of Incarcerated Women</title>
         <publication-date>2004-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Castro</lname>
               <fname>Yezzennya</fname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Race</keyword>
            <keyword>Incarcerated Women</keyword>
            <keyword>MMPI-2</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Psychology</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;The present study examined whether or not differential MMPI-2 profile elevations would appear between African American and Caucasian incarcerated women.
            MANOVAs followed by discriminant function analyses found support for differential profile elevations, replicating previous findings. In addition the current study
            investigated whether or not experience of racial discrimination may account for these differential profile elevations between African Americans and Caucasians. This
            hypothesis was not supported in the current study, however, age and educational level did appear to account for differential profile elevations. Implications and future
            directions are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4046</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1993&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4046</label>
         <document-type>open_thesis</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>1993</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T07:52:48-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352466</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4046</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Joyce L. Carbonell&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Bryan R. Loney&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - E. Ashby
                  Plant&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>MS, Master of Science</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Psychology</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2004-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>The Use of Pedometers for Promoting Increased Physical Activity Levels and Positive Attitudes towards Physical Activity in Children</title>
         <publication-date>2006-02-27T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Hill</lname>
               <fname>Kory</fname>
               <mname>Jon</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Physical Activity</keyword>
            <keyword>Physical Education</keyword>
            <keyword>Pedometer</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Sports Sciences</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study sought to examine the influence of wearing pedometers on activity levels, attitudes towards activity, and knowledge of physical
            activity.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The participants were members of three intact 4th-grade Physical Education classes from three elementary schools in the Calhoun County
            School District, Calhoun County, Alabama.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A simplified and modified version of the System for Observing Fitness Instruction Time (SOFIT; McKenzie,
            Sallis, &amp; Nader, 1991) was used to gather information regarding the student's physical activity levels during physical education classes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A
            questionnaire assessed affective traits and knowledge of physical activity. The TPB Questionnaire was designed to elicit information on: intentions, attitude, and
            perceived behavioral control as they relate to physical activity. The added knowledge variable consisted of two questions that related the ideas of physical activity
            levels and health benefits.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The treatment consisted of wearing pedometers either during physical education class only or all day long. There was also
            a Control Group that did not wear any pedometers at all. The four week treatment period was preceded by two weeks of gathering baseline data and two weeks of post
            treatment observation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There were no significant differences in the physical activity levels of students wearing pedometers when compared to students
            without pedometers. A MANOVA revealed main effects indicating that the group wearing the pedometers all day had a significant change in perceived behavioral control
            scores and knowledge scores. The results are noteworthy because perceptions of behavioral control and fitness knowledge are associated with higher levels of physical
            activity.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4047</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1992&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4047</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>1992</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T07:50:31-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352457</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4047</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Charles Imwold&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Gershon Tenenbaum&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Kristi
                  Walsdorf&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Tom Ratliffe&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Sport Management</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2006-02-27T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Microstructural and Superconducting Properties of V Doped M&lt;sub&gt;g&lt;/sub&gt;B&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; Bulk and Wires</title>
         <publication-date>2004-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Castillo</lname>
               <fname>Oscar</fname>
               <mname>Eduardo</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Magnesium Diboride</keyword>
            <keyword>MgB2</keyword>
            <keyword>Superconductor</keyword>
            <keyword>Vanadium</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Mechanical Engineering</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;Studies of the effects of doping MgB2 bulk and steel-sheathed wires with V are presented. Samples having the nominal composition
            Mg&lt;sub&gt;1-x&lt;/sub&gt;V&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;B&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; (x = 0, 0.05, 0.10, 0.15) have been fabricated and investigated to understand the role of
            V doping on the phase formation, microstructure and superconducting properties. Characterization of superconducting samples was carried out using XRD, SQUID, ESEM/EDS,
            and I&lt;sub&gt;c&lt;/sub&gt; measurements. Results show an enhancement of superconducting properties with V doping, and suggest the presence of V in the
            superconducting phase. Wires with J&lt;sub&gt;c &lt;/sub&gt;values as high as 1.4 x 10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; A/cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; have been
            achieved.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4048</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1990&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4048</label>
         <document-type>open_thesis</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>1990</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T07:47:56-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352450</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4048</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Justin Schwartz&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Peter Kalu&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Simone
                  Peterson-Hruda&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>MS, Master of Science</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Mechanical Engineering</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2004-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Helping Teachers "Do What They Do": Teachers' Perceptions of the Influence of Peer and Adminitrator Suppor on Teacher Retention</title>
         <publication-date>2009-10-29T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Grantham</lname>
               <fname>Jonathan</fname>
               <mname>Hires</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Peer</keyword>
            <keyword>Attrition</keyword>
            <keyword>Retention</keyword>
            <keyword>Administrator</keyword>
            <keyword>Support</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Education</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to investigate which forms of administrative and peer support facilitate teacher retention. Specifically, I explored both
            administrative and peer forms of support in an attempt to understand the relationships between this support and teacher retention. While most researchers are aware the
            growing attrition rate within the teaching profession (Darling-Hammond, 2001; Hope; 2000; McCreight, 2000), this paper focused on what can be done to keep teachers in
            the profession. My goal was to understand teachersâ&#x80;&#x99; perspectives on how administrative support and peer support influenced the rate of teacher retention at
            a school. Since teachers are leaving high minority, low socio-economic schools at an alarming rate (Ingersoll, 1999), administrators need to be aware of the reasons
            behind the attrition. After closely examining the literature on attrition, I examined specific concepts related to what administrators and other teachers can do to
            support first-year teachers and encourage them to remain in the profession.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This study is a meaningful contribution to our understanding of teacher
            retention and attrition because it explores the perspectives of teachers at critical junctures in their careers. I used a qualitative case study approach to investigate
            teacher attrition and retention at a Florida high school. I collected data from interviews with focus groups to answer research questions. Guided by extant literature,
            I recruited and then interviewed four different groups of teachers based on years of experience. These focus groups were made up of: (1) five teachers in their
            first-year of teaching; (2) five teachers who have taught for three or four years, (3) six teachers who have between five to eight years of teaching experience and (4)
            four teachers who have been teaching for at least twenty-five years.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;My findings suggested that first-year teachers perceived a need for help from
            many sources. They wanted assistance from the district, administrators and from teachers. However, after this first-year of teaching, findings suggested that teachers
            perceive a need for less, but more focused support. In summary, I offered conclusions and recommendations based on the findings of this research. Specifically, my
            recommendations were made for district personnel and school-level personnel, primarily administrators and teachers. I also listed some areas of future research that
            might produce rich data that could change the way researchers view teacher retention in high schools.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4049</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1989&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4049</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>1989</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T07:47:20-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352446</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4049</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Jeffrey S. Brook&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>EDD, Doctor of Education</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2009-10-29T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>

      <document>
         <title>Climate Feedback Analysis of the GFDL IPCC AR4 Global Warming Simulation</title>
         <publication-date>2009-07-23T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
         <authors>
            <author>
               <institution>Florida State University</institution>
               <lname>Castet</lname>
               <fname>Christelle</fname>
               <mname>Clemence</mname>
            </author>
         </authors>
         <keywords>
            <keyword>Climate Change</keyword>
            <keyword>Radiative Forcing</keyword>
            <keyword>Climate Response</keyword>
            <keyword>Feedbacks</keyword>
            <keyword>Sensitivity</keyword>
         </keywords>
         <disciplines>
            <discipline>Meteorology</discipline>
         </disciplines>
         <abstract>&lt;p&gt;Both observed and modeled global warming pattern shows a large surface polar warming and a large upper atmospheric warming in the tropics. This pattern
            leads to an amplification (reduction) of the temperature gradient at upper levels (surface). Physical processes behind this temperature change are the external
            radiative forcing, and subsequent feedback processes that may amplify or dampen the climate response. This unique warming pattern suggests that high latitudes are very
            sensitive to climate change and also the area where the largest warming projection uncertainties occur. The objective of this study is to apply a new coupled
            atmosphere-surface climate feedback-response analysis method to quantify the contributions of the external forcing alone (doubling of carbon dioxide), and subsequent
            feedback processes to the 3-D global warming pattern in the GFDL_CM2.0 model. The feedbacks under consideration include the water vapor feedback, surface albedo
            feedback, surface turbulent heat flux feedback, and the sum of the change in cloud radiative forcing (CRF), vertical convective, and large-scale scale dynamical
            feedback. The partial temperature changes due to the external forcing and due to individual feedbacks are additive and their sum converges toward the temperature change
            produced by the original GFDL_CM2.0 global warming simulations. Therefore, our attributions of the global warming patter to individual thermodynamic and dynamical
            processes are mathematically robust and physically meaningful.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The partial temperature change due to the water vapor feedback is found to be the
            largest contributor to the globally averaged surface warming. It is twice as large as the warming due to the external radiative forcing alone. The surface albedo
            feedback and change in surface cloud radiative forcing increase the surface temperature by a smaller amount. In addition, the changes in atmospheric cloud forcing and
            large-scale dynamics, as well as the surface turbulent heat flux feedback, contribute to an overall damping the surface warming.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In terms of spatial
            pattern of global warming, the external forcing alone would cause a large surface warming in the extratropics. The water vapor feedback strengthens the tropical warming
            substantially and the ice/snow albedo feedback contributes to polar warming amplification. The atmospheric dynamical feedbacks associated with the enhancement of
            vertical convection in the tropics acts to amplify the warming in the upper troposphere at the expense of reducing the warming in the lower troposphere and at the
            surface in the tropics. The dynamical feedbacks due to the strengthening of the poleward energy transport contribute to a warming in the entire troposphere and the
            surface in high latitudes. At the surface and in the lower troposphere, the additional warming brought by the change in circulations strengthens the warming due to
            thermodynamical forcings (e.g., external forcing, water vapor feedback, and ice albedo feedback). In the upper troposphere, the warming brought by the change in
            circulations dominates the cooling due to thermodynamical forcings. As a result, the entire troposphere becomes warmer. The stratospheric cooling is entirely due to the
            external radiative forcing.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
         <coverpage-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/etd/4050</coverpage-url>
         <fulltext-url>http://diginole.lib.fsu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1988&amp;amp;context=etd&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
         <label>4050</label>
         <document-type>open_dissertation</document-type>
         <type>article</type>
         <articleid>1988</articleid>
         <submission-date>2011-11-16T07:44:14-08:00</submission-date>
         <publication-title>Electronic Theses, Treatises and Dissertations</publication-title>
         <context-key>2352433</context-key>
         <submission-path>etd/4050</submission-path>
         <fields>
            <field name="advisor1" type="string">
               <value>&lt;p&gt;Committee Chair - Ming Cai&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Outside Committee Member - William Dewar&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Mark Bourassa&lt;/p&gt;
                  &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Paul Ruscher&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Committee Member - Xiaolei Zou&lt;/p&gt;</value>
            </field>
            <field name="availability" type="string">
               <value>Open Access</value>
            </field>
            <field name="degree_name" type="string">
               <value>PHD, Doctor of Philosophy</value>
            </field>
            <field name="department" type="string">
               <value>Department of Earth, Ocean and Atmospheric Sciences</value>
            </field>
            <field name="embargo_date" type="date">
               <value>2011-11-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
            </field>
            <field name="publication_date" type="date">
               <value>2009-07-23T00:00:00-07:00</value>
            </field>
         </fields>
      </document>
</documents>
