<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Spatial Disparity and Educational Sorting of U.S. Internal Migration</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-0952-4551</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Masek</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Marty</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n84030040">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Carlson</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Elwood</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1950-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2014069337">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Schmertmann</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Carl P.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mehauer">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hauer</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Mathew</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kreynolds3">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Reynolds</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">John K.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Sociology</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (127 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Over the past few decades, U.S. communities have become increasingly unequal in terms of aggregate educational composition. Extant research shows that educational composition predicts community prosperity and community wellbeing consistently and strongly. Research on changes in community educational composition over time suggests that internal migration—movement within a country—plays a key role in such change, but this research does not often quantify or measure the role of internal migration. Therefore, this dissertation closely examines the role of internal migration in heightening or mitigating between-community educational disparity. I use 2013-2017 American Community Survey (ACS) data to estimate several measures of migration at relatively small geographic units, covering every square mile of the United States. These geographic units serve as "communities" for which I also construct a measure of educational capital (EC)—the proportion of the population ages 25 to 64 with at least a bachelor's degree.The current study has four analytic chapters with related research goals. The first analytic chapter explores the relative contributions of origin and destination community EC in shaping the educational composition of migration flows between origin-destination pairs. The second analytic chapter examines the effect of extant community EC on net migration patterns by education group—bachelor's degree and higher (BA+) and less than bachelor's degree (&lt;BA)—and age group to evaluate the potential for internal migration to exacerbate or mitigate between-community disparity. The third analytic chapter articulates population processes underlying migration-induced changes in community EC. And the fourth analytic chapter estimates the effect of migration-induced change on community EC annually and over one generation. All analyses focus on ages 25 to 64. Findings in the first analytic chapter indicate that migration flows from a single origin can have widely different educational compositions depending on destination EC. Educational sorting occurs to destinations such that destinations with highly educated populations attract migration flows that are even more highly educated than the destination and the origin, on average. Analogously, destinations with low levels of education attract migration flows with even lower levels of education than the destination and the origin, on average. Findings in the second analytic chapter measuring net migration for each community indicate that current internal migration patterns reinforce existing between-community spatial disparity in EC. Not only do communities with high extant EC receive positive net migration of the BA+ group, but these highly educated communities experience negative net migration of the &lt;BA group. At the same time communities with low EC experience positive net migration of the &lt;BA group and negative net migration of the BA+ group. Thus, migration of the &lt;BA group contributes to between-community disparity in EC in tandem with the migration of the BA+ group. Further findings reveal a life cycle in this pattern for the BA+ group, while the &lt;BA group has no such life cycle. The third analytic chapter exploring the processes of migration-induced change indicate that changes in the number of BA+ adults in communities occurring via migration more commonly result from differences in the educational compositions of in-migrants compared to out-migrants rather than the sheer number of in-migrants compared to out-migrants. The fourth analytic chapter demonstrates the magnitude of migration-induced change in EC for each community over a generation if migration patterns remain unchanged, ignoring for the moment other population processes. In this scenario, mean community EC decreases as measures of variability (i.e., standard deviation) increase. Communities already at the top continue to pull ahead, and many at the bottom see sizeable decreases in community EC over time. I also highlight exceptional cases. Overall, findings reveal a self-reinforcing pattern of selective internal migration between U.S. communities that exacerbates spatial disparity in community EC by conferring further advantage to EC-rich communities at the expense of those that are already disadvantaged.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Sociology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 9, 2022.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Communities, Education, Geographic Disparity, Internal Migration, Spatial Disparity</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Elwood Carlson, Professor Directing Dissertation; Carl Schmertmann, University Representative; Mathew Hauer, Committee Member; John Reynolds, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036659">
      <mods:topic>Demography</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">2022_Masek_fsu_0071E_16984</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Sociology</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-10-10T17:55:50.20129-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
