<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Changing with the Times? </title>
      <subTitle>A Generational Comparison of the Effects Parental Social Ties on Crime and Drug Use during Emerging Adulthood</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <namePart type="family">Lloyd</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kristin</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2019007242">
      <namePart type="family">Turanovic</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jillian J.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1985-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lmcwey">
      <namePart type="family">McWey</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Lenore M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n99025425">
      <namePart type="family">Hay</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Carter H.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ssiennick">
      <namePart type="family">Siennick</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sonja E.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Criminology and Criminal Justice</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Criminology and Criminal Justice</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (164 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>Emerging adulthood is a phase of the life-course unique to the 21st century that was brought about by rapid social, cultural, and demographic changes to society (Arnett, 2000a, 2000b, 2004, 2007, 2015). These changes include delays in traditional markers of adulthood, such as marriage and employment, and prolonged time spent in higher education between the ages of 18-29. As a result, recent generations of young adults may no longer develop traditional social ties (marriage, employment) thought to be protective against crime and deviance until later on in life (e.g., in their thirties). This may result in other sources of influence, such as social ties to parents, being more important protective factors against crime and deviance in emerging adulthood today than in prior generations. Accordingly, drawing from key perspectives in life-course criminology and cohorts of Baby Boomers and Millennials, the goal of this dissertation is to examine generational differences in the influence of parental social ties throughout emerging adulthood. Further, this dissertation seeks to understand whether transitions into marriage, employment, and college in emerging adulthood affect the influence of parental social ties, and if these patterns vary across generations. To this end, this dissertation answers three primary research questions. The first research question is, "are there generational differences in the influence of parental social ties on within-person changes in crime and drug use during emerging adulthood?" The second question is, "are the effects of parental social ties on crime and drug use in emerging adulthood conditioned by marriage and employment for Baby Boomers and Millennials?" And finally, the third question is, "are the effects of parental social ties on crime and drug use moderated by enrollment in higher education for Baby Boomers and Millennials?" These questions are answered using data from the National Youth Survey (NYS) and the National Longitudinal Survey of Youth 1997. The NYS represents Baby Boomers who were born between 1959 and 1965 (N=1,036; N*T=6,741 person-waves). The NLSY97 represents the earliest Millennials, born between 1980 and 1984 (N=7,178; N*T=43,068 person-waves). Each data source follows respondents from adolescence through early emerging adulthood (up to age 24). Analyses reveal two key findings with respect to the research questions investigated in this dissertation. Regarding the first research question, which seeks to understand the effects of social ties to parents on within-person changes in crime and drug use across generations, findings indicate that social ties to parents have a protective effect against crime in emerging adulthood for Millennials, but not for Baby Boomers. Further, predicted probabilities show that there is a generational difference in this relationship over time, as the probability of offending among those with weak ties to parents in the Millennial cohort increases over time compared to those with strong ties to parents. Among Baby Boomers, however, there is no real difference in offending over time between those with strong ties and weak ties to parents. The second and third research questions center on the moderating effects of key adult transition events (i.e., marriage, employment, and college enrollment) on the influence of social ties to parents on emerging adults' crime and drug use. Results show that marriage and college enrollment are not significant moderators for Baby Boomers or Millennials with respect to crime or drug use. Employment is not a significant moderator with respect to crime for Baby Boomers or Millennials either, but it is a statistically significant moderator of drug use among Millennials only. However, predicted probabilities estimated for each of these models indicate that the effects are marginal. Thus, it can be concluded that marriage, employment, and college enrollment have no substantively meaningful conditioning effects of crime or drug use among Baby Boomers or Millennials. More broadly, these findings highlight the need for additional inquiry into the salience of social ties to parents during emerging adulthood and have implications for both theory and policy. Theoretical implications include expanding studies of parental attachment and support to incorporate measures of the quality of adult child-parent relationships, the continuation of the learning process between parents and their adult children, and the need to expand longitudinal research to accommodate multiple generations for theoretical testing. Findings also reveal the need to tailor policies to emerging adults in contemporary society, such as implementing programming that encourages prosocial parent-child relationships beyond adolescence.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the College of Criminology and Criminal Justice in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 8, 2021.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">Baby Boomers, crime, drug use, emerging adulthood, life-course criminology, Millennials</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jillian J. Turanovic, Professor Directing Dissertation; Lenore McWey, University Representative; Carter Hay, Committee Member; Sonja E. Siennick, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002994">
      <topic>Criminology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2021_Summer_Lloyd_fsu_0071E_16615</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Criminology and Criminal Justice</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-01-31T17:03:20.741646-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
