<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Essays in the Economics of Mental Health</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <namePart type="family">Magee</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ellis</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/djcooper">
      <namePart type="family">Cooper</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">David J.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n84098064">
      <namePart type="family">Weissert</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">William G.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2017025730">
      <namePart type="family">Hamman</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">John R.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/asemykina">
      <namePart type="family">Semykina</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Anastasia</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Economics</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (134 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>One in five adults in the United States experiences mental illness in a typical year. Less than half get treatment. The novel coronavirus pandemic has increased mental health pressures above that baseline. This dissertation addresses the intersection between mental health and economic issues building upon two important findings: (1) the economic finding of a bidirectional causal relationship between mental health and economic outcomes and (2) the psychiatric finding that mental-wellness-focused smartphone applications (apps) are effective. Mental wellness apps are low-cost, scalable, and pandemic-appropriate, but current use is limited. Given the relationship between mental health and economic outcomes and the efficacy of mental wellness apps, can we leverage mental wellness apps to improve economic outcomes? The first two chapters of this dissertation report on my randomized controlled trials testing strategies to expand usage of mental wellness apps. First, I find providing mental-wellness-app privacy ratings increases selection of privacy-preferred apps by six percentage points among likely app users, a significant shift that could drive competitive pressures toward improved privacy protections. Likely app users care about this issue and are willing to pay one third of the average monthly app price to access the ratings, suggesting $80 million in social welfare gains from implementing privacy ratings nationally. Second, among individuals willing to download apps, I find offering $3 for downloading, installing, and using a mental wellness app for two weeks does not have significant mental wellbeing or work productivity impacts on my sample as a whole. Instead, high-productivity individuals see productivity increases of 0.127 standard deviations, worth $20 per high-productivity participant over the measured second week of treatment. However, low-productivity participants experience no change or negative changes in productivity as a result of the intervention. Taken together, these findings suggest further research is necessary to clarify the conditions under which workplace use of mental wellness apps is beneficial before broadly implementing similar incentive schemes. Third, I investigate the presence and impacts of gender-identity-related social stigma on health and work outcomes using Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System (BRFSS) data maintained by the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). I find transgender status is associated with poorer mental and physical health and controlling for mental and physical health status and demographic characteristics, transgender Americans experience poorer work outcomes than similarly situated cisgender (that is, not transgender) Americans, by about $10,000 per year. This outcome is not the result of using stigmatized health behaviors, as after controlling for adverse childhood experiences, transgender people use no more stigmatized health behaviors than their cisgender peers. Mental wellbeing is a key component of individual and social welfare and human capital. This dissertation investigates the intersection between mental health and economics, a promising and important area for economic research.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Economics in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 6, 2021.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">apps, behavioral economics, covid-19, experimental economics, mental health, transgender</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">David Cooper, Professor Directing Dissertation; William Weissert, University Representative; John Hamman, Committee Member; Anastasia Semykina, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85108638">
      <topic>Public health</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85083615">
      <topic>Mental health</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87002293">
      <topic>Information technology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2021_Summer_Magee_fsu_0071E_16687</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Economics</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-01-31T17:03:20.741646-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
