<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Immigrant Paradox in the Black Box? </title>
      <subTitle>Evaluating in-Prison Maladaptive Behaviors among Foreign-and Native-Born Persons</subTitle>
      <nonSort>An</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-8046-8919</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Kuper</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Julie L.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jcopp">
      <namePart type="family">Copp</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jennifer E.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2019007242">
      <namePart type="family">Turanovic</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jillian J.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1985-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/stripodi">
      <namePart type="family">Tripodi</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Stephen J.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n99025425">
      <namePart type="family">Hay</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Carter H.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2015068755">
      <namePart type="family">Brancale</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Julie Mestre</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Criminology and Criminal Justice</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Criminology and Criminal Justice</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (146 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >The U.S. regularly incarcerates its residents, where time spent behind bars is overwhelmingly negative (Massoglia, 2008a; Rose &amp; Clear, 1998). But not all persons have an equal chance of incarceration. State and federal policies target ethnically heterogenous neighborhoods in ways that lead to residents' disparate surveillance, arrest, and incarceration, even while research demonstrates that such policies are damaging (Menjívar &amp; Abrego, 2012; Peterson &amp; Krivo, 2010). Contrary to traditional criminological theory, evidence suggests that cultural diversity may work to keep individuals and their communities safer (Wright &amp; Rodriguez, 2014). Indeed, an immigrant paradox has been found, where immigrants are less likely to commit violence, use substances, or offend, though they are more often exposed to criminogenic environments (Salas-Wright et al., 2016).Criminological literature takes this protective effect of diversity for granted, neglecting to unpack the immigrant paradox. It is unknown whether the immigrant paradox extends to prison—where foreign-born persons are less likely to exhibit mental health crises or engage in misconduct—or if incarceration will undo their resilience. Yet effective correctional policy must be sensitive to the diversity of those incarcerated. Guided by theory and research on the immigrant paradox, prison misconduct, and mental health behind bars, the goal of this study is to examine whether incarcerated native- and foreign-born persons vary in the number and kinds of misconducts they engage in and/or mental health crises they experience. Further, this dissertation examines whether relationships vary by sources of heterogeneity within the immigrant group, including sending country, race, and detainer status. To solve these research puzzles, this study asks three primary research questions. First, do incarcerated immigrants differ from non-immigrants in their involvement in prison misconduct? Second, do incarcerated immigrants differ from non-immigrants in their likelihood of experiencing an in-prison mental health crisis? Third, and finally, do incarcerated immigrants who are subject to deportation differ from those who are not in their involvement in prison misconduct or experience of a mental health crisis? Data from administrative records on the full population of incarcerated adults housed in a state prison in the western U.S. between 2010 and 2020 (N=58,289) are used. Over 13% (N=7,697) of individuals come from over 120 different countries, not including the U.S. or its territories. Data trace all administrative details of individuals' in-prison experiences from intake to release. This rich information, coupled with the growing diversity of this western state, render this system ideal for advancing theory and research on the bounds of the immigrant paradox. Analyses find support for an in-prison immigrant paradox, but they further reveal that the effect of immigrant status varies by race. That is, incarcerated immigrants are expected to engage in fewer counts and types of misconduct than their non-immigrant counterparts and are less likely to experience in-prison mental health crises. But patterns differ for property misconduct and are not uniform across racially diverse individuals. Instead, the immigrant paradox is pronounced among Latinx persons, where these individuals are less likely to engage in most types of prison infractions and have lower odds of mental health crises compared to those of other races. Alternatively, White immigrants more often experience mental health crises behind bars relative to immigrants of color. These differences signify that the protective factors that drive the immigrant paradox may not be readily available to all foreign-born persons, that diverse persons present with diverse in-prison needs, and that prior experience with hardship may be one reason that immigrants are resilient to adversity. Finally, incarcerated immigrants who face deportation only slightly differ from those who do not in their involvement in misconduct or their experience of mental health crises. While immigrants with detainers were less likely to engage in drug misconduct or experience in-prison mental health crises than those without, findings did not significantly differ by detainer status for overall misconduct or any other infraction type. As such, incarcerated immigrants may already anticipate deportation, and certain characteristics about immigrants who receive detainers may matter more than the threat of deportation itself. Yet further investigation of the effect of deportation is needed. Broadly, the substantive effect of the immigrant paradox is diminished in a prison setting and is conditioned by heterogeneous statuses of immigrants, but it is not erased. Treating immigrants harshly for fear that they pose a dangerous criminal threat is unfounded and is only successful in perpetuating legal violence against them. While additional work is needed to further unpack the immigrant paradox in incarcerated settings, we must be mindful of clumsy, overly punitive social policies that harm foreign-born populations.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the College of Criminology and Criminal Justice in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 22, 2024.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">heterogeneity, immigrant paradox, incarceration, mental health, prison, prison misconduct</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jennifer Copp, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Jillian J. Turanovic, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Stephen Tripodi, University Representative; Carter Hay, Committee Member; Julie Brancale, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002994">
      <topic>Criminology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Kuper_fsu_0071E_18656</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Criminology and Criminal Justice</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
