<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Mechanochemical Synthesis, Characterization, and Quadrupolar NMR Crystallography of Multicomponent Crystals</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-1544-4205</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Vojvodin</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Cameron Spencer</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rschurko">
      <namePart type="family">Schurko</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Robert W.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2006081590">
      <namePart type="family">Hill</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">S. (Stephen Olof)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/latturne">
      <namePart type="family">Latturner</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Susan</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rsilvers">
      <namePart type="family">Silvers</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Robert</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (305 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >This dissertation focuses on the mechanochemical synthesis of several families of multicomponent crystals (MCCs), their characterization by multinuclear solid-state NMR (SSNMR) and powder X-ray diffraction (PXRD), and their structure determination by single crystal XRD (SCXRD) and/or NMR-guided Rietveld refinements. All MCCs reported herein are inorganic-organic hybrids featuring different combinations of simple organic molecules with alkali or ammonium chloride salts, and sometimes water. The MCCs were prepared via ball milling, with syntheses optimized for maximum yield and efficiency. NMR crystallography (NMRX), which features a combination of multinuclear SSNMR, XRD methods, and dispersion-corrected plane-wave DFT calculations, was used to validate, refine, and in some cases, aid in solving the crystal structures via Rietveld analysis. The NMRX work herein relies upon quadrupolar nuclides (i.e., those with spin &gt; ½), with an emphasis on 35Cl SSNMR of chloride ions (Cl–) present in each MCC, as well as alkali metal SSNMR (7Li, 23Na, 39K, 87Rb, 133Cs). Additionally, comparisons of experimental and calculated 35Cl electric field gradient (EFG) tensors are presented as guiding metrics for structural validation, and to elucidate their relationships to molecular-level structures and crystallographic symmetry. In Chapter 2, five MCCs of the form NR4Cl:xUrea·yH2O (R = H, Et, n-Pr; x = 1, 2; y = 0, 2) were prepared to demonstrate the utility of 35Cl SSNMR for use in NMRX investigations. 35Cl SSNMR spectra reveal powder patterns that act as spectral fingerprints for each MCC, while also detecting residual educts not observed in corresponding PXRD patterns. DFT calculations on geometry-optimized structures yielded 35Cl EFG tensors in good agreement with experiment, except for NH4Cl:Urea; hence, ab initio molecular dynamics (aiMD) simulations were used to study the impact of molecular motions of NH4+ cations on the 35Cl EFG tensors, and their concomitant use for structural characterization. Chapter 3 explores accelerated aging (AA) reactions that produce four of the MCCs from Chapter 2, using in situ and ex situ 35Cl SSNMR and ex situ PXRD for monitoring. Different aspects of the AA reactions were investigated, such as mechanical activation (ball milling vs. gentle mixing), environmental conditions (temperature and humidity), sample packing and unpacking, and different reactant ratios. Comparisons of the AA reactions yielding NH4Cl:Urea and NEt4Cl:2Urea demonstrate that the induction times dramatically impact reaction rates. Reaction mixtures of NPr4Cl and urea in 1:2 and 1:3 ratios produced MCCs with very different AA rates, and revealed a series of transient species, offering insight into competitive kinetic and thermodynamic effects on AA reactions. In Chapter 4, two classes of MCCs of the forms MCl:xCA (CA = cyanuric acid; M = Li, Na, Rb, Cs; x = 1, 2) and MCl:xBA∙yH2O (BA = barbituric acid; x = 1, 2; y = 0, 2; M = Li, Na, K, Rb, Cs) were prepared with ball milling. Twelve MCCs were characterized using multinuclear SSNMR, including 35Cl, 13C, and alkali metal nuclides, as well as PXRD and SCXRD methods. Seven novel MCl:xBA∙yH2O MCCs were discovered, and new crystal structures are reported for five of these. Alkali metal SSNMR spectra aid in determining the number of distinct sites and rapidly detecting residual educts. Comparison of experimental and calculated 35Cl EFG tensors suggests they are influenced by both H⋯Cl– hydrogen bonds and electrostatic interactions involving alkali cations. Finally, Chapter 5, which combines many ideas from the preceding chapters, features three MCCs of the form MCl:Urea∙xH2O (M = Li, Na, Cs; x = 0, 1) that were prepared via ball milling and NMRX-guided Rietveld refinements to solve their crystal structures. 35Cl SSNMR was the most useful technique for their characterization, due to its inherent sensitivity to different H⋯Cl– hydrogen bonding configurations. 23Na MAS NMR allowed for the in situ monitoring of the autocatalytic degradation of NaCl:Urea∙H2O. All characterization data were used to inform the initial structures for Rietveld analysis, with final Rietveld structures subjected to DFT geometry optimizations, enabling exploration of relationships between the local hydrogen bonding environments of the chloride ions and NMR interaction tensors. It is anticipated that the synthetic methods herein will be used to generate a broad range of MCCs of increasing complexity, featuring different metal ions, simple organic molecules, and ratios of components. These highly efficient syntheses, in combination with the characterization protocols described herein, could be beneficial for the design of new quadrupolar NMRX techniques for validating, refining, and solving the crystal structures for a wide range of MCCs where conventional characterization methods fall short, perhaps even allowing for the prediction of hitherto unknown structures in tandem with modern crystal structure prediction methods.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 12, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Robert W. Schurko, Professor Directing Dissertation; Stephen Hill, University Representative; Susan E. Latturner, Committee Member; Robert Silvers, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022986">
      <topic>Chemistry</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Vojvodin_fsu_0071E_18220</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
