<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Exploration of the Effects of Primary and Secondary Trauma on Child Welfare Workers' Mental Health and Commitment to the Field</mods:title>
      <mods:nonSort>An</mods:nonSort>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart type="family">King</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Erin A. (Erin Albrecht)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dwilke">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Wilke</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Dina J.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lmcwey">
      <mods:namePart type="family">McWey</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Lenore M.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/stripodi">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Tripodi</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Stephen J.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no99033530">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Randolph</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Karen A.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Social Work</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (174 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>The field of child welfare continues to suffer due to high rates of worker turnover. The child welfare workforce plays a crucial role in promoting child well-being and preventing abuse and neglect. When workers leave their jobs, sometimes after only a few months, at-risk children are negatively impacted. Work-related trauma exposure of workers is an understudied area. This study revealed three categories of trauma workers experience as a part of their jobs. Analyses examined the relationship between type of trauma exposure and personal and work-related outcomes of child welfare workers in the state of Florida. This study examined workers' exposure to trauma from a stress-response framework. Conservation of resources theory and identity theory informed the conceptual model for this study. This model examined how different typologies of trauma influence workers' mental health and commitment to the field of child welfare. Mental health was examined as a potential mediator in the relationship between trauma and commitment to the field. A sample of child welfare workers who had been employed in the field for 18-months (n=657) responded to items relating to their experiences of client perpetrated violence, deaths or injuries on their caseloads, and secondary trauma. They also completed scales measuring their current levels of depression, anxiety, PTSD (at 18 months), and their overall commitment to the field of child welfare (measured at 2 years post-hire). T-tests, ANOVA analyses, and structural equation modeling (consisting of confirmatory factor analysis and path analysis) were used to determine the prevalence, severity, and effects of trauma exposure on workers. Three typologies of trauma emerged: primary trauma, caseload trauma, and secondary trauma. Threat emerged as the most reported form of primary trauma in this sample (78.4%), followed by non-physical violence (44.8%), and then assault (5.7%). Twenty-six percent (26%) of workers met the criteria for moderate to severe secondary trauma symptomatology. Relating to caseload trauma, 7.7% (n=49) of workers reported death of a child on their caseload due to maltreatment, 16.7% (n=106) reported the death of a child due to accident/injury, and 29.4% (n=187) reported the severe illness/injury of a child on their caseload. Moderate to severe levels of anxiety and PTSD were found in 4.3% and 3.7% of these child welfare workers. Depression levels for workers were higher, with 16.6% reporting moderate levels of depression. Structural equation modeling (SEM) analysis indicated that primary trauma had a small, but positive relationship with commitment to the field (B=.17, p&lt;.05). Caseload trauma predicted workers' levels of secondary trauma (B=.14, p&lt;.05), and secondary trauma had a strong, predictive relationship with worker mental health (B=.77, p&lt;.001). Each type of trauma contributed differentially to workers' personal and organizational outcome. These findings contribute important information about the prevalence and effects of different types of trauma child welfare workers face as a part of their job. Results of this study have implications for administrative practice, training, and intervention development in child welfare. Limitations of this study included participant attrition, a limited measurement period for mental health, and the use of dichotomous variables to measure primary and caseload trauma. Future research should focus on exploring these relationships between worker trauma exposure and personal/organization outcomes longitudinally and by using qualitative research methods to examine workers' experiences in more depth.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the College of Social Work in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Summer Semester 2019.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 24, 2019.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">child welfare workforce, client-perpetrated violence, mental health, secondary trauma, trauma exposure</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Dina J. Wilke, Professor Directing Dissertation; Lenore McWey, University Representative; Stephen J. Tripodi, Committee Member; Karen A. Randolph, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124049">
      <mods:topic>Social service</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2019_Summer_King_fsu_0071E_15332</identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Social Work</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2020-01-08T16:41:25.408-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
