<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Renewed Critical Pedagogy</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Rethinking Activism within Writing Program Administration</mods:subTitle>
      <mods:nonSort>A</mods:nonSort>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Lehn</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jeanette Louise</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n98010396">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Graban</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Tarez Samra</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2012007578">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Jones</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Tamara Bertrand</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2010050868">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Neal</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Michael R.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2015038714">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Lathan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Rhea Estelle</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1961-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of English</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (195 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>This dissertation is a qualitative study of activism within writing program administration though the lens of the term critical pedagogy. The study responds to calls in the field of rhetoric, composition, and writing studies to address inequalities and to forward social justice ends. This disciplinary desire can be evidenced in chairs' addresses at the flagship conference, The Conference on College Composition and Communication, in institutional mission statements and in the pedagogy of individual instructors. In the past, local efforts to respond to social justice have been classified under the term critical pedagogy. While the term critical pedagogy has fallen out of favor, I argue that the term still holds utility for conceiving of a contemporary response to progressive desires for teaching. The term critical pedagogy, often associated with Paulo Freire, a Chilean activist, is commonly associated with designing classroom practice. The term evolved into more frequent parlance in the 1960s and 1970s as institutional structures changed, and again in the 1990s, as issues of identity and culture were more centrally the focus of composition studies. One conception of critical pedagogy is that individual teachers can create social change through classroom practice. It is difficult to address global or systemic problems solely at the local level, and in reconceiving of critical pedagogy for contemporary exigencies, the need to theorize activism on a systemic level is salient. This dissertation study accounts for that critique of critical pedagogy by theorizing critical pedagogy from institutional and systemic angles utilizing a method called Critical Systems Theory (CST). To theorize critical pedagogy and activism from both individual and institutional angles simultaneously, this dissertation utilizes qualitative methods, chiefly interviews, chosen for their ability to reveal relationships between actors within the educational system. Ten writing program administrators from "research extensive" universities (Carnegie Classification D/RU-E) were interviewed about institutional contexts, activism, critical pedagogy, multiculturalism, and the treatment of race and racism within TA training. The research utilizes an ecological framework and is done for the purpose of institutional critique. Participants were recruited via e-mail and the "snowball" referral method. Interviews were conducted over Skype and transcripts of the interviews were coded for patterns. Interviewees were offered three levels of participation to allow for confidentiality: confidential participant (name and institution withheld); named participant (name and institution present); and collaborator (name and institution present with the option for collaborators to give feedback on data and results). Within the study, the writing program is conceived of as an entity within multiple ecologies and the results of this research reflect that by presenting the results in terms of "inner" and "outer" spaces. The inner spaces refer to aspects of the data pertaining to classroom pedagogy and the internal administration of writing program administration. The outer spaces refer to aspects of writing program administration connected to the institutional, external stakeholders and the discipline. Opportunities for administrative agency within writing programs or "points of leverage" as they are referred to in the dissertations included dialogue, the design of both curriculum and assignments and the mentoring of teaching assistants within graduate programs. Opportunities for administrative agency in outer spaces included outreach, positive collaboration and acting as a representative for writing studies outside of department spaces. Additionally, the study describes intersectional factors that modified writing program administrator agency including identities or philosophies, location, geography, and pre-existing exigencies that modified available resources. This data can be used for the purposes of describing the dynamic and situated positionality of a writing program administrator. Limitations of this study included the limitations of qualitative research related to the small sample size and the difficulty of creating findings from narrative data. Future research can be done in terms of replicating this study on a larger scale or looking more extensively into more detailed and specific aspects of social justice action within writing programs.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of English in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Summer Semester 2019.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 10, 2019.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">activism, composition, critical pedagogy, Institutional critique, rhetoric, writing program administration</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Tarez Samra Graban, Professor Directing Dissertation; Tamara Bertrand Jones, University Representative; Michael Neal, Committee Member; Rhea Lathan, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989">
      <mods:topic>Education</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2019_Summer_Lehn_fsu_0071E_15336</identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>English</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2020-01-08T16:41:25.408-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
