<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Fishing Alone No More? </title>
      <subTitle>A Study of Rural Dynamics and Evolution of a Community-Based Aquaculture Collaborative Network</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-0545-7758</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Shie</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Wen-Chi</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2001091993">
      <namePart type="family">Brower</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ralph S.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2012007578">
      <namePart type="family">Jones</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Tamara Bertrand</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n81065572">
      <namePart type="family">Berry</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Frances Stokes</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dberlan">
      <namePart type="family">Berlan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">David G. (David Gregory)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Reubin O' D. Askew School of Public Administration and Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (198 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>This is a study about the role, structure, and evolution of rural community collaborative networks and partnerships as well as a subsequent aquaculture policy network. The study uses ethnographic methods with long-term qualitative data to explore the formation and evolution trajectories of the aquaculture community collaborative network in a rural community context. In practical terms, this dissertation examines network evolution trajectories and how the power and resource imbalances in rural collaboration processes are influenced by different forms of social capital and the multiplicity of social ties in their dense rural networks. The focus of this research case – the rural community-campus collaborative networks and partnerships – was initiated by a community college's new satellite campus which they undertook without prior essential resources and knowledge. Rural communities are vulnerable to change because conditions such as scarce resources and weak infrastructure lead to high uncertainty and complexity for community development and innovation. Being isolated and marginalized from external resources, the challenges for increasing resource munificence make rural community collaborative networks and partnerships difficult to expand or strengthen. Therefore, rural community collaborative networks and partnerships are often unstable in their evolution processes. There are few studies that focus on network trajectory, formation, and evolution with an emphasis on community-centered collaborative networks built bottom up from diverse rural contexts. This study illustrated five stages of community collaborative network dynamics in rural aquaculture education and industry development within two coevolving network trajectories: one trajectory with primarily coherent interactions and another that was more conflicted. The conflicted trajectory pursued goals other than aquaculture development and emerged gradually, lagging the coherent trajectory by a few months. The extended network evolution trajectory framework in my analysis illustrates how complexity, uncertainty, and conflict generate networks that do not fit neatly into the ideal types suggested in the literature: goal-directed, purpose-oriented, and serendipitous. I have suggested that serendipity may take several forms, and I suggested four elements of serendipitous changes – stage, trajectory, policy/collaboration problems, network connectivity and disconnections – in network evolution that offer a conceptual contribution to our understanding of serendipitous trajectories. Also, I found that forms of social capital may be transformed. I have been able to illustrate social capital transformative processes in part because my six years of data among community participants reveal several of these transformations. That is, over time, individual ties that may initially operate as bridging social capital may become bonding social capital with repeated use; conversely, when individuals disassociate themselves from others with whom they previously maintained strong ties (Granovetter, 1973), it is possible for those bonding social capital structures to become bridging social capital. This dissertation also contributed a novel view of linking social capital that distinguishes between those links that connect between vertical elements within a community, as distinct from those linking social capital connections to hierarchically more powerful entities outside the community. I refer to these distinct forms as internal and external linking social capital. Since linking social capital is newer to the literature than bonding and bridging social capital, and there is a more limited body of research about it, this distinction is particularly significant for rural communities because they are often isolated from and marginalized from higher levels of government activity outside their community boundaries. In addition, because of the limitations and forms of rural data I had available, I illustrated the three types of social capital as interactions among individuals according to whether they were enacting bonding, bridging, or linking social capital. I argue that this is a more "active" approach that provides a methodological contribution for studying community social capital. Finally, this study also provides recommendations for future research and strategies for practitioners.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Askew School of Public Administration and Policy in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 2, 2021.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">Collaboration, Community, Network Evolution, Network Trajectory, Rural, Social Capital</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Ralph S. Brower, Professor Directing Dissertation; Tamara Bertrand Jones, University Representative; Frances S. Berry, Committee Member; David G. Berlan, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85108611">
      <topic>Public administration</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2021_Summer_Shie_fsu_0071E_16681</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Public Administration and Policy</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-01-31T17:03:20.741646-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
