<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Refining the Cycling Framework of Vanadium Isotopes in Marine Environments and the Future Application to Better Reconstruct the Ancient Marine Redox Variations</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-5481-0605</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Li</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Siqi</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jdowens">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Owens</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jeremy D.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/steinbck">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Steinbock</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Oliver</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mmookherjee">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Mookherjee</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Mainak</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/sayoung2">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Young</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Seth A.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (131 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Marine redox conditions are closely coupled with atmospheric oxygenation and essentially regulate the marine nutrient cycling (e.g., C, N, P, Fe, and S) in surficial processes, and marine life evolutions. Vast efforts have been invested, in the last decades, to reconstruct the geological marine redox perturbations, where the redox-sensitive elements, e.g., S, Mo, U, and Fe, including their sedimentary species and isotopic compositions, have been widely utilized to identify the strongly reducing conditions, i.e., anoxic conditions (oxygen- and H2S-absent water columns) and euxinic conditions (oxygen-absent yet with free H2S in the water columns). Recently, the V isotope system (50V and 51V) has emerged as a promising proxy to better constrain the previously underestimated low-oxygen environments in ancient oceans which can serve as the preceding stage of the widespread oceanic anoxia, essentially impacting the nutrient cycling pathways and casting oxygen-deprivation stress over the marine biological communities. However, research exploring the cycling of V isotopes in marine environments is still limited, thus, this dissertation research aims to: 1) better constrain the global variations of seawater V isotopic compositions (δ51V); and 2) the authigenic sedimentary δ51V values responding to different marine redox environments; hereafter, 3) V isotopes are applied to the relatively well-studied oceanic anoxic event 2 (OAE-2, ~ 94 million years ago), testifying the practicality of V isotopes to track the local and global marine redox fluctuations. The profiles of seawater V concentration ([V]) and isotopic composition were analyzed at ~40°S South Atlantic Ocean off the west African coast. The sampling profiles, spanning from ~ 5 m to ~ 4500 m, intersected nearly all the major water masses, thus experiencing different and complicated circulations. The results show relatively homogeneous seawater [V] and δ51V values in deep oceans below the euphotic zone (&gt; ~100 m), providing the most robust dataset that V behaves with conservative cycling in the deep oceans, excluding the more negative δ51V value in the Antarctic Bottom Water, which likely reflects regional influence from weathering input into the Antarctic continental margin. Such a negative shifting seems only local rather than extensive influence as suggested by the spatially consistent δ51V values of oxic sediments deposited in different ocean basins. On the other hand, local/regional processes such as the weathering inputs in near-coastal areas and severely restricted basins and the biological uptake of V in surface seawater can cause potential shiftings of the seawater δ51V values up to ~0.3‰. The pore fluid [V] values and the sedimentary metal element concentrations and δ51V values were studied in a setting of marine depositional environments along the California-Mexican oxygen minimum zone. The studied sites present major depositional variations in benthic redox conditions from oxic to anoxic and organic carbon burial rates varying between 0.08 8.4 mmol/(m2·day). It shows that the authigenic sedimentary δ51V signatures are primarily controlled by the benthic redox conditions, likely seeing the isotopic signature in the redox-controlling partition of vanadate and vanadyl species and subsequent scavenging processes, with more positive values documented in more reducing environments. The mineralogy of Mn and Fe oxides likely yields secondary impacts in oxic environments, with more negative authigenic sedimentary δ51V values observed in Mn oxide-rich sediments. Furthermore, profiles of the pore fluid [V] and the sedimentary elemental authigenesis indicate potential remobilization and redistribution of authigenic sedimentary V, which is mainly governed by the pore fluid redox gradients, whereas the invariant authigenic sedimentary δ51V values from surface sediments to depth at individual sites propose limited alterations of original signals by post-depositional diagenesis. Based on the fundamental framework of V cycling in modern marine environments, V isotopes were applied to three relatively well-studied sites documenting the OAE-2 event. At the Tarfaya Basin site and the tropical proto-North Atlantic Basin site, the authigenic sedimentary δ51V profiles present variations plotting in the anoxic-to-euxinic conditions, consistent with previous biogeochemical evidence. In contrast, the Demerara Rise site presents pronounced authigenic sedimentary δ51V variabilities, indicating wobbling benthic redox conditions between the low-oxygen conditions to the euxinic conditions. Especially, the negative δ51V perturbations pointing to more oxic benthic conditions coincide with the reappearances of the low-oxygen-tolerant benthic foraminifers. Such short-term variations to more oxic benthic conditions allowing for the proliferation of opportunistic benthic faunas are not tracked by previous geochemical proxies, owing to redox sensitivities and/or complicated burial mechanisms. Altogether, our research provided an improved cycling framework of V isotopes in marine environments, allowing for more explicit interpretations of ancient sedimentary δ51V records. Coupling with previous geochemical tools, this further allows for refining ancient temporospatial marine redox variabilities and associated nutrient cycling and biological perturbations.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">September 29, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jeremy D. Owens, Professor Directing Dissertation; Oliver Steinbock, University Representative; Mainak Mookherjee, Committee Member; Seth Young, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85054037">
      <mods:topic>Geology</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Li_fsu_0071E_18279</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-05-06T16:57:02.841686-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
