<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Applications of Liquid Chromatography-Tandem Mass Spectrometry for Measuring Hormones Secreted from Islets of Langerhans</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-3007-7984</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Donohue</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Matthew Joseph</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mroper">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Roper</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Michael Gabriel</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jfadool">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Fadool</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">James M.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nb2002004599">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Schlenoff</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Joseph B.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/yhu">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hu</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Yan-yan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (92 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>In this dissertation, liquid chromatography and solid phase extraction – mass spectrometry (LC and SPE-MS) techniques are applied for rapid quantitation of four glucose-regulating hormones secreted from human islets of Langerhans. The four species monitored throughout are the peptide hormones of somatostatin, C-peptide, insulin, and glucagon. All four hormones have well-documented roles in islet biology which make them optimal targets for analysis. LC and SPE-MS offers a powerful quantitative methodology capable of simultaneous, multiplexed measurements of islet-secreted species in response to glucose stimulation. LC and SPE steps are necessary for clean-up of raw biological samples prior to MS analysis but are time-consuming. This limitation reduces LC and SPE-MS applicability for experiments monitoring the dynamic changes in biological systems. Integration of rapid LC or SPE steps using higher flow rates, gradient separations, or short columns enable faster measurement times. Detection sensitivity is often affected by the decreased analysis time but triple quadrupole MS instrumentation operating in multiple reaction monitoring mode has been shown to match immunoassay sensitivity at higher flow rates. Rapid separation steps and MRM MS were therefore employed in our attempts to develop a fully automated, online LC or SPE-MS assay capable of multiplexed detection of glucose-regulating hormones secreted from islets of Langerhans. The second chapter of the dissertation describes the development of an LC-MS method capable of quantitation of somatostatin, C – peptide, insulin, and glucagon secretion from human islet populations. For rapid analysis, a 5 min separation was achieved with a 2.1 × 30 mm (i.d. x length) C18 column with 2.7 μm diameter core shell particles. A sacrificial protein hydrolysate was used with the sample. The hydrolysate was found to improve signal magnitude, repeatability, and to reduce carryover between runs. At optimized gradient conditions, the gradient run time was 4.55 min which produced an average peak width of 0.3 min, a minimum resolution of 1.2, and a peak capacity of 20. As a proof of concept, the method was used to measure secretions from static incubations of human islets. Insulin and C-peptide were quantified and matched well with literature values, but somatostatin and glucagon responses were not quantifiable, as they were secreted in lower amounts and fell below the calibrated range. The third chapter of the dissertation features the integration of a microfluidic device as well as the switch from LC-MS to SPE-MS. Microfluidic devices enable improved analysis of glucose-regulating hormones due to improved recovery and minimal analyte dilution. SPE was chosen to further increase the speed of analysis. Analysis was performed with a 1 x 8 mm (I.D. x length) SPE cartridge that contained C8 stationary phase particles with a 5 µL bed for analyte extraction. Method development with SPE was performed by means of response surface methodology (RSM) to identify a set of optimal load and elution conditions capable of enhanced responses for each of the analytes and internal standards in solution. Analysis of SPE-MS sensitivity did not match limits of the LC-MS method for all peptides (0.5 nM for LC, 0.5 nM for C-peptide and somatostatin on SPE, 2 nM for insulin and glucagon) but was still expected to encompass the concentration of peptides in secreted fractions. Dynamic glucose incubation of 30-35 islets was done with the microfluidic device and fractions were collected for SPE-MS analysis. Insulin was matched well with literature reported values for 1 of the batches analyzed. C-peptide and glucagon responded to the glucose stimulants outside of the quantifiable range. The fourth chapter describes the integration and automation of the SPE-MS assay into an online microfluidic system. The system uses a 10-port HPLC valve to house multiple sample loops which will decrease sample loss to waste during fraction collection. Experiments performed with standards to evaluate the reproducibility of subsequent injections using the system as well as an evaluation of system dynamics are shown in this chapter. These experiments confirmed system capabilities to produce precise responses and respond to a stimulus change faster than was shown when the device was used offline.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">November 10, 2021.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Michael G. Roper, Professor Directing Dissertation; James M. Fadool, University Representative; Joseph B. Schlenoff, Committee Member; Yan-Yan Hu, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023011">
      <mods:topic>Chemistry, Analytic</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">2021_Fall_Donohue_fsu_0071E_16896</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-05-23T16:09:53.352975-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
