<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Modernist Mending of the Mind-Body Split? </mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Historicizing the Ideals of Musicality and Embodiment in the Eurhythmics of Émile Jaques-Dalcroze</mods:subTitle>
      <mods:nonSort>A</mods:nonSort>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-4546-2693</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Bishop</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Caroline</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2003072097">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Von Glahn</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Denise</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1950-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85275076">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Corrigan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">John</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1952-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88679431">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Brewer</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Charles E. (Charles Everett)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88291333">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Broyles</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Michael</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1939-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Music</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Music</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (309 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Swiss composer, educator, and creator of eurhythmics Émile Jaques-Dalcroze (1865-1950) oriented his pedagogical philosophy around the concept of unifying the mind-body split, the ontology that is often attributed to René Descartes and Western traditions of thought. In this dissertation I consider how Jaques-Dalcroze sought to instrumentalize music and musicality toward mind-body unity and how contemporary Dalcroze Eurhythmics practice remains committed to giving students the sense of returning to their bodies and becoming whole, integrated selves, and in the process finding joy and interconnectedness. The term "eurhythmics," not a coinage of Jaques-Dalcroze himself, uses the Greek prefix eu- to signify the goodness, health, and ease that early practitioners observed to be its benefits. The study draws upon analyses and histories of modernism from the fields of literature, cultural geography, and musicology to place eurhythmics within the discourse of modernism in a way that previous scholarship has not yet done. Within musicology, the past thirty years or so have witnessed a fruition of scholarship on embodiment. At the outset of this movement to include the body more explicitly and more thoughtfully in scholarly analyses of music, such work represented a necessary counterbalance to existing paradigms. Now that embodiment is a well-developed terrain in the discipline, it is possible to position Jaques-Dalcroze, a figure whose work centralizes the body, in this musicological tradition and to think about what a history of his eurhythmics can add to our understanding of musical modernism. It is instructive to think of Jaques-Dalcroze as a modernist artist both because of the role he assigned to music and more specifically because of his preoccupation with rhythm. Rhythm was a topic of great interest to philosophers, physicians, painters, and acousticians at the turn of the twentieth century in Europe and America; in fact, it would be difficult to name a field in which rhythm did not garner excitement. Influenced by his rhythm-obsessed milieu and by German Idealism, Jaques-Dalcroze conceived of music as transcendent, and though eurhythmics is ostensibly about the mind-body unification that he described in his own writings, he also frequently expressed a desire for music to help transcend the trappings of physicality. He often wrote about "absolute" music as the highest form of music. I argue that this is because, paradoxically, he feared the sensuality of the body and the diversity of human bodily forms. The major critique that runs throughout the dissertation is thus that Jaques-Dalcroze's claim for eurhythmics as a restorative force in the face of fin-de siècle decadence and later after the destruction of the First World War was not equitably conceived. Rather, it was ineluctably marred by his commitment to sexist, racialist, and ethnonationalist views. He was a believer in the utopia and universality of rhythmic movement at the same time as he professed anti-Semitic and anti-Black views. Jaques-Dalcroze's career trajectory is telling as to how he came to espouse his discriminatory views. He framed his experience of non-Western musics in French-colonized Algiers as the impetus to centralizing rhythm in his pedagogy. His accounts of this time of inspiration are marked by the anti-Black racialized stereotyping that was endemic to the colonizer perspective within many colonialist contexts. I argue that histories of eurhythmics must no longer recapitulate the existing pattern in scholarship that for the most part overlooks the racialism embedded in Jaques-Dalcroze's recollections of the creative stimulus he found abroad. His later involvement with German industrialists and architects enabled him to play out an idea of a eurhythmic utopia at Hellerau, near Dresden. It is evident that Jaques-Dalcroze associated himself with staunch anti-Semites there, but it is likely that his own anti-Semitism predated those associations. By examining textual evidence supplemented with iconography, I reconstruct a history of eurhythmics as it existed under the auspices of its creator. I focus on the early period of this history, from the 1880s to about 1930, and on continental European settings, even as eurhythmics found enthusiastic support in England and America by 1920. My delimitations allow me to conclude that Jaques-Dalcroze was a product of a period of intense ethnonationalist sentiment, and while he might be dismissed by some as merely a product of his time, I maintain that historical relativism should not excuse his racist biases. When we discuss Jaques-Dalcroze's premise of mind-body unity today, we should account for his intent to include only certain groups of people in this utopian construction.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the College of Music in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 13, 2022.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Denise Von Glahn, Professor Directing Dissertation; John Corrigan, University Representative; Charles E. Brewer, Committee Member; Michael Broyles, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003673">
      <mods:topic>Music</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>History and criticism</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85088796">
      <mods:topic>Music</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Instruction and study</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Summer 2022_Bishop_fsu_0071E_17121</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Music</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-01-27T10:52:08.836275-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
