<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Neoliberal Globalization and Mediated Sport Fandom</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>A Study of Chinese Distant Fans</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-0887-5402</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Chen</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Zhenyan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2011019943">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Newman</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Joshua I.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1976-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/deccles">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Eccles</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">David W.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2008063392">
      <mods:namePart type="family">James</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jeffrey D. (Jeffrey Dalton)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jdu3">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Du</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">James</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Education</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Sport Management</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (249 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>The intensified process of globalization has reconfigured the formation and composition of sport fandom, which was—for a long period of time throughout history—rooted in local social practices and identities. With advances in telecommunication technology, today, many people follow, support, and identify with sport teams at a distance; they become 'distant sport fans.' In this project, I seek to understand the formation of distant sport fandom. Research pertaining to sport fandom has been generally conducted from two decoupled perspectives, yet complicit in studying local sport fans. Sport marketing scholars have focused on the psychological connection between fans and a sport team. While meaningfully theorizing the formation of fan's identification towards a sport team, this approach can be bolstered by accounting for some important nuances that are situated in the context of sport fandom. Conversely, researchers of sport sociology have recognized the context that has made the contemporary fan identity a consumer identity in nature. However, many sociologists have not studied how, at the individual level, a fan identity is formed. This project marks an attempt to integrate these different fields of inquiry in presenting a more complex understanding of sport fandom and the formation of fan identity in the age of neoliberal globalization. Specifically, drawing upon theoretical perspectives that seek to explore the historically-specific conjunctures of what is often referred to as the 'neoliberal condition,' I aim to understand how structural forces shape the processes through which distant fan identities are formed. Upon reviewing the relevant literature, I believe mediation is an important concept for us to deconstruct and understand how our daily experiences, ways of perceiving, and social relations are deeply embedded within the advanced capitalist mode of production as we continue living our lives in a mass-mediated world or the "spectacle" in Guy Debord's (2014) words. In this project, I chose to focus on the case of Chinese distant soccer fans. By interviewing some Chinese distant fans of Bayern Munich within a certain local context, such an inquiry allowed me to highlight the importance of context in studying sport fandom, while also taking an individual's psychological connection to a distant sport team into consideration. Based on the online semi-structured interviews conducted, I discovered that, since distant fans rely on contextualized media outlets as their major access to a foreign sport team, they are likely to form their connection to a distant team based on some unique team objects, differing from the previously studied local fans. Sport fandom is contextualized in a particular local setting when distant fans' experiences with a team are mediated by global (the team itself and the foreign sponsors of a team) and local mediators (the domestic sponsors of a team, fans' social relations, streaming companies within a local context, and the local government) across the global-local conjunctures. To further complicate the scenario, fans' experiences with a team can also be mediated by the interplay between global and local mediation, leading to their unique meaning-making of a distant sport team within a certain local context. For instance, some Chinese distant fans believed that their favorite soccer team should stay away from the political sphere so that the team would not be banned by the Chinese government; this meaning-making interestingly differs from how local fans usually make sense of a sport team now in the west. The profound schematics of mediation then lead us to consider the extent to which structural forces can shape the ways through which distant fandom is formed in the contemporary era of neoliberalization. My project implicates that the expansion of the global soccer industry and China's neoliberalization may constitute the growth of distant fandom in the context of China. Through new ways of media production, soccer culture has been disseminated primarily for the purpose of establishing a sport consumer's attachment to a team. In the context of China, the global expansion of the soccer industry leads to the formation of new fan communities with some Chinese characteristics. Distant fandom can also be regarded as a neoliberal project that has been created alongside China's economic opening-up. By identifying with a distant sport team, distant fans in China not only respond to but also carry forth the aforementioned structural forces, perpetuating and reproducing the further global and local progression of neoliberalization. In these ways, I explicated how individuals become distant spectators and how that process of identification might lead to different perceptions, intentions, and identities from the previously researched local fans.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Sport Management in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">May 24, 2022.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Joshua I. Newman, Professor Directing Dissertation; David W. Eccles, University Representative; Jeffrey D. James, Committee Member; James Du, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126896">
      <mods:topic>Sports administration</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Summer 2022_Chen_fsu_0071E_17354</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Sport Management</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-01-27T10:52:08.836275-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
