<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Applications of Liquid Chromatography Tandem Mass Spectrometry for the Analysis of Complex Mixtures</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-2411-6238</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Popovic</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Zeljka</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n77017670">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Marshall</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Alan G. (Alan George)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1944-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/fzhu">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Zhu</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Fanxiu</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mroper">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Roper</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Michael Gabriel</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="viaf"
              authorityURI="http://viaf.org/viaf/"
              valueURI="http://viaf.org/viaf/35658877">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Bleiholder</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Christian</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (97 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>From inside our bodies to the environment we live in, there are a wide variety of unknown compounds that have been difficult to identify and characterize through current methods. We aim to study these compounds by liquid chromatography (LC) high-resolution tandem mass spectrometry (MS/MS). LC-MS/MS has become the gold standard for the analysis of complex mixtures due to its capabilities to decrease spectral overlap and high mass measurement accuracy. Proteins are of particular interest biologically because they give insight into various diseases and the health of our biological processes. Analysis of these proteins is hindered by the current methods implemented in laboratories due to the size and characteristics of these compounds and their natural behavior outside of biological systems. Just as import as what is inside the human body is what is in the environment, specifically the Earth's oceans. Just like proteins in the body, the Earth's oceans give us a picture into the health of the environment. We know that human activity has severally impacted our atmosphere and water sources. We aim to understand the connections with pollution and the effects it has on oceans, a major water source on Earth. First a broad overview of LC-MS/MS is presented in Chapter 1. The first section discusses the MS instrumentation used for the studies in the following chapters, the 14- and 21-Tesla Fourier Transform Ion Cyclotron Mass Spectrometer (14- and 21-T FT ICR MS). The custom-built system is designed to produce the highest resolution data for compound identification and structural information. Our facilities are also equipped with various liquid chromatography (LC) systems that are used to separate mixtures and decrease sample complexity. Lastly, a brief introduction to various complex mixtures analyzed by LC-MS. The chapters that follow cover the specific studies performed with the knowledge of LC-FT ICR-MS and compound identifications. Chapter 2 discusses a study into the benefits and limitations on the application of isotopic depletion for cultured proteins. Isotopic depletion is a method used to deplete compounds of various heavy isotopes of elements present, most commonly carbon, nitrogen, hydrogen, oxygen, and sulfur. Heavy isotopes effect MS experiments in multiple ways which are investigated in the study for proteins derived from multiple cell lines (E. coli and C. elegan). This work is novel in the application and analysis of isotopically depleted C. elegans proteins The methods used for the biological applications can be applied to the analysis of marine samples which is discussed in Chapters 3 and 4. Chapter 3 investigates the composition of sinking particles in the California Coastal Current, specifically metabolites. Sinking particles play a role in the regulation of biological processes in the water column but additionally have shown to regulate greenhouse emissions. We take an even deeper look with analysis of marine sediments to see how far pollutants travel down the water column and are stored at the bottom of the ocean, in Chapter 4. Marine sediment samples were collected from the Oregon continental shelf at established sample stations. The analysis of these environmental samples by LC-MS/MS is still in the developmental phase. Our work aims to develop novel LC-MS/MS methods that can give a fuller picture into environmental impacts of pollution. The overall goal is to expand the capabilities of LC-MS/MS experiments to complex mixtures. LC-MS/MS shows its true capabilities and potential in the experiments discussed here. From 300 Da to 40 kDa in size, LC-MS/MS can efficiently analyze a wide dynamic range of compounds which is critical to broad applicability. With this work, future experiments can analyze and identify a wide range of compounds by high-throughput LC-MS/MS analysis.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 23, 2022.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Liquid Chromatographygraphy, Mass Spectrometry, Metabolomics, Proteomics</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Alan G. Marshall, Professor Directing Dissertation; Fanxiu Zhu, University Representative; Michael G. Roper, Committee Member; Christian Bleiholder, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023011">
      <mods:topic>Chemistry, Analytic</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Summer 2022_Popovic_fsu_0071E_17322</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-01-27T10:52:08.836275-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
