<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Alternative Cartographies</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Reflection(s) for the Complexities of Writing and Sustainability</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Thomsen</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jessica Renee</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2001108549">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Fleckenstein</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kristie S.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2008031674">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kearns</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Stephen</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1979-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n98010396">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Graban</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Tarez Samra</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jfiscus">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Fiscus-Cannaday</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jaclyn</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/sjm10d">
      <mods:namePart type="family">McElroy</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Stephen J.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n91108860">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Yancey</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kathleen Blake</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1950-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of English</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (274 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>In an increasingly threatening and threatened world—with ongoing climate crises, rampant social injustices, ecological devastation, and the related consequences of language use—writing and living sustainably are of vital importance (Dobrin and Weisser; Lynch; Owens). The exigence for this dissertation is this double sustainability, or the intertwining of writing and living for the survival and flourishing of socially just societies and healthy ecosystems. This project begins with reflection, with a space for contemplation in the woods, and with the thinking, doing, and composing of spinning wool and knitting cloth alongside possibilities for sustainability. Weaving together rational inquiry with material and affective resonances, this project considers writing and living as mutually dependent across the complexities of social and ecological dimensions. Reflection, a concept and practice woven across both writing and living, is the focus of this inquiry, and it serves as an important agent and engagement for ensuring joint-prospering for double sustainability. Reflection, as a practice in writing studies (Yancey), has often been pursued as a practice in rationality, but double sustainability calls for increasing attention to alterity and materiality. Thus, the goal of this project is to explore—to map and re-map—the cartographies of reflection to determine how it might more fully serve the increasingly complex demands of double sustainability. To that end, this project first addresses the typical framework of reflection in writing studies and then maps two possible alterative frameworks for reflection. A consideration of multiple frameworks is sensitive to the limitations of each, while also drawing on their strengths, and offers a transformation of these three frameworks toward a response-able reflection. This (re)mapping project, thus, begins with a rational framework for reflection, common in writing studies, which emphasizes consequences, problem solving, and metacognition, supporting movement toward coherence that serves double sustainability. However, rationality also tends to reinforce dualisms—of mind and body, human and nonhuman, nature and culture (Boyle; Price)—which truncates the potential for rational reflection to serve the complexities of social-ecological concerns of writing and living sustainably. An alternative framework for reflection, based on decoloniality, calls into question the dualisms of a rational framework, unveiling the continued repercussions of coloniality, which are supported by a Western rationality that universalizes and, simultaneously, obscures difference (García and Baca; Mignolo). As an alternative, decolonial reflection affirms difference through pluriversality by inhabiting contradictions, uncovering power dynamics, and supporting localization, but it also risks perpetuating the macronarrative it seeks to subvert, including the totalization of certain marginalized perspectives and minor traditions. While a decolonial framework emphasizes difference between agents, a new material framework for reflection, as another alternative, picks up a minor tradition of Western thought and emphasizes the process of differing that occurs across agents (Coole and Frost; Dolphijn and van der Tuin; Micciche). Instead of perpetuating the mind-matter dualism that persists in a rational framework, a new material reflection functions as a material-discursive apparatus that arises from intra-action and co-constitution and participates in further cycles of intra-activity (Barad; Syverson). However, such a reflection de-emphasizes individual responsibility, a strength of a rational framework, opening a question regarding its service of double sustainability. Rather than prioritize or synthesize frameworks, this dissertation moves toward a transformation of key elements from all three frameworks, spinning out the potentialities of their co-shaping of each other, in order for reflection to serve, as fully as possible, the complexities of writing and living sustainably. Such a transformed framework for reflection may be termed response-able (Barad; Haraway), an attempt to account for strengths across all three frameworks—rational, decolonial, new material—while also redressing some of the limitations identified within each of the frameworks. Through an articulation of iridescence, resilience, and multiple scales, a response-able reflection offers possibilities for implementing and enacting reflective practices toward more sustainable futures in writing, pedagogy, and living. The project comes full circle, back to the woods, considering the nuances of organic engagements, the generativity of uncertainty, and the renewed potential of reflection for double sustainability. By (re)mapping and offering a response-able framework for reflection, this project has implications for how reflection is studied in and beyond the writing classroom and how conversations surrounding sustainable initiatives might be bolstered by attention to reflection for the inextricable practices of writing and living.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of English in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 30, 2021.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">decoloniality, new materialisms, rationality, reflection, sustainability, writing</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Kristie S. Fleckenstein, Professor Directing Dissertation; Stephen Kearns, University Representative; Tarez Samra Graban, Committee Member; Jaclyn Fiscus-Cannaday, Committee Member; Stephen J. McElroy, Committee Member; Kathleen Blake Yancey, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113628">
      <mods:topic>Rhetoric</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">2021_Summer_Thomsen_fsu_0071E_16635</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>English</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-01-31T17:03:20.741646-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
