<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Female Student-Athlete Leadership, Mentorship, and the Transition to the Post-Collegiate Labor Force</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0005-8370-0321</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Beck</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Courtney Ann</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2004110130">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Giardina</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Michael D.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1976-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/deccles">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Eccles</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">David W.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kamy">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kim</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Amy C. H. (Amy Chan Hyung)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/hxue2">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Xue</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Hanhan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Sport Management</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (170 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>This past year (2022) marked the 50th Anniversary of Title IX of the 1972 Education Amendments, which prohibits sex-based discrimination in any school or any other education program that receives federal funding (Hextrum and Sethi, 2022). This federal anti-discrimination law has had a particular impact on sport, directly leading to an increased amount of participation in sport by girls and women, thus showcasing much talent from female athletes. Since the enactment of Title IX, women have come a long way in sport, however, there is progress still left to be witnessed for women (Acosta and Carpenter, 2009). Female athletes are gaining attention not just from fans and marketers, but venture capitalists are pouring their financial efforts into women's sports (Strauss and Hensley-Clancy, 2021). Given the heightened focus on female athletes especially-whether in media coverage, endorsements (for professionals) or Name-Image-Likeness (NIL; for collegiate) sponsorships, discourses of empowerment, and the promotion of women as leaders in the workforce more generally- it is critical to explore the preparation and development of leadership skills that female student-athletes are receiving during their collegiate career. There is a general acknowledgement in the literature on leadership concerning an underrepresentation of women in leadership positions, globally (Evans and Pfister, 2021). It is important to understand what female student-athletes' needs and desires are while still in college and how a university can invest in women to meet these needs through resource accessibility. Investigating at the collegiate level is imperative because education and opportunities available for the development of essential leadership skills can begin earlier for female student-athletes before they reach the workforce. This could potentially increase the number of women set to take on leadership positions in the industry of sport. As such, in this dissertation the focus is to understand current and former DI female student-athletes' perspectives on leadership development, mentorship opportunities, and preparation for the post-collegiate labor force. This study encompassed five research questions: RQ1: What are the perceived professional needs of current DI female student-athletes which could allow for the attainment of success in leadership roles in the workforce? RQ2: What are the professional needs identified from former DI female student-athletes which could equip current student-athletes allowing for the attainment of success in leadership roles in the workforce? RQ3: How do DI female student-athletes experience types of leadership and mentorship opportunities at the university level? RQ4: What types of leadership and mentorship opportunities do DI female student-athletes seek to obtain? RQ5: What types of leadership/mentorship experiences do former DI female student-athletes believe would help a current female student-athlete prepare for the workforce? Using thematic analysis (Braun &amp; Clarke, 2006), I identified themes from interviews of both current and former DI female student-athletes concerning their experiences with leadership training, mentorship they received, and preparation for the post-collegiate labor force. Key findings and summarized themes involve mentorship, student-development, communication, community, and leadership skills development. The need to focus on effective communication skill development was highlighted throughout this study. Participants explained the importance of entailing communication skills to be of significance for a leader to possess. Communication skills were also understood to be of importance to assist others in need, as well as function effectively in the workforce. Potential implications and recommendations for future research are identified that involve specific direction of leadership development and mentorship to be offered at the collegiate level to ensure effective preparation is present for DI female student-athletes concerning the post-collegiate labor force.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Sport Management in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">October 19, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Michael D. Giardina, Professor Directing Dissertation; David Eccles, University Representative; Amy Kim, Committee Member; Hanhan Xue, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126896">
      <mods:topic>Sports administration</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Beck_fsu_0071E_18307</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Sport Management</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-05-06T16:57:02.841686-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
