<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Audition Agendum</title>
      <subTitle>Analyzing the Development, Procedure, and Repertoire of Orchestral Oboe Auditions</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0009-6415-9209</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Prokop-Seaton</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Noel</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n90621988">
      <namePart type="family">Ohlsson</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Eric Paul</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1952-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing treatise</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2013006835">
      <namePart type="family">Eyerly</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sarah</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2002107071">
      <namePart type="family">Keesecker</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jeff</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kmclaughlin">
      <namePart type="family">Large</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Karen McLaughlin</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Music</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Music</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Although the United States had a rich musical culture prior to the 19th century, the first permanent symphony orchestras were not formed until the mid-1800's when an influx of German immigrants prompted the establishment of ensembles and festivals in cities across the country. Concurrently, the United States shifted from individual entrepreneurialism to corporate ideals. World War I further impacted the sound of American orchestras as repertoire shifted from largely Austro-German to French, Russian, and American compositions. Additionally, technological advancements such as the radio and television increased the symphony orchestra's popularity. These same advancements brought about new genres of music, and in the 1970s, the symphony orchestra's popularity saw a decline. Today, orchestras can still be found throughout the United States, with larger ensembles in more densely populated areas such as Boston, New York, Philadelphia, Chicago, and Los Angeles. Musicians are typically appointed to these orchestras through a lengthy audition process. Prior to any demonstration of skill, candidates are often required to submit materials such as a resume, references, or even a prescreen recording. Only after the submissions are reviewed will a musician be invited to the live audition. Larger orchestras will often use multiple rounds of playing, sometimes over several days, to reduce the plentiful number of applicants. Many auditions are also blind or screened, meaning the panel of judges are unable to see the players in an effort to reduce biases or favoritism towards different genders, minorities, or person. When the day of the audition begins, each musician is asked to play a series of short excerpts from a predetermined list distributed prior to the audition, which consists of sections from famous symphonies, solos, and/or chamber works. Musicians will spend weeks, if not months, preparing hours of repertoire for a 10 or 15 minutes time slot in front of the judges. Every oboist studies a list of "standard excerpts" which consists of those pieces most often found on auditions lists. However, there is little to no research regarding the origin of these lists. In the forward to his book, Orchestra Excerpts for Oboe, John Ferrillo discusses his experiences as an auditionee, taking 23 orchestral auditions before being offered a job. Although not discussed outright, it is safe to assume he compiled this list based on his plethora of experiences. There is, however, no literature regarding exactly how orchestras compile these lists of excerpts, yet many of them contain the same materials. Furthermore, auditions today will often specify the solo work as Mozart's Oboe Concerto in C Major, K. 314. This concerto, while most-likely written in 1777, was lost for almost 150 years. It was only discovered in 1920 by Bernhard Paumgartner, who then published a version in 1948 based on the discovered manuscript. This indicates that there is over a century worth of oboists in professional orchestra positions who never played the Mozart concerto. This modern system developed as a result of different social, political, and economic conditions. The purpose of this project is to identify the development of audition repertoire, etiquette, and protocols through a variety of sources, including previous audition announcements, historic and current news articles, interviews, and publications, to formulate a coherent idea of how auditions worked prior to the modern 21st century system. It is meant to be a valuable resource for undergraduates or those entering the audition circuit by identifying standard procedures and how they are effected by current events.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Treatise submitted to the College of Music in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Music.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 6, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Audition, Oboe, Orchestra</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Eric Ohlsson, Professor Directing Treatise; Sarah Eyerly, University Representative; Jeffrey Keesecker, Committee Member; Karen Large, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85099818">
      <topic>Performing arts</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">ProkopSeaton_fsu_0071E_17871</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Music</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Music</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
