<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Healthcare Stereotype Threat and LGBT Well-Being across the Life Course</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-7944-949X</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Saunders</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Russell Kyle</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/aburdette">
      <namePart type="family">Burdette</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Amy M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2006097242">
      <namePart type="family">Carr</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Dawn C.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2013118586">
      <namePart type="family">Boot</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Walter Richard</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/phoman">
      <namePart type="family">Homan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Patricia A.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2005111038">
      <namePart type="family">Taylor</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Miles G.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1976-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Sociology</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (104 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Sexual and gender minorities (i.e., gay men, lesbians, bisexuals, trans people) (SGMs) have experienced both social and legal progressive change over the last 50 years. However, this group still reports worse health outcomes and healthcare experiences, compared to heterosexuals (Fingerhut and Abdou 2017; Fredriksen-Goldsen et al. 2013). An innovative survey instrument that applies stereotype threat to the healthcare setting (e.g., healthcare stereotype threat, HCST) offers a new avenue to detail these disparities and uncover potential means of mitigation. Stereotype threat is the fear of confirming negative stereotypes about one's social group (Steele and Aronson 1996). HCST expands the construct to also include the fear of being negatively judged, evaluated, or diagnosed because of one's SGM status (Abdou and Fingerhut 2014). Work on HCST shows it has significant effects for sexual minorities' well-being (Fingerhut et al. 2021) and variations exist across age (Abdou et al. 2016). However, previous work is limited in several aspects. First, it is unknown how and if HCST retains its significant adverse effect on well-being while considering more established health factors such as everyday discrimination and experiencing stigma. Second, the extant literature currently treats SGMs as a monolith by ignoring how HCST effects can differ across SGM groups and across birth cohorts. Third, there is currently no literature that details how HCST is associated with the well-being of trans people. Guided by previous literature, this dissertation investigates three main research questions to address these gaps: (1) How does the inclusion of discrimination and stigma influence HCST's association on well-being?; (2) How does the effect of HCST on well-being vary across SGM groups?; (3) What moderating effects does birth cohort have on the association between HCST and well-being. To explore these questions, I used two national probability datasets that I harmonized: Generations and Transpop. Both of these dataset are the first of their kind to have national probability samples focusing on SGM status. These data are also the first of their kind that capture representative groups of SGMs across three birth cohorts: young (18 to 27 years old), middle-aged (32 to 43 years old), and older (50-60 years old). Results from Study #1 showed evidence that HCST is a unique health factor and that its effects significantly vary across SGM groups. Examining how HCST's association performed with the inclusion of everyday discrimination and stigma shows that HCST retains a significant association on self-rated health and psychological distress, which supports that HCST is a unique, viable, and useful tool to understand health disparities SGMs experience. Second, Study #1 shows how trans people tended to report significantly worse outcomes when HCST was high compared to gay men reporting the same level. This result shows the importance of including trans people in future analyses and examining inter-group differences. Results from Study #2 highlighted variations of HCST effects on well-being across birth cohorts and further highlighted a heightened plight trans people face. Standardized effects of HCST on self-rated health show worse effects for older lesbians and older bisexuals while the effect is similar for young and older gay men. Middle-aged trans people's self-rated health suffered significantly more so than young trans people's. HCST emerged to hold a more severe effect on the psychological distress of the older cohort as their distress were significantly higher than their younger counterparts, regardless of SGM group. This latter trend also emerged for trans people compared to gay men in the young and middle-age cohorts for self-rated health and for the young and older cohorts for psychological distress. In these cases, trans people reported worse outcomes than gay men when both groups were reporting the same level of HCST. This dissertation contributes to scholarship in many ways such as using two nationally-probability samples of SGMs in the US, exploring differences within the SGM groups, and including transgender people. And, known to this author, the first cohort differences tests of HCST on well-being for SGMs. The dissertation breaks new ground also in testing how HCST as a measure performs compared to more established health factors, which highlights a new avenue in studying health disparities. Finally, these results have several implications for informing future work on health disparities, beyond SGMs, and with informing interventions and policy change to mitigate this process.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Sociology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">November 14, 2022.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Cohort Differences, Healthcare Stereotype Threat, LGBTQ, Psychological Distress, Self-rated Health</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Amy Burdette, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Dawn C. Carr, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Walter Boot, University Representative; Patricia Homan, Committee Member; Miles Taylor, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124200">
      <topic>Sociology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004003385">
      <topic>Sexual minorities</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Saunders_fsu_0071E_17579</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Sociology</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
