<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Effects of Digital Audio and Video Quality on Collegiate Music Students' Ratings of Vocalists</title>
      <nonSort>The</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4734-4495</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Sullivan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Corey</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jgeringer">
      <namePart type="family">Geringer</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">John M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kadams6">
      <namePart type="family">Adams</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kari</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2002093654">
      <namePart type="family">Okerlund</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">David</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mjh09h">
      <namePart type="family">Hanawalt</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michael</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dgspringer">
      <namePart type="family">Springer</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">D. Gregory  (Douglas Gregory)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Music</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Music</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >The purpose of this study was to determine whether differences in digital audio and video quality impact collegiate music majors' ratings of a solo vocalist's performance. With this purpose in mind, I developed the following research questions: 1) Do instrumental and vocal collegiate music students perceive differences in tone quality of a vocalist's performance encoded at high and low audio and video qualities? 2) Do instrumental and vocal collegiate music students perceive differences in technique of a vocalist's performance encoded at high and low audio and video qualities? 3) Do instrumental and vocal collegiate music students perceive differences in musicality of a vocalist's performance encoded at high and low audio and video qualities? 4) To what extent are collegiate music students aware of differences in audio and video quality when rating a vocalist's performance? I made a stimulus recording of a vocalist and pianist performing four verses of Cecil J. Sharp's arrangement of The Holly and The Ivy. These four verses were then encoded at two video qualities (1080p resolution and 144p resolution) and two audio qualities (48 kHz sample rate with 24 bits of depth and 8kHz sample rate with 8 bits of depth) for a total of four possible video combinations. Participants (N = 93) watched each of the four video clips and rated the participant's tone quality, technique, and musicality in each condition. After viewing the stimulus videos and making ratings, participants then answered the free-response question "What factors influenced your ratings?" After performing statistical analyses, I found significant main effects for audio quality in all three rating categories. Participants rated the vocalist's tone quality, technique, and musicality higher in the high audio quality conditions than in the low audio quality conditions. I also found significant main effects for participants' self-identified primary instrument in two of the rating categories, with instrumentalists (n = 35) rating the vocalist's tone and technique higher overall than vocalists (n = 58) did. Additionally, there were two interactions involving participants' ratings of the vocalist's tone: an audio quality by primary instrument interaction and an audio quality by video quality by viewing order interaction. Instrumentalists rated tone quality higher in the high audio quality condition and lower in the low audio quality condition than vocalists did. In the three-way interaction, participants in one viewing order rated tone in the high audio and low audio recordings higher when paired with congruent video quality, even when the audio and video were of congruently low quality. I coded participants' answers to the free-response question to analyze which factors were most cited by participants as affecting their ratings. Most participants cited either audio quality, video quality, or general recording quality as affecting their ratings. A smaller, but not insubstantial portion of the participants stated they were aware of the recording quality but did not let it influence their ratings. Taken together, this would indicate that judges will inconsistently incorporate knowledge of the quality of digital recordings when making judgements of solo vocalists. Other commonly cited factors included performer sounds and appearance. These findings have ramifications for musicians, particularly vocalists, who use both livestreamed and pre-recorded audiovisuals to share and view recordings of performances. Given the links between household income, urban-rural classification, parent education level, and other socio-economic factors and at-home internet speed, educators in particular should consider the methods by which they recommend and implement streaming in their classrooms and curricula.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the College of Music in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 4, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">John M. Geringer, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Kari Adams, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; David Okerlund, University Representative; Michael Hanawalt, Committee Member; D. Gregory Springer, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85088796">
      <topic>Music</topic>
      <topic>Instruction and study</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Sullivan_fsu_0071E_17834</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Music</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
