<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Longleaf Pine (Pinus palustris) Growth and Population Dynamics under Climate Change</title>
      <subTitle>A Dendroecological Investigation across Unique Natural Communities in FL, USA</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-1990-9153</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Zampieri</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Nicole E.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/spau">
      <namePart type="family">Pau</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Stephanie</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/miller">
      <namePart type="family">Miller</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Thomas E.</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Professor of Biological Science)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/slester">
      <namePart type="family">Lester</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sarah</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/tzhao">
      <namePart type="family">Zhao</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Tingting</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Geography Professor)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department Of Geography</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >The longleaf pine (Pinus palustris) savanna is an endangered ecosystem within a global biodiversity hotspot. However, most studies of longleaf habitats have not considered the distinct structure and function of unique longleaf communities, which is critical for developing appropriate management strategies. Florida has 50% of the remaining habitat, where it occurs in unique community types that differ in their hydrology, species composition, and disturbance regimes. The structure and growth of longleaf pine in the different community types depends on the unique interactions between these abiotic and biotic components. The legacy of anthropogenic disturbance through logging, fragmentation, fire exclusion, and the rapidly changing climate have resulted in potentially novel dynamics for longleaf pine ecosystems. Identifying the drivers of tree growth and population dynamics can facilitate a better understanding of longleaf status and vulnerability to global change. In this dissertation, I explored and assessed how disturbances (fires and hurricanes) interact with species composition and climatic conditions to affect tree density, growth rates, and stand structure across community types in Florida. First, I assessed how differences in climate, fire, and species composition interact and relate to longleaf pine densities and growth rates in distinct communities. I used field surveys and tree cores to estimate stand structure and growth rates across community types. I used linear mixed-effects models to examine the effect of community type on longleaf pine density and growth rates and then used recursive partitioning and regression tree analyses to identify how climate, fire, and species composition affect density and growth rates. I found that stand structure and species composition were different across communities, whereas growth rates were not. Across communities, unique interactions between climate, fire, and species composition, resulted in differences in stand structure. In general, tree and grass stage densities were best predicted by species composition and fire rather than by climate within unique community types, whereas overall growth rates were best predicted by climate. I show that longleaf growth rates increased with higher temperatures, but this effect is reversed in dry conditions. Our research includes the southernmost extent of longleaf, and our results suggest that longleaf growth rates across its range will be more sensitive to current and future climate change than longleaf population density. Second, I used unique dendroecological methods to explore how climate and fire interact to affect annual tree growth. Traditional dendrochronological methods mask out individual variation by using stand level indices, and have a bias towards sampling resource limited trees, which is an effective strategy for climate reconstruction, but lacks an ecological focus. I present eight ecologically representative Florida longleaf pine chronologies and compare the strength of seasonwood and total ring width chronologies, finding that latewood growth had stronger climatic correlations, but not stronger crossdating. Then, I used correlation analyses to identify the primary climatic drivers of tree growth and found summer precipitation had a positive effect and summer temperature had a negative effect at a majority of sites, although there was no climatic variable at any season length with exact effects on tree growth across sites. Finally, I used linear mixed effects models to estimate how the climatic drivers interact with fire to affect individual tree growth. I identified unique effects from fire seasonality, with negative effects due to dormant season burning at 60% of sites. I found positive effects from fire in the previous year in 60% of sites. In many cases, fire reversed or neutralized the effect of climate, suggesting unique implications for management under climate change. By using ecologically representative samples, I show how climate and fire interact differently to affect tree growth and highlight variability in ecosystem function across communities and sites. Finally, I investigate immediate hurricane impacts to stand structure at four sites after experiencing an unprecedented Category 5 storm, which exemplifies the growing threats the longleaf pine ecosystem faces under anthropogenic climate change. I used variable-area transects and generalized linear mixed-effects models to estimate tree densities and logistic regression to estimate mortality by size class. I found at least 28% of the global total remaining extent of the longleaf pine ecosystem was affected in Florida alone. Mortality was highest in medium sized trees (30-45 cm dbh) and ranged from 4.6-15.4% at sites further from the storm center, but increased to 87.8% near the storm center. As the frequency and intensity of extreme events increases, management plans to mitigate the effects of climate change need to account for large-scale stochastic mortality events to preserve critical habitats. Even where protected, critical habitats are vulnerable to the effects of climate change.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department Of Geography in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">December 9, 2022.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">biogeography, dendrochronology</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Stephanie Pau, Professor Directing Dissertation; Thomas Miller, University Representative; Sarah Lester, Committee Member; Monica Rother, Committee Member; Tingting Zhao, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85053986">
      <topic>Geography</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014203">
      <topic>Biology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146731">
      <topic>Wildlife conservation</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Zampieri_fsu_0071E_17649</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Geography</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
