<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Effects of Written Corrective Feedback, Planning, and Individual Differences on English Language Learners' Development in Target Structure Accuracy and Task Performance</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>A Classroom-Based Study</mods:subTitle>
      <mods:nonSort>The</mods:nonSort>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0004-5259-7707</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">An</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Hye Jin</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/sli9">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Li</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Shaofeng</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/yyang3">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Yang</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Yanyun</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/phiver">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hiver</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Philip V.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2011024781">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Jones</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Ithel</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>School of Teacher Education</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (209 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Situated in the growing body of task-based language teaching research, this quasi-experimental study explored whether different types of written corrective feedback and task planning jointly influence 115 English as a foreign language learners' development in target structure accuracy and linguistic performance in L2 writing. In response to the increased need to examine the roles of learners' individual differences in second language acquisition research, the study further investigated how multiple individual characteristics variables—executive working memory, phonological short-term memory, L2 writing anxiety, and L2 writing self-efficacy—moderated the effectiveness of written corrective feedback and task planning. Additionally, the variation in learners' task-specific anxiety and self-efficacy across time points and treatment conditions was explored. The participants were from six intact classes in a public high school in South Korea, and they were assigned into six experimental groups. The groups were first divided into two feedback groups: Direct Correction (DC) and Metalinguistic Explanation (ME). The two feedback groups further diverged into three planning groups: Pre-task Planning (PTP), Within-task Planning (WTP), and No Planning (NP). During the treatment sessions, the participants received and studied different types of corrective feedback on their essays from a preceding session and subsequently engaged in a picture-based narrative writing task under the various planning conditions. The feedback targeted two linguistic structures: English articles and past tense. In the testing sessions (pretest, immediate posttest, and delayed posttest), all students were given the same picture prompt and asked to write a narrative essay describing what happened in the picture strip. The essays collected from the testing sessions were assessed in terms of their accuracy in target structures and linguistic performance (complexity, accuracy, and fluency; CAF). The students were also asked to respond to general L2 writing anxiety and L2 writing self-efficacy questionnaires (at the onset of the study) as well as task-specific anxiety and self-efficacy questionnaires (after finishing each writing test). Learners' executive working memory was measured by an Operation Span test, while the phonological short-term memory was assessed via a Digit Span test. The study aimed to answer three research questions: i) What are the main and interaction effects of written corrective feedback and task planning on EFL learners' development in target structure accuracy and linguistic performance of CAF?, ii) What is the role of learners' individual differences in executive working memory, phonological short-term memory, L2 writing anxiety, and L2 writing self-efficacy in predicting the development of target structure accuracy and linguistic performance of CAF under various task conditions?, and iii) How do learners' task-specific L2 writing anxiety and L2 writing self-efficacy vary from their initial writing experience to the final experience in different task conditions? Regarding the effects of feedback and planning, two-way ANCOVA revealed that Metalinguistic Explanation was slightly more effective than Direct Correction for the immediate past tense accuracy, but only when the learners engaged in Within-task Planning. The development of English articles, which was one of the targeted structures, was not influenced by the treatments. Regarding the performance of CAF, Pre-task Planning served as a playing field discerning the superior effects of Direct Correction over Metalinguistic Explanation on immediate and delayed syntactic complexity. Under the No Planning environment, the learners exhibited higher immediate lexical complexity when they were treated with Direct Correction, while they demonstrated enhanced general morphosyntactic and lexical accuracy upon receiving Metalinguistic Explanation. When it came to L2 writing fluency, Within-task Planning notably decreased writing speed in the immediate posttest, especially when compared to Pre-task Planning. Moreover, Direct Correction was found to be less disruptive than Metalinguistic Explanation. In examining the impact of the individual difference variables on the development of the diverse outcome measures across task conditions, two-way ANCOVA was employed, with interaction terms between treatments and individual difference factors. It was found that the impact of executive working memory on immediate outcome measures was observed across several domains, including the accuracy of articles and past tense, syntactic complexity, and overall morphosyntactic accuracy. Furthermore, this cognitive device exhibited varying influences across different treatment conditions. On the other hand, L2 writing self-efficacy emerged as a significant predictor of immediate past tense accuracy across all treatment conditions (without interaction with feedback or planning types). Other individual difference factors, namely phonological short-term memory and L2 writing anxiety, were not shown to play significant roles. It is important to highlight that the notable findings regarding the role of executive working memory and L2 writing self-efficacy were limited to the immediate posttest performance, suggesting the transient nature of individual difference factors' effects. With regard to the changes in task-specific anxiety and self-efficacy, the mixed design repeated measures ANOVA showed that learners' anxiety level toward the given writing task generally decreased from the pretest (Time 1) to the delayed posttest (Time 3), while their self-efficacy increased over time. In relation to the impact of different interventions, the combination of Direct Correction and Pre-task Planning proved beneficial in enhancing task self-efficacy during the L2 writing task performance.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of School of Teacher Education in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 25, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Anxiety, Self-efficacy, Task Performance, Task Planning, Working Memory, Written Corrective Feedback</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Shaofeng Li, Professor Directing Dissertation; Yanyun Yang, University Representative; Phil Hiver, Committee Member; Ithel Jones, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85043710">
      <mods:topic>English language</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Study and teaching</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Foreign speakers</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">An_fsu_0071E_18575</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Teacher Education</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
