<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Coordination, Advice, and Misunderstanding in Dynamic Games</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-3732-3703</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Ballard</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Joe</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lboosey">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Boosey</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Luke A.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jgrosser">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Großer</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jens W.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/djcooper">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Cooper</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">David J.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2017025730">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hamman</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">John R.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2010073490">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Isaac</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">R. Mark (Robert Mark)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1954-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Economics</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (188 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>This dissertation is comprised of three related projects, each of which explore the difficulties associated with information problems and imperfectly aligned incentives in dynamic organizational settings. The first chapter, co-authored with Luke Boosey, investigates coordination between parties who lack a common language through which to communicate their specialized procedures and, consequently, understand how to coordinate. We introduce a model of dynamic coordination with costly switching, where two players are in search of compatible platforms. In the efficient symmetric equilibrium, players remain on their current platforms with certainty if their common belief about compatibility lies above a cutoff belief (that depends on the switching cost) and otherwise mix between switching platforms and remaining on their current platforms. In the presence of switching costs, the equilibrium switching probability increases as the common belief converges toward zero, but remains below 0.5 for all beliefs. We conduct an experiment to test whether behavior supports the equilibrium predictions of the model, varying (i) whether success occurs deterministically or stochastically when players are on compatible platforms and (ii) the cost of switching platforms. Behavior is mostly in line with comparative statics predictions, especially for the Deterministic treatments, although subjects display a tendency to switch less (more) often than optimal when their common belief is low (high). Next, the second chapter examines how a decision maker optimally uses temporary and permanent disciplinary instruments to influence the quality of advice she receives from an adviser over time. I consider an infinite-horizon, repeated advice environment, where an adviser of privately known expertise, either competent or incompetent, recommends one of two options to a decision maker in each period. The decision maker chooses whether to "check" the adviser's recommendation prior to implementation in every period and then, following the public outcome, either continues or terminates the relationship. When checking is too costly, termination is the only instrument used in equilibrium, resulting in inefficient termination of competent advisers. When checking is sufficiently cheap, the decision maker never terminates the relationship, but frequent (costly) checking may occur. If competent advisers receive fully informative signals, an efficient, cooperative equilibrium can be supported through the use of continual checking (for low checking costs) or termination (for high checking costs), but this is no longer possible under a partially informative signal structure. In this case, the welfare of both competent advisers and decision makers can be improved when checking is cheaper, as this enables the use of probation periods following bad outcomes. Finally, the third chapter, co-authored with Luke Boosey, explores how the potential for misunderstanding between parties in a repeated interaction affects the informal relationships that evolve over time. We develop and analyze a principal-agent model with perfectly observed (but unenforceable) actions. In each period, the principal chooses a wage to advance to the agent, who then chooses to exert either high effort or low effort. Although high effort is more costly to the agent, it also increases the probability that the principal obtains a high project payoff. In this environment, we consider three types of unexpected shocks, with each shock increasing the expected total surplus in a high-effort equilibrium. The occurrence of such a shock raises the question of how an increase in surplus should be divided between the parties. Assuming the parties are only concerned with their own material payoffs, unexpected shocks that favor (or harm) one of the parties have no impact on the equilibrium constraint of the other party. Yet, considerations of fairness, equality, envy, or guilt may influence the way in which the parties adapt the terms of an established relational contract after an unexpected shock. To accommodate these kinds of considerations, we propose a model that uses a variation of the inequity-averse preferences of Fehr and Schmidt (1999) and show that, in the presence of inequity aversion, a high-effort equilibrium can be supported for a wide range of discount factors, provided that the equilibrium wage is sufficiently high. Moreover, the equilibrium wage range increases as the players become less patient and the principal becomes more sensitive to guilt.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Economics in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 27, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">advice, coordination, experiments, game theory, organizations, relational contracts</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Luke Boosey, Professor Directing Dissertation; Jens Grosser, University Representative; David Cooper, Committee Member; John Hamman, Committee Member; R. Mark Isaac, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040850">
      <mods:topic>Economics</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005162">
      <mods:topic>Animal behavior</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Ballard_fsu_0071E_17358</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Economics</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
