<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Gustatory and Intraoral Thermosensory Signaling in the Insular Cortex of the Mouse</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-5301-0961</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Bouaichi</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Cecilia</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rvincis">
      <namePart type="family">Vincis</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Roberto</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2004009588">
      <namePart type="family">Keel</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Pamela K.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1970-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/aspector">
      <namePart type="family">Spector</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Alan C.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dstorace">
      <namePart type="family">Storace</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Douglas</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/elemmon">
      <namePart type="family">Lemmon</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Emily C.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Biological Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (136 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>The experience of eating food and beverages generates sensations within the mouth that are inherently multimodal. These sensations involve the integration of intraoral gustatory, olfactory (retronasal), and somatosensory cues, which all contribute to the percept of flavor. The following studies detailed in this dissertation aim to better understand how neurons in the rodent's brain integrate information from two of these oral signals: taste and oral temperature. Over the years, researchers have investigated both the behavioral and physiological components of taste, which originate when nonvolatile chemicals dissolved in saliva stimulate specialized chemoreceptors within the mouth. The sense of taste allows us to nourish our bodies by identifying nutrients and calorie-rich foods and discerning foods that may be potentially harmful or toxic. Information about nonvolatile chemicals dissolved in saliva is transduced into electrical signals by specialized receptors on the tongue. The gustatory information is then transmitted to multiple central and interconnected brain regions, including the gustatory portion of the insular cortex (gustatory cortex; GC), the primary cortical region responsible for processing taste information. GC neurons have been extensively studied and are known to represent the five basic taste qualities – sweet, salty, sour, bitter and umami - through changes in their spiking activity. These responses reflect the ongoing processing and integration of diverse gustatory information. For example, GC neurons respond to the chemosensory qualities of gustatory stimuli while also accounting for sensory signals that anticipate the availability of food and behavioral states. The vast majority of previous studies on cortical taste processing in behaving animals have been performed using rats as animal models, and intraoral cannulae (IOCs) as a method for fluid taste delivery. In contrast, relatively less work has been done in mice, an animal model that offers easier access to genetic tools for manipulating and visualizing neuronal activity. Additionally, although IOCs provide a reliable and rapid method of delivering taste solutions, they add a degree of passivity to taste delivery and could potentially alter the sequence of events associated with neural processing of gustatory information. In Chapter 2, I present data pertaining to cortical taste processing in behaving mice that sense liquid gustatory stimuli by licking, a stereotyped behavior by which fluids are actively introduced in the mouth. The result of this study, published in The Journal of Neurophysiology, provided the first description of how the GC of active licking mice encodes information about taste qualities and ongoing sampling (licking) behavior, expanding our knowledge of cortical taste processing. Most of what is known about the neural substrates of taste originates from studies - including my first one - in which stimuli are experienced at a single temperature. Although this approach has shaped our understanding of the role of gustation, it provides only a partial picture of the functional features of the gustatory system. In our natural environment, foods and beverages are rarely experienced at a single temperature. From our common daily experience, we know that temperature can serve as an important signal that can influence the sensory attributes of food and the perceived intensity of taste qualities relevant to food and beverage preferences, influencing eating habits. In the second part of my dissertation, I first focused on understanding how neurons in the GC of active licking mice represent oral thermosensory input in the absence of taste information. The results of this study, published in Chemical Senses, highlight that GC neurons are capable of representing different non-nociceptive fluid temperature in absence of a taste signal, further expanding on their multimodal nature. In Chapter 4, we begin to explore the interaction between taste and temperature within the mouse GC. Our aim is to elucidate how GC neurons process intraoral thermal cues and how this information might modulate taste quality or intensity coding. Preliminary findings indicate that GC neurons possess the capacity to integrate intraoral thermal and taste information, distinctly coding taste qualities at different temperatures and modulating taste intensity representation. Collectively, these observations highlight the potential role of the GC as a cortical nexus for integrating intraoral taste and thermal inputs.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Biological Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">May 15, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">Active licking, Cortex, Extracellular recording, Flavor, Gustation, Thermal</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Roberto Vincis, Professor Directing Dissertation; Pamela Keel, University Representative; Alan Spector, Committee Member; Douglas Storace, Committee Member; Emily Lemmon, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91006099">
      <topic>Neurosciences</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Bouaichi_fsu_0071E_18857</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Biological Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
