<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Enhancing Learning Achievements and Self-Efficacy for Preservice Teachers Using Model-Based Support in Simulation-Based Learning with Artificial Intelligence-Powered Virtual Agents</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-0977-0039</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Dai</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Chih-Pu</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2013090332">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Ke</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Fengfeng</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2011088991">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Yuan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Xin</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="termsOfAddress">Ph. D</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2012011678">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Dennen</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Vanessa P.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1970-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2003122703">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Klein</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">James D.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Educational Psychology and Learning Systems</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (140 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>The quality of teachers is crucial for students' learning and human development, particularly in modern multicultural classrooms and rapidly evolving environments. A key focus of teacher preparation is to transform classroom discourse and promote problem-solving skills and critical thinking. In order to foster critical thinking and facilitate rigorous understanding among students, teachers need to acquire ambitious teaching practices that elicit students' existing knowledge, facilitate discussions, and promote synergistic negotiation. Practice-rooted simulation-based teacher learning programs that provide ample practice opportunities and real-time feedback are essential for systematic knowledge and skills development for teachers before they engage in classroom practicum with human students. Unfortunately, there is a lack of such programs. One way to address this gap is through the use of virtual reality simulation with artificial intelligence (AI)-powered virtual agents. It is also important to provide guidance and support within this type of teacher learning environment. To this end, the purpose of this study was to examine the effects of model-based support (the widgets that are integrated into virtual reality simulation for teacher learning that contain prompts, hints, modeling, and reflection in the pretraining, in-simulation, and post-simulation phases) on teaching knowledge and skills development and teaching self-efficacy in simulation-based teacher learning with AI-powered virtual agents. I employed an experimental design in this study to investigate the effects of model-based support in simulation-based learning with AI-powered virtual students on the teaching knowledge and skills as well as teaching self-efficacy of preservice teachers. I recruited 57 preservice teachers to participate in this study. The participating preservice teachers were randomly assigned to either the model-based support with AI-powered virtual agents group (i.e., model-based support group), AI-powered virtual agents without model-based support group (i.e., AI-powered virtual agent only group), and the no-treatment control group. I used pre- and post- teaching knowledge and skills tests and pre- and post-teaching self-efficacy scales to collect the data. ANCOVA results demonstrated that participants in both model-based support group and AI-powered virtual agents only group outperformed those in the no-treatment control group on the teaching knowledge and skills test. Bonferroni post hoc comparisons revealed no significant difference between model-based support group and AI-powered virtual agents only group. In terms of teaching self-efficacy, no significant differences were found between the experimental groups (i.e., model-based support group and AI-powered virtual agent only group) and the control group. Further, with regression analyses, I found significant predicting effects of the total duration of model-based support use (the sum of the duration of pretraining support, in-situ support, and post-simulation support use) on teaching knowledge and skills. Specifically, the significant effects were observed for the pretraining stage and the post-simulation stage, but not for the in-situ stage. The significant predicting effects were not found for teaching self-efficacy. The implications of the study findings suggest that the design of supports in simulation-based learning for preservice teachers should incorporate preparations for ambitious teaching practices as well as human-AI interactions. It is also beneficial for the preservice teachers to engage in post-simulation reflections. Future research should continue to explore the different designs of learning support in simulation-based learning with AI-powered virtual agents for preservice teachers, particularly the ones that improve intrinsic integration of the learning support in virtual reality simulation-based learning.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Psychology and Learning Systems in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 10, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Ambitious teaching, Artificial Intelligence, Learning support, Simulation-based learning, Virtual agents</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Fengfeng Ke, Professor Directing Dissertation; Xin Yuan, University Representative; Vanessa Dennen, Committee Member; James Klein, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041150">
      <mods:topic>Educational technology</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989">
      <mods:topic>Education</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132999">
      <mods:topic>Teachers</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Training of</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Dai_fsu_0071E_18132</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Psychology and Learning Systems</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
