<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Colloidal Perovskite Quantum Dots</title>
      <subTitle>Surface Passivation and Photochemical Processes</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-1377-2689</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Donmez</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Selin</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nb2009002696">
      <namePart type="family">Mattoussi</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Hedi</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/steinbck">
      <namePart type="family">Steinbock</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Oliver</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dfadool">
      <namePart type="family">Fadool</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Debra Ann</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kennemur">
      <namePart type="family">Kennemur</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Justin Glenn</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/strouse">
      <namePart type="family">Strouse</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Geoffrey F.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (109 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>The colloidal lead halide perovskite nanocrystals (PNCs) have sparked significant interest in recent years due to their unique optical properties and potential applications in light-emitting devices and solar cells. However, challenges with their colloidal and photophysical instability have hindered the exploration of their fundamental properties and integration into optoelectronic devices. The focus of this dissertation is to introduce a surface chemistry strategy based on ligand exchange method using high affinity coordinating polymers. This enhances the surface passivation of PNCs and enables their use in photochemical processes. In Chapter 1, we provided an overview of the fundamental physical and chemical characteristics of semiconducting quantum dots (QDs), as well as a detailed introduction to metal halide perovskites, emphasizing their growth methods, crystal structures, shape control, anion exchange, and characteristic phase transformations. Additionally, we summarized various strategies reported in literature to address the stability issues of PNCs, focusing on their colloidal, structural, and photophysical properties. In Chapter 2, we studied the photo-assisted halide exchange reaction of CsPbBr3 perovskite quantum dots (PQDs) dispersed in chlorinated solvents. We probed the kinetics of this process and the associated blue shift in the emission properties, by varying the irradiation source, its duration, and the structure of the solvent molecules. We carried out a thorough characterization of the nanocrystal intermediates during this irradiation period, using optical and fluorescence spectroscopy, supplemented with powder X-ray diffraction and X-ray fluorescence spectrometry measurements. Our findings indicate that the PQDs can act as photocatalysts, where they absorb high-energy photons, promoting rapid electron transfer to the alkyl chloride molecules and triggering their dissociative degradation to produce radical alkyl molecules and chloride ions. These findings show that PQDs exhibit promising photocatalytic properties that may find use in common organic reactions including dehalogenation. In Chapter 3, we presented energy transfer interactions between PQDs and cyanine-based dye molecules. We employed CsPbBr3 PQDs and various cyanine dye molecules with tailored structures to control spectral overlap and their affinity to PQD surfaces, enabling a precise manipulation of the donor-acceptor separation distance. This approach offers a unique system for xiii probing FRET interactions within PQD/dye assemblies. Our findings consistently indicate efficient energy transfer between donor and acceptor molecules, as evidenced by the reduced PQD emission, shortened PQD fluorescence lifetime, and concurrent enhancement of dye fluorescence. Additionally, we assessed the impact of spectral overlap on FRET efficiency, revealing that reduced spectral overlap leads to less efficient energy transfer, aligning with the Förster formalism. In Chapter 4, we introduced a novel polyzwitterionic polymer ligand based on the carboxybetaine motif with enhanced coordination interactions for the surface treatment of hybrid MAPbBr3 PNCs. These ligands incorporate several octylamine solubilizing moieties, in addition to multiple carboxybetaine groups. We showed that mixing as-grown dispersion of MAPbBr3 PNCs with polycarboxybetaine ligands triggers rapid homogenization of the nanocrystal dispersion, resulting in narrow emission profiles along with increased quantum yield. This was attributed to enhanced ligand binding to the PNC surfaces, promoted through templating effects, which produces size focusing combined with better passivation of surface defects. Furthermore, we found that this coating strategy is effective in promoting long term colloidal stability of these dispersions while preserving their colloidal and structural integrity. In Chapter 5, we summarized the work in this dissertation on the surface passivation of PNCs and their use in photochemical processes, along with a discussion on future directions, including the exploration of their potential applications in light emitting diodes.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 14, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Hedi Mattoussi, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Oliver Steinbock, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Debra Fadool, University Representative; Justin G. Kennemur, Committee Member; Geoffrey F. Strouse, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023027">
      <topic>Chemistry, Physical and theoretical</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Donmez_fsu_0071E_18967</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
