<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Defining the Responsiveness of Glucocorticoid Myopathic Skeletal Muscle to Mechanical Overload</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0007-5892-2103</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Dunlap</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kirsten R.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/bsgordon">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Gordon</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Bradley S.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/pchase">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Chase</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">P. Bryant</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rhickner">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hickner</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Robert C.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1962-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2013036098">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Steiner</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jennifer L.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Health and Human Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Nutrition and Integrative Physiology</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (120 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Muscle atrophy decreases physical function and overall health. Increased glucocorticoid production and/or use of prescription glucocorticoids can result in a myopathy that presents with significant muscle atrophy and weakness. Glucocorticoids cause atrophy by activating the glucocorticoid receptor, thereby transcribing genes that shift protein balance in favor of net protein degradation. While mechanical overload can blunt glucocorticoid-induced atrophy in young muscle, it is unknown whether mechanical overload influences glucocorticoid receptor nuclear translocation, a critical step in the receptor activation process. Moreover, it is unknown whether muscle contractile force alters regulation of glucocorticoid receptor because those susceptible to glucocorticoid myopathy are generally at risk of having reduced muscle force generation capacity. Therefore, Specific Aim 1 sought to determine whether contractile force differentially regulates glucocorticoid receptor activation within the skeletal muscle. Male mice were subjected to a single bout of unilateral, electrically induced muscle contractions by stimulating the sciatic nerve at 100 Hz or 50 Hz frequencies to elicit high force or moderate force contractions of the tibialis anterior (TA), respectively. Dexamethasone (DEX) was administered via intraperitoneal (IP) injection at 1mg/kg to activate the glucocorticoid receptor acutely. Treatment with DEX increased glucocorticoid nuclear translocation and expression of putative target genes, but those outcomes were mitigated by high force, but not moderate force, contractions. The ability of high force contractions to mitigate glucocorticoid receptor translocation coincided with a sustained ability for muscle contractions to increase rates of muscle protein synthesis, which is an outcome that can ultimately reduce the negative shift in protein balance induced by glucocorticoids. Interestingly, moderate force contractions did not increase rates of muscle protein synthesis only in the DEX treated mice. Thus, these data show that force generation is important for the ability of resistance exercise to mitigate glucocorticoid receptor translocation and ultimately activate the processes that will reduce the loss of muscle mass in those with elevated glucocorticoids. While these data and the classic data demonstrate the potential for mechanical overload to mitigate glucocorticoid myopathy by reducing glucocorticoid receptor activation and increasing rates of muscle protein synthesis if the mechanical overload and glucocorticoid treatment are started at the same time, it is unknown whether mechanical overload can increase muscle protein synthesis when the glucocorticoid myopathy is already present. Determining whether mechanical overload can increase rates of muscle protein synthesis in glucocorticoid myopathic muscle is important because long-term glucocorticoid exposure can increase the expression of genes that may prevent activation of pathways like the mechanistic target of rapamycin in complex 1 (mTORC1) that contribute to the increase in rates of muscle protein synthesis. Therefore, Specific Aim 2 sought to determine the extent to which mechanical overload increases muscle protein synthesis during the initiation of glucocorticoid myopathy and after the myopathy has more fully developed. Early myopathy was induced in physically mature female mice via daily IP injections of saline as control or 1mg/kg DEX. After 1 week of treatment, the left TA muscle of all mice was subjected to a bout of muscle contractions as stated in Aim 1. In a subsequent experiment, physically mature female mice received regular drinking water as control or DEX in their drinking water for 2 weeks to fully induce myopathy. After 2 weeks of treatment, mice were subjected to unilateral muscle contractions. In both experiments, signaling through mTORC1 and rates of muscle protein synthesis were assessed. Despite initiation of myopathy following 1 week of DEX treatment, mechanical overload increased protein synthesis and mTORC1 signaling equally compared to control mice. After 2 weeks, mechanical overload activated mTORC1 signaling equally in both DEX and control mice, but protein synthesis was only increased by mechanical overload in control mice, suggesting that the stage of glucocorticoid myopathy alters the anabolic response to mechanical overload. Altogether, our data demonstrate that contractile force and duration of glucocorticoid treatment regulates the ability of mechanical overload to alter the signals that would be needed to minimize the atrophy induced by glucocorticoids.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Nutrition and Integrative Physiology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">May 3, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Anabolic resistance, Glucocorticoid myopathy, Mechanical overload, mTORC1, Muscle atrophy, Protein synthesis</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Bradley S. Gordon, Professor Directing Dissertation; P. Bryant Chase, University Representative; Robert C. Hickner, Committee Member; Jennifer L. Steiner, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85101679">
      <mods:topic>Physiology</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Dunlap_fsu_0071E_17956</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Nutrition, Food, and Exercise Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
