<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Effects of the First Language on the Second</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>A Psycholinguistic Investigation of Bilingual Lexical Processing and First Language Attrition</mods:subTitle>
      <mods:nonSort>The</mods:nonSort>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">lauragil</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Gil</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Ana Laura</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/gsunderm">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Sunderman</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Gretchen L.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/cjackson3">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Wood</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Carla</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Speech-Language Pathology Professor)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2015008326">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Muntendam</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Antje</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2004039478">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Leeser</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Michael J.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Modern Languages and Linguistics</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (311 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Research on language and cognitive processes in bilinguals over the past few decades has underscored the activation of words in the first language (L1) during comprehension and production of the second language (L2) (e.g., Dijkstra, Van Jaarsveld, &amp; Ten Brinke, 1998; Van Heuven, Dijkstra, &amp; Grainger, 1998; Hermans, Bongaerts, De Bot, &amp; Schreuder, 1998;Lemhöfer, et al., 2008). This activation extends bidirectionally, with words from the L2 also influencing the processing of the L1 (e.g., Van Hell &amp; De Groot, 2008; Linck, Kroll, &amp; Sunderman, 2009; Schmid &amp; Jarvis, 2014; Schmid &amp; Keijzer, 2009), leading to cross-linguistic interference (CLI) in bilinguals' language processing. However, the nature and extent of this interference may vary depending on the bilingual's dominant language and immersion context. L1-dominant bilinguals may struggle to control interference from their L1s, while the opposite may hold true for L2-dominant bilinguals, even when their L2 is not their native language. Consequently, the formerly dominant L1 of some bilinguals may exhibit signs of attrition. This dissertation explores the relationship between attrition and L2 acquisition, addressing two key questions: (1) to what extent does context (place of residence) and nature of bilingualism influences the amount and direction of cross-language interference? and (2) to what extent (if any) is the activation of form and meaning modulated by the nature of the lexical relationships and individual differences measures? And, if effects are found, how does sentence context modulate those effects? The contribution of this study stems from the novel examination of two types of semantic extensions: a) new meanings or words that share form but do not share any semantic relationship across languages; and b) extended meanings or words that share form and at least one semantic sense across languages. Additionally, synonyms, unrelated words, cognates, interlingual homographs and translation pairs are also included to explore form-meaning interactions. The comprehension of words with varying degrees of form-meaning relatedness is evaluated in two tasks: (1) a semantic-relatedness decision task (SRDT) within and across languages and (2) a self-paced reading task (SPR). Sentence cues in unilingual language contexts are manipulated in congruent and incongruent conditions to assess interference effects. Participants also complete a flanker task as a measure of cognitive control and a battery of proficiency measures. These tasks are implemented across five participant groups: Page 12 of 308 (1) monolingual speakers of English in the U.S, (2) monolingual Spanish speakers in Argentina, (3) L1 Spanish-L2 English bilinguals in the USA, (4), L1 Spanish-L2 English bilinguals in Argentina and (5) L1 English-L2 Spanish learners in the USA. Results from this study indicate that immersion context influences the direction of language interference, with more L2 to L1 effects observed for immersed bilinguals compared to non-immersed counterparts, and with both groups being vulnerable to CLI effects compared to monolinguals. Despite extended exposure in an L2 dominant context, bilinguals can maintain their L1 proficiency, contradicting L1 attrition views. The activation of form-meaning relationships is directly related to the nature of the lexical relationships, with orthographically and semantically related words (e.g., cognates; extended meanings) showing processing advantages over orthographically related but semantically unrelated words across languages (e.g., false friends, new meanings). Within-language semantic competitors cause more interference during processing compared to unrelated words. Inhibitory control mechanisms or language dominance do not significantly attenuate CLI effects from form-meaning competitors in the non-target language. Results from the SPR revealed that sentence context can modulate interference effects, facilitating the resolution of lexical ambiguities and form-meaning relationships. However, language cues from a sentence alone are not sufficient to constrain CL competition, highlighting the importance of semantic information conveyed by the sentence context for language non-selectivity to occur. Overall, bilingual characteristics, including the type of bilingual, linguistic exposure/experience and levels of L1-L2 proficiency all seem to influence language processing. This dissertation contributes to the field of psycholinguistics of bilingualism, language attrition and second language acquisition. It highlights the importance of understanding language-attrition as a bridge between first- and second-language lexical processing.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Modern Languages and Linguistics in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 25, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">bilingualism, cross linguistic interference, first language attrition, language contact, psycholinguistics, second language acquisition</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Gretchen L. Sunderman, Professor Directing Dissertation; Carla Lynn Wood, University Representative; Antje Gerda Muntendam, Committee Member; Michael J. Leeser, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077222">
      <mods:topic>Linguistics</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85074518">
      <mods:topic>Language and languages</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Gil_fsu_0071E_18599</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Modern Languages and Linguistics</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
