<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Using 'Omics' Methodologies to Identify Active, Novel Hydrocarbon Degrading Microorganisms in the Northern Gulf of Mexico and in the Global Ocean</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0000-4586-0694</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Howe</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kathryn Lynn</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2004084871">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Mason</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Olivia Underwood</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/marbeitman">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Arbeitman</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Michelle N. (Michelle Nina)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mhuettel">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Huettel</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Markus</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2006015588">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Knapp</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Angela Noel</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1976-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/skranz">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kranz</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Sven Alexander</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (152 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Hundreds of millions of liters of oil and natural gas are introduced to the ocean annually, yet the ecological consequences of hydrocarbon inputs into the marine environment are poorly understood. In particular, the role of microbes in oil and gas consumption in the marine environment is not well characterized. Much of what is known about hydrocarbon degrading microorganisms, particularly those in the marine environment, stems from cultivation-based studies. However, the majority of microbes elude cultivation, which leads to a significant knowledge gap regarding the degradation capabilities of uncultured, indigenous microbes in the ocean. Multi-omics approaches allow for circumventing the need to culture an organism in the lab to study its physiology and provides a definitive link between taxonomy, function and activity of uncultured hydrocarbon degrading microbes. In this thesis, resolving the identities, metabolic capabilities, and activity of uncultured hydrocarbon-degrading microorganisms was done through utilization of new computational methods for multi-omics datasets to analyze metagenomes and metatranscriptomes from the Gulf of Mexico (GOM) water column and global ocean by taking advantage of. Chapters two and three were solely focused on microbial hydrocarbon degradation, while chapter four included analysis of both hydrocarbon production and consumption. In chapters two and three, genome assembly, gene annotation, and read mapping was used to elucidate microbial hydrocarbon degradation pathways in the GOM (our datasets) and global ocean (previously existing datasets, such as TARA Ocean). Metagenome assembled genomes (MAGs) combined with read mapping revealed that previously unrecognized, uncultured microbes are actively expressing genes and pathways for hydrocarbon degradation. For example, in chapter 2, Planctomycetota, Verrucomicrobiota, and Latescibacterota, clades lacking known methane-oxidizers in the marine environment, were identified as novel, non-canonical methanotrophs in the GOM and in the global ocean. These findings help resolve rate measurement and metatranscriptomic data that showed methane oxidation is an active process in northern GOM hypoxic zone, an ecosystem where canonical methane-oxidizing microbes are at negligible abundances. Similarly, chapter three multi-omics data analysis from the Deepwater Horizon (DWH) oil spill deep-sea plume, in which methane was the most abundant hydrocarbon, and from the global ocean revealed non-canonical methanotrophs in the Cycloclasticus. This represents a novel finding as this clade lacks members that are known carry out aerobic methane oxidation. Additional clade specific substrate degradation potentials that have not been reported previously included Bermanella genomes that encoded and expressed genes for medium and long chain n-alkanes and cycloalkane degradation, as did Colwellia, Cycloclasticus, and UBA11654. However, DWH Bermanella encoded an alkane hydroxylase, not an alkane monooxygenase, which is an important finding given that alkane hydroxylase has a narrow substrate range (C8-C16) compared to alkane monooxygenase (alkB) (C12-C26), and is entirely consistent with the profile of Macondo oil where C8-C16 were the most abundant non-gaseous n-alkanes. Lastly, SAR324 and UBA11654 contained members that encoded for aromatic hydrocarbon degradation. While chapters two and three evaluated microbial consumption of fossil fuels input to the marine environment, both naturally and through anthropogenic activities, in what is termed the long-term hydrocarbon cycle, chapter four evaluated the complete cycle of hydrocarbon production to consumption in the photic zone, termed the short-term hydrocarbon cycle. The short-term hydrocarbon cycle was evaluated using metatranscriptomic data from the photic zone of the GOM and previously assembled genomic data from over 8,000 MAGs from OceanDNA (Nishimura and Yoshizawa 2022) and close to 1,000 Prochlorococcus and Synechococcus genomes from the Prochlorococcus Portal. This analysis revealed active pathways for the production of pentadecane (C15) and heptadecane (C17) by Prochlorococcus and, to a lesser degree Synechococcus, co-occurring with active n-alkane degradation, including C15 and C17 alkanes, by microbes in the photic zone of the GOM. Additionally, this active n-alkane degradation pathway was similar to the dominant hydrocarbon degradation pathway in the DWH oil spill plume. Specifically, the complete pathway from alkane degradation via alkane-monooxygenase through fatty acid metabolism was reconstructed for 18 bacterial phyla and one archaeal phylum. Overall, the findings in this dissertation indicate there is a large, diverse, and active group of microbes with the ability to degrade a spectrum of hydrocarbon substrates. Collectively, these analyses of uncultured planktonic microbes link taxonomy and function and provide an opportunity to predict the microbial response to oil and gas input to the marine environment, thus providing new insights into the fate of oil (and gas) when hydrocarbons are input to the ocean, leading to a greater understanding of the ecological consequences to the marine environment.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Earth, Ocean and Atmospheric Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">May 1, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">hydrocarbon-degrading microbes, marine hydrocarbon cycle, metagenome-assembled genomes, metagenomics, metatranscriptomics</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Olivia U. Mason, Professor Directing Dissertation; Michelle Arbeitman, University Representative; Markus Huettel, Committee Member; Angela Knapp, Committee Member; Sven Kranz, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081138">
      <mods:topic>Marine biology</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Howe_fsu_0071E_18014</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
