<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Build Your Own Living Space</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Architecture and the Politicized Body in the Work of Lygia Clark</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0002-0690-9584</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kershaw</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Julia Talmadge</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2005031540">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Bick</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Tenley C.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/skshields">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Shields</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Sara Scott</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ymclane">
      <mods:namePart type="family">McLane</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Yelena</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2013043288">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Niell</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Paul B.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1976-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2013033964">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Dowell</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kristin L.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/monicaamor">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Amor</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Mónica</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Fine Arts</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Art History</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (319 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>In modernist and contemporary art history, abstract art has long been associated with issues surrounding autonomy and breaks with figurative art. Scholarship surrounding the development of abstract art in Brazil has tended to focus on those connections in addition to its receptions by local art critics Ferreira Gullar and Mário Pedrosa and trajectories of European movements in abstract art, namely De Stijl, neoplasticism, and concrete art. While these readings have recognized important lineages for abstraction contextualized within the visual arts, the intersection between abstraction in Brazil and architecture remains understudied in comparison. I examine the work of Brazilian postwar and contemporary artist Lygia Clark (1920–1988) to show how her work is just at home in fields of painting and sculpture as it is in disciplines of architecture and design. By forging these connections outside of the visual arts, Brazilian abstract art in the postwar period became a political cultural tool of modern architecture and space, as well as an outlet for civilians to contribute to Brazil's status as a growing modern nation by constructing modernist spaces. Through formal and social art historical analysis of the work of Lygia Clark, this dissertation revises histories of abstraction in postwar Brazilian art to better account for understudied contexts of architecture, public space, and the built environment. Clark is best known for her interactive geometric Bicho (Critter; 1960–1966) sculptures and association with the neoconcrete group (1959–1961), the Brazilian artistic avant-garde recognized for its participatory artwork. Much like the histories of abstract art to which she belonged, namely concrete and neoconcrete art, her contributions are often tied to painting and sculpture, despite her career-long engagement with architecture. In response to this historiographic problem, this dissertation addresses Clark's sustained work in and engagement of architecture such as her little-known works, including her ink drawing of a street scene from 1948 and a mural mosaic from 1951, still extant in Rio. Examination of her training and collaboration with landscape designers and architects reveals her synthetic approach to the arts, which facilitates new debates about integrative approaches to the arts that tend to focus on De Stijl and the Bauhaus. Chapter Two, "Staircases, Interiors, and Studies of Space: The Early Works, 1948–1953," focuses on the earliest and often overlooked stage of Clark's career—where her architectural engagement began—prior to her affiliation with concretism with the Grupo Frente in the mid-1950s. Chapter Three, "Clark's Models of Houses and Architectural Interiors: Displays of Modernist Living," provides the first in-depth study of Clark's small-scale models of homes from 1955 to 1964, of which she made six. This chapter argues that Clark re-envisioned neoconcrete art—a form of abstract art—as manipulatable architectural models that engaged with local and global trends of architecture and provided opportunities for viewers to construct home layouts. Chapter Four, "'Walking Along:' Path-Making as Spatial and Subversive Interventions," analyzes Clark's sculptural action and abstract sculptures in politicized contexts of Brazil. Fostering interventionist spatial imaginaries, Caminhando (Walking; 1963), and Trepante (Climber; 1965), and Trepante e caixa (Climber and Box; 1964), use "the winding path" as a strategy to subvert authority by questioning spatial and architectural boundaries of the built environment. Chapter Five, "Clark's Articulation of Architectural and Environmental Imaginaries," examines the sculptural objects, entitled Caixas de fósforos (Matchboxes, 1964) and Arquitetura fantástica bichos (Fantastic Architecture Critters; 1963), the installation, entitled A casa é o corpo: penetração, ovulação, germinação, expulsão (The House is the Body: Penetration, Ovulation, Germination, Expulsion; 1968), and propositions, entitled Arquitetura Biológica II (Biologic Architecture II; 1969) and Estruturas vivas (Live Structures; 1969) as case studies. As articulations of anti-authoritarian architectural and environmental imaginaries in varying degrees, these sculptural objects, installations, and propositions demonstrate how space and structure provided outlets to challenge authority and question the possibilities of architecture, while also intensifying environments and feelings associated with political repression under Brazil's military dictatorship. Using formal and social art historical analysis, supported by extensive archival and field research conducted in Brazil, Argentina, England, and the United States, this dissertation addresses existing gaps between visual art and architecture in the field of art history, particularly in histories of abstract art. Rather than situating Clark's work mainly in relation to histories of neoconcrete art and its broader legacies of painting and sculpture, I have instead mapped out a new trajectory for her practice based on architecture and urbanism as politicized sites of modernism in and out of Brazil in the postwar decades. In doing so, this project also formulates a new term in relation to Clark, the "artist-architect," a helpful designation for artists who straddle the line between the visual arts and the built environment. This term can encourage global intersections across potentially disparate areas and periods. Analyzing works of "artist-architects" across media can also present experimental grounds for transgressive practices of resistance and self-expression.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Art History in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 5, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Tenley Bick, Professor Directing Dissertation; Sara Shields, University Representative; Yelena McLane, Committee Member; Paul Niell, Committee Member; Kristin Dowell, Committee Member; Mónica Amor, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007488">
      <mods:topic>Art</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>History</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85006611">
      <mods:topic>Architecture</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85074895">
      <mods:geographic>Latin America</mods:geographic>
      <mods:topic>History</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Kershaw_fsu_0071E_18692</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Art History</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
