<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Structural Insights into Asynchronous Flight Muscle Thick Filament in Insects</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-6366-6019</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Li</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jiawei</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/taylor">
      <namePart type="family">Taylor</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kenneth A.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/alemmon">
      <namePart type="family">Lemmon</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Alan R.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mestroupe">
      <namePart type="family">Stroupe</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">M. Elizabeth (Margaret Elizabeth)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/pchase">
      <namePart type="family">Chase</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">P. Bryant</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2020182305">
      <namePart type="family">Yin</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Qian (Assistant professor of biological science)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Program in Molecular Biophysics</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (121 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>In structural biology, the ultimate goal is to understand the fundamental function of various biological components through their structure, ranging from a single protein to the complex cellular structures. The key to this mission lies in the visualization of their structures in vitro through various established techniques. Methods like X-ray crystallography, Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectroscopy, Single Particle Cryo-Electron Microscopy (Cryo-EM), and Cryo-Electron Tomography (Cryo-ET) have been developed for this purpose, while each of them comes with its own set of strengths and limitations. When it comes to investigating large biomolecules or complexes in their natural states, Cryo-EM stands out for its ability to probe structural details at high resolution, although it could pose a challenge in the process of sample preparation, data collection and image processing across different type of proteins. The core of this work is devoted to the structure of different insect flight muscle thick filaments resolved by Single Particle Cryo-EM. As one of the major components of muscle structure, the thick filament in insect asynchronous flight muscle is a complex containing the major protein myosin and many associated non-myosin proteins. As one of the largest subcellular macromolecular structures, obtaining a high-resolution structure and investigating its molecular interactions has been historically challenging. Our work started with constructing high-resolution structures. Alongside complementary result from Mass spectrometry, multiple sequence alignment and model prediction, an exhaustive analysis was conducted to correlate structural insights to functional significance. Chapter 1 serves as an introduction to muscle proteins, mostly found in striated muscle, and single particle cryo-EM. The introduction is deliberately concise, outlining only the essential concepts necessary to understand the subsequent chapters. Chapter 2 focuses on the single-particle structure of the Bombus ignitus flight muscle thick filament, the structure of which has been published on the International Journal of Molecular Science (1). Using conventional single particle Cryo-EM techniques but with data collected on a more advanced camera and data analysis conducted with more powerful programs, an exceptional high-resolution structure (6Å) was achieved – a notable feat at the time. This study provides many insights into flight muscle thick filament structure and function by comparing Bombus to the structures of Lethocerus and Drosophila, which highlights the fundamental structure and assembly of the myosin but variations in non-myosin proteins, and more significant, the different myosin heads structure of relaxed muscle. Chapter 3 narrows the scope to data analysis of Drosophila thick filament structure with 4.7 Å resolution. Disordered densities in the Cryo-EM structure have been a big hurdle to attaining high resolution due to the heterogeneity. However, with an expanded dataset and particle number, we improved the resolution of the thick filament structure, even when the myosin heads were disordered. This breakthrough led us, for the first time, to build and study the atomic structure of myosin and non-myosin proteins, it enabled us to investigate the atomic interactions between myosin and flightin, one of the non-myosin proteins associated with myosin, the significance has been demonstrated by sequence conservation and disease-related mutation sites. This segment of work also has been published on the International Journal of Molecular Science (2). Chapter 4 focuses on the work on a Bess beetle, Odontotaenius disjunctus, which is an insect of the Coleoptera order. Coleopterans are the fourth and last insect order that has asynchronous flight muscle. Beetles have a similar lifestyle as Lethocerus as they barely fly, indicating the similar thick filament structure and function. We observed a consistent myosin structure and arrangement in the thick filament backbone, but unexpectedly disordered myosin heads. For the non-myosin proteins, we also observed a novel surface protein appeared in Bess beetle thick filament with unknown identity, also flightin is missing. We also resolved alpha helical structure of putative paramyosin in this thick filament map. Our investigation into the flight muscle thick filaments across four distinct insects - Lethocerus, Drosophila, Bombus and Odontotaenius – belonging to four different orders with a shared ancestor. Our comparative and comprehensive analyses of the thick filaments across the species demonstrated the preservation of fundamental structure of thick filament backbone, and diversity of non-myosin proteins. These findings enhanced our understanding of the structure of thick filaments, which is applicable to all striated muscle, including cardiac muscle. Non-myosin proteins contribute to many key features of thick filament, and they have adapted different conformations in four insects to support distinct muscle functions and physiological demands by cooperating with myosin. We believe all proteins work collectively to establish and preserve the structural integrity of the thick filament.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Molecular Biophysics in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">May 28, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Kenneth A. Taylor, Professor Directing Dissertation; Alan Lemmon, University Representative; M. Elizabeth Stroupe, Committee Member; P. Bryant Chase, Committee Member; Qian Yin, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014253">
      <topic>Biophysics</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Li_fsu_0071E_18877</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Molecular Biophysics</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
