<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Exploring Administrators' Perspectives on Cultivating Sense of Belonging through Black Male Mentorship Programs at Mid-Size and Large Predominantly White Institutions</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0001-8451-8071</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Lovett</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Darryl</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/cbeatty">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Beatty</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Cameron C.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2005039142">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Eklund</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Robert C. (Robert Charles)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1958-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2012049769">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Park</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Toby J.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/amw22l">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Wofford</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Ann Marie</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (108 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Black male students enrolled in predominantly White institutions (PWIs) face a myriad of challenges that hinder their academic success and overall well-being. These students often grapple with feelings of disconnection, stress, and isolation. According to studies, Black male students in PWIs are more likely to experience lower retention rates, higher dropout rates, and lower academic performance compared to their peers (Harper et al., 2018). This research explores the critical need to foster a sense of belonging for Black male students at PWIs, acknowledging the multifaceted nature of their experiences and the systemic barriers they encounter. Drawing on the works of Brooms (2020) and McCoy (2014), this study examines administrators' perspectives on Black male mentorship programs and their impact on Black male students' sense of belonging and success within PWIs. Employing a qualitative methodology (Merriam, 1998), this study focused on gaining insights into administrators' viewpoints on Black male mentorship programs, allowing them to share their experiences and the significance they attributed to these programs (Merriam &amp; Tisdell, 2016). Data collection involved interviews with ten administrators directly overseeing and leading Black male mentorship programs at mid-size and large PWIs. The research questions probed how administrators utilize these programs to cultivate a sense of belonging for Black male undergraduate students and how they addressed challenges encountered in overseeing them. The findings highlight the positive impact of Black male mentorship programs, indicating that administrators perceive them as advantageous for fostering a sense of community, connection, and positive experiences. Although administrators recognized the advantages of these programs, they also highlighted areas for improvement in different aspects of the programs and within their institutions. This nuanced understanding of mentorship programs for Black male students has played a significant role in fostering a sense of belonging within PWI settings. In response to research question one, the data identified two primary themes: (1) facilitating personal connection and (2) fostering an engaging and supportive environment. These themes illuminated the ways in which mentorship programs contributed to the sense of belonging for Black male undergraduate students, emphasizing the importance of personal connections and a supportive academic environment. Addressing research question two, administrators navigated challenges through three key themes: (1) creating and executing strategies for financial resource management, (2) navigating staff and personnel management, and (3) managing the evaluation processes, sharing stories, and aligning with institutional goals. These themes unveiled the varied approaches employed by program administrators to address challenges and enhance the effectiveness of their mentorship programs. Exploring the implications of the findings, administrators demonstrated adaptability and resilience in integrating mentorship programs into institutional structures. The emergence of engaging activities and understanding program origins as crucial elements underscored administrators' ability to seamlessly align programs with institutional goals. Challenges were effectively addressed through adept financial resource management, strategic personnel navigation, and a commitment to storytelling, thus reinforcing institutional alignment. Four recommendations emerged from the findings. Recommendation one advocates for prioritizing the hiring of culturally competent staff sensitive to the unique challenges faced by Black male students and emphasizing the need for ongoing training. Recommendation two stresses the importance of establishing clear and measurable program goals, providing a roadmap for success, and enabling outcome assessment. Recommendation three encourages institutions to customize mentoring programs to meet the specific needs of their campus sizes and communities. Recommendation four underscores the need for individualized resource allocation for Black male mentorship programs. In conclusion, this research contributes valuable insights into the significance of Black male mentorship programs at PWIs, shedding light on their positive impact while addressing challenges. The recommendations offer a roadmap for institutions to enhance these programs, ultimately fostering a sense of belonging and academic success for Black male students in higher education.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Education.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 4, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Cameron Beatty, Professor Directing Dissertation; Robert Eklund, University Representative; Toby Park-Gaghan, Committee Member; Annie Wofford, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001254">
      <mods:topic>Educational leadership</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Lovett_fsu_0071E_18538</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Education</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
