<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>School Principals' Perceptions</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Factors That Influence School-Based Leader Retention</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0006-0454-0073</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">McDaid</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Rebecca A.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n97036418">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Herrington</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Carolyn D.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n81065572">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Berry</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Frances Stokes</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2002112925">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Milligan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jeffrey Ayala</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2005077563">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Rutledge</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Stacey A.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (99 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Problem of Practice: School principals have a powerful effect on student achievement, school culture, and teacher turnover. According to the National Association of Secondary School Principals (2020), the average career of a school principal is four years, and one in five school principals leave their schools annually. These numbers are even greater in more challenging schools with high numbers of minority students, English Language Learners, and students living in poverty. These students need the most experienced school principals, yet they often end up with the newest and least experienced. Even more alarming is that results from a recent survey conducted jointly by NASSP and the Learning Policy Institute (LPI) in 2020 indicated that 42% of school principals were considering leaving their position. This exploratory qualitative research study answers the following research question: The purpose of this study is to answer the following research question: What has motivated school principals to remain in school-level leadership? The study focuses on gaining the perspectives of principals on factors influencing school-based leaders to remain in their positions. Motivation and retention of current school leaders is critical to student growth and success, overall school achievement, and retention of school educators at all levels. This study will add to the current body of research focused on development and support of school leaders to positively impact school principal perseverance and retention. Methods Semi-structured interviews and coding methods have been used to organize and analyze outcomes effectively without losing the individuality of the participants' responses. Ten principals participated in semi-structured interviews. The stratified and purposeful sample included both males and females, principals at all K-12 levels, Title I and non-Title I schools, and urban and suburban schools. Data Analysis First cycle descriptive coding using a priori codes in conjunction with in vivo coding outcomes and second cycle coding outcomes were charted to identify dominant codes: Relevant Preparation, Relevant Experience, Relationships with Staff, the Participants' Perception of the Role/Feelings About the Role, Passion for Helping Others, Internal Drive, Future Role, Informal Collaboration with Peers, and the Mentor/Mentee Relationship. Code outcomes were clustered based on commonality. Six overarching themes emerged and were named: External Validation, Collaboration, Preparation and Support, Future Plans, Intrinsic Motivation, and Relationships. These themes answered the research question: What has motivated school principals to remain in school-level leadership? Recommendations Based on participant interview outcomes for this study, the following recommendations are offered. The first recommendation is to ensure that the right support is being provided to school leaders to positively impact the leader to be able to succeed within the role. The next recommendation is focused on collaboration. A focus on formal collaboration needs to shift from interaction in meetings to shadowing peers and a sharing of ideas to positively impact schools, leadership practices, and student achievement. Informal collaboration when supported and celebrated by school districts could potentially support school leaders professionally as well as emotionally which would positively impact retention rates. Next, mentor programs should be expanded to include both internal and external relationships. For mentoring programs to be most impactful on the decision-making of school principals, evaluation or fear of retribution should be removed, and this often results from an external match. Additionally, it is critical to establish and encourage a pipeline of leaders within a school district to ensure a continual pool of qualified leaders prepared to support and lead schools. All school districts and current leaders should identify and tap potential leaders and provide effective professional development, encouragement, and mentorship to develop leadership skills. Creating a pipeline of educators at all levels positively impacts students, schools, and school districts as a whole. Finally, salaries should increase to compensate school leaders fairly and adequately. Conclusion Addressing this research question provides answers and informs practice to improve formal and informal learning opportunities for school principals in an effort to address principal turnover rates. Ensuring that the right learning opportunities and supportive measures are in place are of the utmost importance to increase longevity of school leaders in their role to ultimately positively impact student achievement, increase teacher retention, and positively impact the climate and culture of a school community. Based on the perceptions of current school principals in this study, 6 themes have emerged from the data: External Validation, Collaboration, Preparation &amp; Support, Future Plans, Intrinsic Motivation, and Relationships. Each plays an important role in developing and supporting school leaders. The combination of these supports and opportunities increases school principal perseverance and retention in their school-based leader role.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Education.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">January 29, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Leader Persistence, Principal Retention, School Based Leader Persistence, School Principal Retention, School-Based Leader Retention, School-Based Principals</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Carolyn Herrington, Professor Directing Dissertation; Frances Berry, University Representative; Jeffrey Milligan, Committee Member; Stacey Rutledge, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001254">
      <mods:topic>Educational leadership</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85118362">
      <mods:topic>School management and organization</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989">
      <mods:topic>Education</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">McDaid_fsu_0071E_18468</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Education</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
