<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Psychological and Social Outcomes of Physical Activity among Children, Adolescents, and Adults with Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD)</title>
      <subTitle>A Systematic Review and Metaanalysis</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0002-6308-6369</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Oh</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Seyoon</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kamy">
      <namePart type="family">Kim</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Amy C. H. (Amy Chan Hyung)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jdu3">
      <namePart type="family">Du</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">James</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/hxue2">
      <namePart type="family">Xue</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Hanhan</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Sport Management</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (167 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) is defined as "a complex developmental condition involving persistent challenges with social communication, restricted interests, and repetitive behavior" (American Psychiatric Association, 2013). The prevalence of ASD has been identified regardless of ethnic, racial, and socioeconomic status, and the prevalence rates of ASD population have increased continuously (Dietz et al., 2020; Maenner et al., 2023). Although there is no specific curative treatment for people with ASD (Shenoy et al., 2017), physical activity is known to be beneficial in alleviating the symptoms of extensive comorbidities, chronic diseases, depression, and anxiety among people with ASD (Sefen et al., 2020). Also, physical activity is treated as a cost-effective treatment compared to other treatments or therapies, being more affordable and versatile for people with ASD, reducing the burden of expenditures on healthcare utilization (Chan et al., 2020; Vohra et al., 2017). However, people with ASD had lower participation rates in physical activity compared to the general population due to the high existence of social and environmental barriers (Arkesteyn et al., 2023). For this study, a systematic review and meta-analysis were used to visit the current body of literature and address the research questions. Systematic review is the process of identification and evaluation of data from primary databases to the pre-defined research question based on the eligibility criteria (Pollock &amp; Berge, 2018). Meta-analysis is a statistical method to synthesize the data from a systematic review to calculate the effect size based on the mean and variance of population effects from various studies identified with the same research question (Field and Gillett, 2010). Ten major databases, including APA PsycINFO, SPORTDiscus with Full Text, EMBASE, Medline (PubMed), Cochrane Library, PubMed (NLM), APA PsycArticles, CINAHL, ERIC (ProQuest), and Applied Social Sciences Index and Abstracts (ASSIA) were used to search and extract the previous studies. For the methodological results, a total of 81 articles were included in the systematic review after the screening process. The Mixed Methods Appraisal Tool (MMAT) was used to assess the quality of the research. 81 studies were included as the final results, with none excluded based on the quality assessment results (Hong et al., 2018). The quantitative design studies used for the meta-analysis data evaluated the risk of bias with the Effective Public Health Practice Project (EPHPP) Quality Assessment Tool (Effective Public Health Practice Project, 2009) under the weak, moderate, and strong rating. A total of 46 studies with 46 independent samples, including 865 participants, qualified for the overall inclusion criteria for the meta-analysis. Comprehensive Meta-Analysis (CMA) version 4 and Jamovi version 2.5 software were used to calculate the effect size in Hedge's g (Borenstein et al., 2021). The meta-analysis results were reported with statistical results, funnel plots, and forest plots. The psychological and social outcomes of different physical activity modes (i.e., unorganized physical activity, exercise, and sport) and different age brackets (i.e., children, adolescents, and adults) were found in the systematic review. The psychological and social outcomes of unorganized physical activity were the development of social communication, relationship, responsiveness, attachment behavior, cooperation, trust, social effectiveness, quality of life, receptive language skills, communicative language skills, socialization skills, individual self-esteem, confidence, positive self-perception, emotional response, great fun along with diminished stress and antisocial stereotypic behavior. Improved social interaction, adaptive behavior, social motivation, coordination, affective engagement, interaction quality, social communication, peer relations, verbal communication abilities, positive emotional expression, emotional inference, self-calmness and reduced level of stereotyped behaviors, sadness, anger, anxiety, fear, social withdrawal, and maladaptive behavior were reported as the psychological and social outcomes of exercise. Sport participation positively impacted relationship skills, social interactions, communication, emotional responses, self-esteem, self-competence, self-awareness, perceived competence, enjoyment, emotional exertion, and alleviation of anxiety, depressive symptoms, and negative emotional responses. The psychological and social outcomes of physical activity among children were reported in enhanced communication, socialization skills, verbal language skills, verbal and non-verbal communication skills, turn-taking skills, interpersonal skills, social reciprocity, and social effectiveness. Also, children experienced reduced socially maladaptive behavior, stereotyped behavior, antisocial behavior, sadness, anger, anxiety, fear, aggression, affect states, and depressive symptoms. Adolescents aged between 14 and 17 years old had positive outcomes in developing psychosocial well-being, self-calming, and socially targeted skills, including eye contact, contributing relevant information, and turn-taking skills. Adults were found to have a higher quality of life, psychological well-being, enhanced intrapersonal factors (i.e., self-concept, belief, and development history), interpersonal relationships (i.e., family systems, friends, acquaintances, and social groups), enjoyment, perceived exertion, affective engagement, competence, self-esteem, confidence, self-perception, mood, and emotional inference. The direction of the overall effect size of physical activity was positive (65%) with a small effect size (g=0.157). The direction of effect size in all different modes of physical activity, including unorganized physical activity (80%), exercise (65%), and sport (71%), were positive. In the comparison of different modes of physical activity, the unorganized physical activity had the largest effect size (g=0.379), and the smallest effect size was found in the exercise (g=0.086). Due to the limited calculable data among the final results, no study was included as the meta-analysis data for the adolescents. The effect size direction of children was majorly positive (62%), while the adult direction had a negative direction (67%). In the comparison of different age brackets (children and adults), the adults (g=0.464) were reported to have a larger effect size than the children (g=0.0016). The current study examined physical activity's psychological and social outcomes among children, adolescents, and adults with ASD using systematic review and meta-analysis. From the comparison of different modes of physical activity, unorganized physical activity can be an effective method resulting in positive psychological and social outcomes due to the less competition and regulations characteristics of participation (Arkesteyn et al., 2023). Even though the effectiveness of physical activity among the adult population was reported, the study still targeted super-aged adults who are over 70 (Suzuki, 2018), as well as adolescents, and it needs to be developed in the future. Considering the effectiveness of integration in various measurements and study designs, future studies need to conduct meta-analysis in specific pre-post design studies in which both comparative and treatment groups exist.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Sport Management in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Science.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 27, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Amy Chan Hyung Kim, Professor Directing Thesis; Wenjie James Du, Committee Member; Hanhan Xue, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126896">
      <topic>Sports administration</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Oh_fsu_0071N_19016</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Science</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Sport Management</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
