<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Composing Commitment</title>
      <subTitle>Diversity Statements on the Writing Studies Job Market</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0004-5872-0753</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Orchard</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Amory</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2010050868">
      <namePart type="family">Neal</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michael R.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jproffitt">
      <namePart type="family">Proffitt</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jennifer M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2015038714">
      <namePart type="family">Lathan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Rhea Estelle</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1961-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2010004120">
      <namePart type="family">Domínguez Barajas</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Elías</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1968-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of English</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (205 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>Over the years, writing studies scholarship on academic labor has focused primarily on the effects of neoliberalism's effects on the academy (Carter; Hendricks; Kahn and Pason; Scott; Winslow), especially for non-tenured employees (Connors; Doe; Hansel and Baird Giordano; Hansen; Horner; Klausman; Mechenbier; Penrose; Sledd; Taylor et al.). However, there has been a shift to study how other academics navigate their careers by studying emotion/emotional labor (Caswell et al.; Geller and Denny; Micciche) and the experiences of graduate students (Edgington and Taylor; Miller; Mountford). That said, with the exception of Carmen Kynard's, Craig Lamont's, and Staci M. Perryman-Clark's work, academic labor scholarship doesn't extensively connect the concept of "advocacy" while also considering facets of workers' identity (e.g., ability, race, gender, and sexuality). Studying professional documents can provide valuable insights into how individuals in the field of program administration identify themselves as teachers, scholars, and administrators. These documents, which include curriculum vitae, teaching philosophies, administrative vision statements, and research statements, are frequently requested when applying for jobs and are used to create a job applicant's dossier. In other words, more work should be done to answer this question: "How do professionals advocate for their stakeholders (i.e. students, colleagues, community members) from within their own positionalities in terms of academic job status (i.e. tenured or non-tenured) and (un)marked identities (i.e. race, ethnicity sexuality, gender status)? I argue that one way to fill this gap is by studying professional documents like diversity statements. The purpose of this study is to provide insight into writing studies professionals' experiences encountering job market diversity statements. This was a necessary measure if I wanted to assemble best practices on this specific writing task once the data collection and analysis was completed. On a broader scale, I hope to expand the current knowledge of how the field of writing studies—as a scholarly and praxis-driven discipline— conceptualizes commitments to diversity, equity, and inclusion across various job types. These include teaching, but also administration, scholarship, and service to the profession. As such, my research questions aim at identifying the ways my interview and survey participants (writers and readers of diversity statements): a)define each of the following terms: diversity, equity, and inclusion; b) articulate their understanding of a diversity statement's task and purpose; c) identify and reflect on the choices writers and readers make, including what writers include in their statements and the rationales they provide for these choices. To answer these questions, I employed thematic analysis to identify commonalities and differences between my participants' varied interactions with diversity statements. From these methods, I was able to make several tentative findings and point towards implications and further areas of study. Drawing from this data, this study assembles participants' recommended best practices for writing and reviewing diversity statements. It offers two contributions to the discipline. First, it provides a current portrait of what kinds of theories, actions, and values get highlighted in diversity statements. Second, I invite conversations about how employees throughout varied scholarly disciplines and job titles in higher education should use the diversity statement to take action against power structures that cause injustice to our students, colleagues, and communities.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of English in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 21, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">academic job market, academic labor, diversity statement, genre, writing studies</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Michael Neal, Professor Directing Dissertation; Jennifer Proffitt, University Representative; Rhea Estelle Lathan, Committee Member; Elias Domínguez Barajas, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113628">
      <topic>Rhetoric</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Orchard_fsu_0071E_18951</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>English</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
