<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Understanding the Evolution of Carriers in Tin Cadmium Oxide Ternary Plasmonic Nanocrystals</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0008-1251-6801</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Ortega</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Raul Eduardo</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/strouse">
      <namePart type="family">Strouse</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Geoffrey F.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/woates">
      <namePart type="family">Oates</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">William</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kghanson">
      <namePart type="family">Hanson</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kenneth G.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rschurko">
      <namePart type="family">Schurko</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Robert W.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (141 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>This dissertation focuses on understanding the plasmonic properties of novel transparent conductive oxides (TCOs), more specifically the family of binary and ternary Sn-Cd-O containing materials. The first chapter introduces the background, fundamental knowledge, concepts, and techniques necessary for the understanding and study of the localized surface plasmon resonances (LSPRs) in nanocrystals (NCs). The second chapter introduces the novel synthesis of a well-faceted cadmium stannate (CTO) inverse spinel plasmonic semiconductor nanocrystals (PSNCs). The use of Sn(II) in the colloidal reaction for CTO results in reproducible octahedral PSNCs. Correlating extinction spectra with magnetic circular dichroism allows the calculation of carrier density and carrier effective mass. 113Cd and 119Sn solid-state NMR (SSNMR) experiments show clear evidence of metallic-like carriers in CTO NCs based upon the observation of Knight shifts (KS). These data suggest that carrier formation in CTO arises from Sn antisite occupation of octahedral Cd sites (SnCd). From a broader perspective, the results point to wide band gap spinels as being an important but understudied class of plasmonic PSNCs. The third chapter studies the evolution of the carrier properties in the Sn-Cd-O system. The defect evolution from an oxygen vacancy (VO) to an antisite (M'M) is underexplored and the nature of the optical properties from different types of defects is not fully understood. This Sn-Cd-O family provides the perfect system to study these changes. The evolution of the structure and optoelectronic properties is investigated through powder x-ray diffraction (pXRD), NMR, and electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR), and femtosecond (fs) transient absorption (TA). The fourth chapter tries to understand the annealing effects on the plasmonic properties of CTO. Annealing is a physical process in which a material is heat up at a specific temperature for a certain amount of time to "anneal" crystallographic defects such as VO, metal vancancies (VM), and metal interstitials (Mi). This happens because atoms diffuse through the crystal during the annealing process, which allows for recrystallization of the crystal lattice into a more "perfect" configuration. Annealing as a technique has a rich history in metallurgy, solid state materials, and thin-film fields. The fifth chapter explores the optical properties of CTO made from SnF2 instead of SnOAc2. By employing a tin(II) fluoride source instead of the acetate, there are significant improvements to frequency of the LSPR, the Q-factor, NMR Knight-shift, and hot carrier dynamics of the final FCTO product. These observations demonstrate significant improvements to the optoelectronic properties by virtue of having an effective mass one order of magnitude lower than the one measured in CTO. Finally, chapter 6 explores some of the future work and some of the relevant questions that are still of much interest to the plasmonic field. These topics present exciting opportunities for future students and researchers to explore.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 1, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">antisite, high mobility, nano, nanomaterial, plasmon, transparent conductive oxide</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Geoffrey F. Strouse, Professor Directing Dissertation; William Oates, University Representative; Kenneth Hanson, Committee Member; Robert W. Schurko, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022986">
      <topic>Chemistry</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Ortega_fsu_0071E_18970</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Chemistry and Biochemistry</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
