<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Ambiguity, Fines, and Social Distance</title>
      <subTitle>Experiments inside and Outside the Lab</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0005-9986-8225</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Ortolani</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Luke R.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2010073490">
      <namePart type="family">Isaac</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">R. Mark (Robert Mark)</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1954-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2017125777">
      <namePart type="family">Blay</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Allen D.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1970-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lboosey">
      <namePart type="family">Boosey</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Luke A.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lprodgers">
      <namePart type="family">Rodgers</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Luke P.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Economics</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (111 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>This dissertation is composed of three studies that take place both inside and outside the lab. Chapter 1 is a laboratory experiment based off of Gneezy and Rustichini's Isreali day care center field experiment and Kornhauser, Lu, and Tontrop's lab experiment. Using Kornhauser et al.'s set up we study whether or not ambiguity of punishment could be a mechanism driving results seen in the original day care center study. We find that subjects are indeed ambiguity averse, but also, more notably that the set up for Kornhauser et al, may not fully capture Gneezy and Rustichini's environment in a lab setting. We find evidence that the real effort task has a trade off between effort and performance. The more effort subjects put into the task, the worse they perform, something not seen in the original day care center study. We also notice that subjects may try harder when there are fewer subjects in the room, something explored further in Chapter 3. Besides the unintended trade off between effort and performance, we do see evidence that as ambiguity of punishment increases, so does performance. These results do not rule out ambiguity of punishment as a possible mechanism for Gneezy and Rustichini's day care center experiment where they proposed ambiguous punishments, or a possible incidence of moral crowding out driving behavior. Chapter 2 is a natural experiment using real world data collected from the University libraries of Florida Atlantic University, Florida International University, Florida State University, the University of Florida, and the University of South Florida to test if moral crowding out might impact book borrowing behavior. On July 1st, 2015 FSU became the first school within the sample to stop the collection of daily late fees. Using this as a natural experiment we are able to estimate the effect that daily late fees have on book returns using a difference-in-differences model. We find that books were returned roughly 2-3 days earlier without late fees, contrary to the deterrence hypothesis. This shows that moral obligation may be a mechanism behind returning books on time, and daily late fees may crowd out moral motivation and increase late returns. We are also able to estimate the effect that increasing the base borrowing period length has on late returns. we find that patrons hold books for about 50\% of the loan period, thus, increasing loan lengths does increase the amount of time a book is held, but crucially, it also decreases late returns. Chapter 3 is a laboratory experiment motivated by a result seen in the first chapter where sessions with fewer subjects seemed to outperform sessions with more subjects. In this study we test whether physical distance in the lab impacts social distance in three canonical economic games. Round 1 is a four person one-shot linear MPCR public goods game, round 2 is a dictator game, and round 3 is a trust game. The treatments vary the number of subjects in each session (4 vs 16) and the physical distance between subjects in small sessions (far apart vs close together). We find no statistical difference of average contributions in the Far treatment comparing high and low MPCR sub-treatments. We also find significant differences in behaviors in dictator games and trust games. Dictators tend to give more in smaller sessions closer together, supporting the hypothesis that physical distance can impact social distance. In the trust game subjects in smaller closer sessions tended to ensure equity of earnings between partners more often than in larger sessions. These results show that subtle changes in laboratory settings may play a more important role in lab experiments than previously thought.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Economics in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 1, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">ambiguity, economics, experimental, fine, library, price</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Robert Mark Isaac, Professor Directing Dissertation; Allen Blay, University Representative; Luke Boosey, Committee Member; Luke Rodgers, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040850">
      <topic>Economics</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Ortolani_fsu_0071E_18979</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Economics</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
