<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Reimagining 'Bodywork' in the Wake</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>A Collection of Black Queer, Transgender, and Nonbinary Body Autonomy Oral Testimonies</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0125-7564</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Rochon</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Monica A.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2011019943">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Newman</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Joshua I.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1976-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2013033964">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Dowell</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kristin L.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2004110130">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Giardina</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Michael D.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1976-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kamy">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kim</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Amy C. H. (Amy Chan Hyung)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Sport Management</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (216 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Black queer, transgender, and nonbinary (BQTN) people are among the most vulnerable populations in the United States due to structural racialized and gender discrimination (Clifton, 2021). In the United States, civil and human rights protections for lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, queer, asexual, and intersex (LGBTQAI+) people have historically been politically and culturally contested within sport and physical culture studies. As a bodyworker and insider to the queer and trans community, I am choosing to use oral history interviews to explore the liberatory bodywork spaces created by and for BQTN bodyworkers in the Southeastern United States. Liberatory bodywork is an expression of various modalities of physical and/or energetic techniques working with the human body for individual and collective transformation and freedom praxis. Liberatory bodywork recognizes the ongoing anti-Black violence and colonialism on our physical beings. Through liberatory bodywork, physical activity, and embodied movement is practiced and taught with an explicit recognition and reverence for the land, participants lived experiences, and personal and collective commitments to freedom. Moreover, liberatory bodywork invites scholars and community members into integrative approaches to understanding human and non-human relations as emancipatory sites and interventions into the ongoing harm of structural oppression. Though gender identity is not documented in the U.S. Census, the estimated population size of transgender individuals has been collected through national population surveys and has significantly increased over the last decade (Meerwijk &amp; Sevellius, 2017). In 2016, the Williams Institute estimated that 1.4 million adults identify as transgender, and more recently in 2021, more than 1.2 million LGBTQ adults identify as nonbinary. Yet, in June 2021, the United States introduced (over thirty states to date) record-breaking anti-transgender legislation, focused specifically on eliminating sport participation and gender-affirming healthcare for transgender and nonbinary people (Mosier, 2022). In response to the state's discriminatory measures, individuals and groups at the local, state-wide, and national levels have organized in the fight for transgender rights, affirming healthcare, and sports participation. Federal and state anti-transgender sport and healthcare legislative policies are predicated on the structural erasure of transgender people resulting from Western colonial constructs such as gender, race, and sexual orientation hierarchies (Carrington &amp; McDonald 2009; Travers, 2008; White et al. 1995). These value systems permeate institutional practices that reproduce regulatory policies regarding sex, gender identity, and expression by categorizing their cultural acceptability exclusively on a binary basis (Travers, 2008). Further, such laws and regulations become an impetus for further material conditions and symbolic violence that decrease and severely restrict access to basic resources such as housing, healthcare, employment, education, sport, and recreation, to name some (Johnson et al., 2020). The deliberate practice of systemic oppression compounds historical and generational traumas endangering the livelihood and well-being of BQTN people. Such corporealized harm is somaticized and lives inside of physical material bodies, contributing to the shortening of BQTN people's lives. The immense amount of stress caused by the struggle to simply survive is a great barrier to health and vitality. Consequently, BQTN communities need resources that contribute to both understanding and addressing the oppressive conditions that restrain access to embodied healing resources, which can alleviate individual and collective harm. Accordingly, this dissertation explores the ways that BQTN bodyworkers in the Southeastern United States navigate sport and physical cultural spaces, in turn, by generating ontological spaces of liberatory bodywork and resisting normative (and oppressive) practices of bodywork. Throughout this process, I draw from the Sankofa tradition, politically engaged sport sociology, and physical cultural studies (PCS) literature. My research study is important because BQTN people have been strategically and systemically disembodied by governmental policies, public discourse, everyday practices, and incomprehensible violence. Further, the dominant hegemonic culture in institutionalized sporting spaces compounds this harm. Consequently, this dissertation confronts racialized and gendered discrimination that leads to the erasure of BQTN people. Despite the social reproduction of power relations that erase BQTN people, we still exist and in particular claim our existence within sport and physical culture. These liberatory and life-affirming bodywork communities do exist and play an important part in BQTN's struggles for body autonomy and self-determination.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Sport Management in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 20, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Bodywork, Cultural body, Liberatory, Oral Histories, Queer, Trans</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Joshua I. Newman, Professor Directing Dissertation; Kristin L. Dowell, University Representative; Michael Giardina, Committee Member; Amy C. H. Kim, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126896">
      <mods:topic>Sports administration</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001992">
      <mods:topic>African Americans</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Study and teaching</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004003385">
      <mods:topic>Sexual minorities</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Rochon_fsu_0071E_18111</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Sport Management</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
