<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Nucleosome Distribution and Sensitivity Dynamics Characterize the Functional Genome in Infection and Disease</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-5372-7973</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Rubel Hoq</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Mohammad</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="viaf"
              authorityURI="http://viaf.org/viaf/"
              valueURI="http://viaf.org/viaf/171975698">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Dennis</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jonathan Hancock</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mroper">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Roper</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Michael Gabriel</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nb2012004932">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Bass</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Hank W.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/gerickson">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Erickson</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Gregory M.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/thoupt">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Houpt</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Thomas A.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Biological Science</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (118 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>The 6.8 billion base pairs of human DNA must be packaged into chromatin to fit into the nucleus. The nucleosome, approximately 150 bp of genomic DNA wrapped 1.65 times around the histone octamer, is the fundamental unit of chromatin. While this organization likely evolved for packaging, it has been co-opted for regulatory processes. All cells undergo DNA-templated processes such as transcription, recombination, replication, and DNA damage repair. Therefore, the nucleosome architecture must be remodeled to provide access to the underlying genome. Assessment of nucleosomal dynamics in response to certain stimuli reveals the genomic loci that play a role in response to that stimulus. Classically nucleosomal dynamics are assessed by MNase mapping of nucleosome occupancy. MNase digests the internucleosomal linker DNA leaving only nucleosomally protected DNA. Sequencing nucleosomally protected fragments and mapping their genomic location suggests nucleosome locations. One longstanding expectation has been that nucleosome occupancy should be fundamentally different in cell types with different physiologies. Surprisingly, our lab has discovered that disparate cell lines have fundamentally similar basal nucleosome occupancy. We showed that nucleosome occupancy changes only transiently in response to a stimulus returning to basal positions on a timeframe commensurate with the response. The transient nature of these occupancy changes shifted the perspective on studies of chromatin structure and suggested that future studies of nucleosome occupancy dynamics should include high-resolution temporal analysis. More recently, we demonstrated that nucleosomes in their basal positions differ in their sensitivity to MNase, with some locations readily digested with relatively low concentrations of MNase, and others requiring higher concentrations of MNase to be digested. The works presented here used these two analyses, occupancy, and sensitivity, to identify distinctly different features of the functional genome. The present research focused on two disease models using a model of the Kaposi sarcoma herpes virus (KSHV) reactivation and an immortalized cell line from a Cockayne syndrome patient. For each of these models, we have identified transient changes in nucleosome occupancy with temporally resolved MNase mapping. Additionally, we have identified longer-lasting nucleosomal changes with MNase sensitivity. KSHV is a gamma herpes virus that is responsible for the oncogenic transformation of infected cells. We used an inducible system to reactivate KSHV, which simulates the lytic cycle of the virus life cycle and is eventually responsible for oncogenic transformation. We measured nucleosome occupancy at 0, 12, 24, 36, and 48 hours after reactivation. We observed changes in nucleosome occupancy at the -1 nucleosome at loci important for viral reactivation and oncogenic transformation, such as the AKT2, PRCC, and CDC6 genes. These loci are enriched for MAZ, PATZ1, WT1, KLF15, EGR2, E2F, and PBX3 transcription factor binding sites (TFBS). These TFBS are consistent with responses regulating cell growth, proliferation, and oncogenesis. Our nucleosome sensitivity studies revealed persistent changes at loci important in nuclear transport, signal transduction, and oncogenesis, including TPR and TRAF6. We identified TFBS for factors that regulate oncogenesis, including WT1, MAZ, KLF12, PATZ2, and E2E4. We conclude that occupancy and sensitivity studies provide distinct and biologically important aspects of the functional genome. Cockayne syndrome B is a progressive autosomal recessive developmental disorder resulting from mutations in the CSB protein. CSB plays multifaceted cellular functions. CSB plays a role in chromatin remodeling, transcription-coupled nucleotide excision repair (TC-NER), and oxidative DNA damage repair. We measured nucleosome occupancy in a CSBnull cell line and a CSBWT cell line. We observed changes in nucleosome occupancy at the -1 position in genes that contribute to the neuroactive ligand-receptor interaction and hippo signaling pathways. These loci are important in neurological development and organ size development, two important aspects of Cockayne syndrome B. We also observed that these loci are enriched for TFBS that have a role in DNA damage response, DNA repair, and development. Our nucleosome sensitivity studies revealed changes at loci, including NEIL2, which is important in base-excision pathways. Interestingly we identified different classes of TFBS in the sensitivity analysis. These TFBS included ZIC2, ZIC3, TBX1, and TBX15 and are involved in neurogenesis, bone, and cartilage formation. We conclude that occupancy and sensitivity studies provide distinct and biologically important aspects of the functional genome. In conclusion, we surmise that nucleosome occupancy and sensitivity can detect two levels of change in nucleosome architecture. Nucleosome occupancy changes are transient and happen in disease-specific genes and global genes, which are common to other genes. Nucleosomes with changes in sensitivity to MNase represent more persistent changes and occur in the genes which are more disease-specific.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Biological Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 12, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Chromatin, Cockayne syndrome B, Kaposi sarcoma herpesvirus, Nucleosome, Occupancy, Sensitivity</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jonathan H. Dennis, Professor Directing Dissertation; Michael G. Roper, University Representative; Hank W. Bass, Committee Member; Gregory M. Erickson, Committee Member; Thomas A. Houpt, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086577">
      <mods:topic>Molecular biology</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00003585">
      <mods:topic>Bioinformatics</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014203">
      <mods:topic>Biology</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">RubelHoq_fsu_0071E_18207</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Biological Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
