<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Theory and Evaluation of Undergraduate Stem Education Interventions</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-0792-9256</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Šaras</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Emily Daina</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kreynolds3">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Reynolds</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">John K.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lperezfelkner">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Perez-Felkner</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Lara</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/abarrett">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Barrett</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Anne E.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1971-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/sbuggs">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Buggs</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Shantel</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Sociology</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (213 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>The United States higher education system has developed strategies to prepare students for Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math (STEM) careers as the STEM labor market expands. One set of educational interventions, known as STEM Intervention Programs (SIPs), employs extracurricular activities to engage and retain STEM major students. These SIPs often target underrepresented racial-ethnic minority (URM) students, low-income students, and women to reduce social disparities in STEM education. However, studies assessing the effectiveness of SIPs in improving STEM retention, graduation, and career outcomes have produced inconsistent results. Another area of racial-ethnic inequality in STEM education is the faculty roster, particularly in terms of representation, hiring, and promotion practices. Increasing the number of URM STEM faculty members addresses two main issues: equitable representation and providing URM STEM students with race-matched instruction, mentorship, and role models. Extracurricular SIPs and Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion (DEI) hiring initiatives for URM STEM faculty are common strategies for promoting racial-ethnic equity in STEM education. However, these efforts, along with other DEI campaigns, have shown limited success in improving academic experiences and outcomes for marginalized groups, including URM STEM students. Some of the implicit bias in STEM education can be categorized as institutional racism, which is perpetuated through the policies, practices, and structural elements of organizations. These institutional features create barriers for URM STEM scholars and faculty during their education, hiring, and promotion, limiting race-matched learning opportunities for URM STEM undergraduates. This dissertation seeks to advance the literature by investigating the relationship between institutional racism and SIPs: does underrepresentation of Black and Hispanic/Latino STEM faculty undercut the intended benefits of SIPs on academic and career outcomes of URM participants? Using a quantitative research design, this study examines the impact of SIPs and the underrepresentation of URM STEM faculty on individual and cohort outcomes. Analyzing institutional datasets of three complete, consecutive cohorts of undergraduates from a predominantly white higher education institution, this study examines how SIP participation and URM faculty exposure relate to the success of URM STEM students. As previous research has found the long-term benefits of SIP participation to partially depend on other student characteristics and experiences, the present study also explores whether the benefits of URM-targeted SIPs differ from other SIPs and how these benefits compare with exposure to URM faculty in the classroom. I analyzed how these practices and their associated outcomes relate to the persistence of institutional racism in STEM education. To contextualize and validate the quantitative findings, I triangulated my findings with my advisor and committee members with substantive expertise, teasing out the details and broader meanings of the quantitative results. Ultimately, the strongest positive relationships observed between inputs and desired STEM graduation outcomes was between URM STEM faculty exposure and timely STEM graduation. Increasing URM STEM faculty exposure may improve timely graduation outcomes, reduce student loan debt, and prepare URM STEM graduates for the workforce. In contrast, high-cost extracurricular programming may not move the needle URM STEM students' graduation goals. In sum, this case study provides insights into the limited benefits of programs that many universities have implemented to retain URM STEM students and interprets those lackluster results as demonstrating the key tenet of Critical Race Theory known as "interest convergence."</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Sociology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 1, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">critical race theory, diversity equity and inclusion, interest convergence, race-matched teaching, STEM education, STEM intervention programs</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">John Reynolds, Professor Directing Dissertation; Lara Perez-Felkner, University Representative; Anne Barrett, Committee Member; Shantel Buggs, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124200">
      <mods:topic>Sociology</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Saras_fsu_0071E_18592</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Sociology</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
