<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Teacher Beliefs about Mathematics Teaching and Learning and Classroom Achievement Growth</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0001-8171-8457</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Schultz</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Heather A.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2003057796">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Akiba</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Motoko</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/stibi">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Tibi</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Sana</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/piatarola">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Iatarola</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Patrice</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/eharbatkin">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Harbatkin</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Erica</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (92 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>The study conducted in Dolphin County School District offers a comprehensive exploration of teacher beliefs among K-8 educators, specifically focusing on perspectives related to mathematics instruction. The findings reveal a diverse array of beliefs, shedding light on nuanced aspects of transmissionist, facts-first, and fixed instructional plan beliefs. An examination of background characteristics and their relationship with teacher beliefs emphasizes the intricate nature of these beliefs within the teaching community. The study identifies a weak connection, highlighting the diverse array of perspectives held by educators. Factors such as gender, race, and teaching experience contribute to this complexity, emphasizing the need for a nuanced understanding of the interplay of these factors in shaping teacher perspectives on mathematics education. Professional development emerges as a crucial factor influencing teacher beliefs. However, the study reveals a lack of statistically significant correlations between professional development and teacher beliefs. This calls for a critical reevaluation of existing professional development initiatives, urging the district to ensure their content aligns effectively with instructional practices that enhance mathematics education. The multiple regression analysis accentuates the substantial impact of teacher beliefs on average classroom math score growth. Teachers endorsing traditional approaches are associated with lower student performance, while those embracing more progressive beliefs exhibit a positive influence. Notably, overall teacher beliefs wield a particularly strong influence on student outcomes, emphasizing the significance of fostering innovative and student-centered approaches to teaching mathematics. While the study acknowledges the existence of conflicting research, particularly concerning culturally relevant beliefs, it underscores the need for a more extensive study dedicated to beliefs about the teaching and learning of mathematics. This recognition of the complexity of teacher beliefs aligns with the observations made by Beswick (2007), emphasizing the necessity for a more in-depth understanding of these intricate aspects. In response to these findings, several recommendations are proposed for Dolphin County School District. Firstly, a thorough evaluation and refinement of professional development programs are essential to ensure their efficacy in shaping teacher beliefs. Internal examinations of belief consistency, encouragement of curriculum flexibility, and initiatives promoting innovative teaching approaches are prioritized to foster a cohesive instructional culture. Additionally, the district is encouraged to actively support a culture of continuous learning and collaboration among teachers through communities of practice. By implementing these recommendations, Dolphin County School District can position itself as a leader in cultivating a teaching environment where beliefs align with effective instructional practices. This proactive stance is poised to enhance the quality of mathematics education within the district, ultimately resulting in positive impacts on student outcomes. The district's commitment to continuous improvement and the provision of high-quality education for all students is evident in these recommendations, reflecting its dedication to fostering an environment conducive to both teacher and student success.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Education.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">February 29, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Motoko Akiba, Professor Directing Dissertation; Sana Tibi, University Representative; Patrice Iatarola, Committee Member; Erica Harbatkin, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989">
      <mods:topic>Education</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Schultz_fsu_0071E_18515</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Education</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
