<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>6 June 2020 Western U.S. Derecho</title>
      <nonSort>The</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0007-2718-649X</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Silas</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Thomas Peter</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n81021102">
      <namePart type="family">Fuelberg</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Henry E.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rhart">
      <namePart type="family">Hart</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Robert E. (Robert Edward)</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1972-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2018001437">
      <namePart type="family">Liu</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Guosheng</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Professor of meteorology)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (66 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>This study examines a rare derecho that formed in the western United States. During the morning hours of 6 June 2020, a complex of severe thunderstorms formed in southeastern Utah. These storms organized into a northeastward-propagating line that produced severe winds over a large swath of eastern Utah, northern Colorado, eastern Wyoming, southeastern Montana, western Nebraska, western South Dakota, and southwestern North Dakota before finally weakening. The total path length was approximately 1030 km (640 mi). A total of 339 severe wind reports (67 damage and 272 measured, including 44 significant severe gusts), 12 severe hail reports ranging from 2.5 to 4.4 cm (1.00 to 1.75 in.) diameter, and 2 tornado reports related to the derecho were recorded by the Storm Prediction Center. The maximum wind report was a 49 m s-1 (96 kt) gust at Winter Park, CO. The derecho is especially notable since only two other derechos have been documented west of the Great Plains, and none have successfully crossed the Continental Divide. This research investigates the meteorological factors that contributed to the formation, persistence, and intensity of the derecho, including synoptic-scale patterns and mesoscale influences. Results show that the 6 June 2020 event was a progressive-type derecho forced primarily by an unseasonably strong shortwave trough, with an accompanying southwesterly jet stream present at mid and upper levels. A channel of low- to mid-level moisture extending northward into the Four Corners region from the subtropical Eastern Pacific also was evident. The resulting unstable and highly sheared environment was quite favorable for strong deep convection to develop over southeastern Utah. The discrete cells that initially formed quickly grew upscale into a squall line. The line propagated to the northeast across the Rocky Mountains and into the northern Great Plains during the afternoon and evening hours, passing through at least three other distinctly different environments. Over northeast Utah, northwest Colorado, and southern Wyoming, very strong shear was present, but temperatures were remarkably cool and instability was weak. Over eastern Wyoming, eastern Colorado, and western Nebraska, inverted-V soundings were commonplace with moderate instability and shear. Finally, over South Dakota and North Dakota, strong shear was accompanied by strong instability due to much higher low-level moisture. Despite these differences and the weak instability along much of the derecho's track, the derecho was able to maintain itself throughout these regions likely due to the strong shear and mid-level winds. Results suggest that downward momentum transfer from the mid- and upper-level synoptic-scale jet was likely responsible for much of the damaging winds, especially in the cooler region. Thermodynamically generated downdrafts due to evaporation of precipitation were likely important in the formation region as well as the dry region, while other mesoscale processes such as a rear inflow jet were likely important in severe wind production in the moist region.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Science.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 18, 2024.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Henry E. Fuelberg, Professor Directing Thesis; Robert E. Hart, Committee Member; Guosheng Liu, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85084334">
      <topic>Meteorology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">Silas_fsu_0071N_18862</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Science</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-10-30T13:17:45.832113-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
