<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Habitat Use and Ecological Connectivity in Imperiled, Highly Migratory Species</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Case Studies with Loggerhead Sea Turtles</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-0279-1443</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Silver-Gorges</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Ian</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/mfuentes">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Fuentes</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Mariana</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/slester">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Lester</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Sarah</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007101869">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Baco-Taylor</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Amy R. (Amy Rose)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/simona.ceriani">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Ceriani</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Simona A.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n89605460">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Chanton</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jeffrey P.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jingels">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Ingels</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jeroen</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lkomoroske">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Komoroske</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Lisa</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (147 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Characterizations of habitat use and ecological connectivity are essential components of a complete ecological understanding of any organism. Habitat use may be broadly defined as the behaviors that an animal exhibits in any scenopoetic context, while ecological connectivity comprises the multitude processes, whether spatial, geochemical, or genetic, that connect geographically discrete populations or assemblages. Such efforts are particularly important for imperiled, highly migratory species, which are typically comprised of reduced populations that exist in anthropogenically-reduced scenopoetic contexts. These species often face multiple threats with the potential to disrupt habitat use and ecological connectivity, and ensuring that these processes are preserved in these species is critical to their survival. However, these species are difficult to observe due to their vagile natures, and it is therefore difficult to holistically characterize baseline habitat use and ecological connectivity to inform conservation efforts. There is a need for research that seeks to fill in gaps in our understanding of habitat use and ecological connectivity in individual imperiled species, and that augments or develops tools to aid in these efforts, for pplications in both focal species and other imperiled species. Sea turtles (superfamily Chelonioidea) comprise seven highly-migratory imperiled species that face contemporary threats to their existence via the disruption of habitat use and ecological connectivity. Gaps in the current understanding of sea turtle habitat use and ecological connectivity include: 1) Limited knowledge of habitat use at relatively low-abundance nesting beaches; 2) Limitations of approaches used to characterize ecological connectivity between breeding and foraging areas, and to make inferences about habitat use at these areas; 3) Limited ecological knowledge of immature sea turtles; 4) Limited specific knowledge of resource use at high-use foraging areas; and 5) Lack of characterizations of genetic structuring and connectivity utilizing contemporary genetic markers. I undertook a multifaceted approach that utilized loggerhead sea turtles (Caretta caretta) as a case study to address these gaps, and to provide information to inform effective management efforts for this and other imperiled, highly-migratory species. My work took place in four parts. The first (Chapter 2) addressed gap 1 by providing an important update to knowledge of nesting abundance and hatchling productivity for an understudied population of loggerhead sea turtles in the Gulf of Mexico, and highlighting the importance of site-specific management plans for sea turtles. The second (Chapter 3) addressed x gaps 2 and 4 by investigating the relationships between epibiont assemblages and tissue stable isotopes from nesting loggerhead sea turtles, and showing that epibionts have the potential to be informative towards sea turtle foraging ecology. The third (Chapter 4) addressed gaps 3 and 4 by characterizing the isotopic niches of foraging adult and subadult loggerhead turtles and providing evidence that loggerheads exhibit intraspecific niche partitioning between adults and subadults. The fourth (Chapter 4) addressed gap 5 by analyzing genome-wide SNPs from loggerheads nesting at four genetically discrete populations in the Gulf of Mexico and providing a higher-resolution characterization of structuring and connectivity between these populations, in addition to identifying putatively informative markers for future population assignments. This work can serve as a foundation for impactful future studies into habitat use and ecological connectivity of, and the augmentation of management plans for, sea turtles and other imperiled, highly migratory species. Agencies responsible for management of nesting beaches or other reproductive units can make efforts to analyze high-resolution data on threats and productive output to inform management practices at a biologically relevant scale. Further investigations into epibionts in any host species could lead to the identification of indicator species used to determine where individuals have been prior to migration. Spatial, behavioral, and isotopic studies can help determine why and how lifestages partition their resources in loggerhead, and perhaps other species, of sea turtles. Agencies responsible for management of these assemblages can begin to account for that partitioning in management plans. Genome-wide SNPs have the potential to inform genetic structuring and connectivity and generate accurate assignments in species with metapopulation dynamics. Agencies responsible for management of imperiled marine species can take steps to ensure that existing genetic connectivity is maintained and that isolated populations receive adequate protections. Researchers can investigate dispersal, and agencies responsible for management can investigate the direct impacts of threats to specific populations, and ideally work to mitigate those threats, using genetic assignments. My work can provide impetus for these efforts to improve our knowledge of habitat use and ecological connectivity and to augment management efforts in sea turtles and other imperiled, highly-migratory species.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 22, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Mariana M.P.B. Fuentes, Professor Directing Dissertation; Sarah Lester, University Representative; Amy Baco-Taylor, Committee Member; Simona A. Ceriani, Committee Member; Jeffery Chanton, Committee Member; Jeroen Ingels, Committee Member; Lisa Komoroske, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081138">
      <mods:topic>Marine biology</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">SilverGorges_fsu_0071E_18087</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
