<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Virtuous Knowers</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>A Virtue-Theoretic Analysis of the Intersection of Doxastic Agency, Doxastic Obligations, and Doxastic Justification</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-4601-7804</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Smith</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Joseph Emmanuel</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ehinchman">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hinchman</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Edward</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88005645">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kelsay</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">John</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1953-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2008031674">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kearns</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Stephen</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1979-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/zward">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Ward</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Zina</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Philosophy</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (96 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>In this dissertation, I argue for a virtue-epistemological take on doxastic agency, doxastic reasons, doxastic obligations, and doxastic justification. After a brief introduction, in chapter 2 I argue in favor of doxastic involuntarism. I argue that, though the work of theoretical reason is to produce true beliefs, it does not do so in a way similar to how practical reason produces actions. I support this claim by focusing on the debate between doxastic voluntarists and involuntarists. I reframe this debate and then argue in favor of doxastic involuntarism, which has significant implications for theoretical reason. Many proponents of doxastic involuntarism characterize their view as one that denies that we can form beliefs at will. A sometimes-implicit assumption is that the formation of a belief is something that could, in principle, be an action. Their reason for why we cannot form beliefs at will is that there are various obstacles that impede us performing such an action. In contrast, I characterize the dispute between doxastic voluntarists and involuntarists as a dispute over whether the formation of a belief is an action, not over whether it is an action we can perform. I present an understanding of the nature of belief that implies that the formation of a belief is never an action. I use this characterization of the nature of belief in an argument in favor of doxastic involuntarism. In chapter 3, I argue for a new understanding of reasons for belief and doxastic obligations. I argue that, if doxastic involuntarism is true, then we should reconceive what are traditionally called reasons for belief. The truth of doxastic involuntarism would rule out a certain understanding of reasons for belief according to which they are necessary conditions for doxastic obligations. Thus, reconceiving reasons for belief would require reconceiving doxastic obligations. I argue that, in fact, a re-conception of reasons for belief warrants abandoning the notion of doxastic obligations, understood as obligations to form, alter, or relinquish doxastic states. Instead, the only sorts of obligations we would have that concern our doxastic states would be aretaic or practical. In chapters 4 and 5, I apply the arguments from chapters 2 and 3 to testimonial beliefs and doxastic justification, respectively. In chapter 4, I argue that a general feature of human psychology provides strong reason to modify or reject anti-reductionism about the epistemology of testimony. Because of the work of what I call 'the background' (which is a collection of all of an individual's synthetizations, summarizations, memories of experiences, beliefs, etc.) we cannot help but form testimonial beliefs on the basis of a testifier's say so along with additional evidence, concepts, beliefs, etc. Given that we arrive at testimonial beliefs through the work of the background, to be justified in holding a testimonial belief, we must not only have a rational speaker's say so, but we must also form such beliefs in the right way. If this is right, then, contrary to typical anti-reductionism, justified testimonial beliefs require more than just a trustworthy testifier's say so—another requirement is that they are formed in the right way. In chapter 5, I argue that what it takes for an agent to be justified in holding a belief is that the agent formed the belief in the right sort of way, which should be understood in terms of virtue epistemology. That is, in contrast to the predominant way of understanding doxastic justification—a deontological view according to which you are justified in holding a belief if and only if it is permissible for you to hold the belief—we should understand doxastic justification aretaically: you are justified in holding a belief if and only if your belief is the result of the operation of virtue. I argue that the aretaic account of justification is superior to the deontological one.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A dissertation submitted to the Department of Philosophy in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 16, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Doxastic Agency, Doxastic Involuntarism, Ethics of Belief, Justification, Virtue Epistemology</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Edward Hinchman, Professor Directing Dissertation; John Kelsay, University Representative; Stephen Kearns, Committee Member; Zina Ward, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100849">
      <mods:topic>Philosophy</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85072732">
      <mods:topic>Knowledge, Theory of</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85045096">
      <mods:topic>Ethics</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Smith_fsu_0071E_18070</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Philosophy</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
