<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Carbon Dynamics in a Changing Arctic Landscape</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Characterizing Dissolved Organic Matter across Multiple Scales</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-0182-5368</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Starr</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Sommer Faith</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016068194">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Spencer</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Robert G. M.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/spau">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Pau</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Stephanie</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n98061219">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Chassignet</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Eric P.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n89605460">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Chanton</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jeffrey P.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kpwick">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Wickland</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kimberly P.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (197 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Northern high-latitude freshwater systems are an essential link between terrestrial and marine carbon cycles, transporting organic matter from ecosystems on land to the Arctic Ocean. However, polar regions are warming faster than the global average due to anthropogenic climate change, potentially releasing hundreds of tons of carbon currently stored in peatland and permafrost soils. Arctic ecosystem dynamics are also changing under continued warming, and changing land cover and hydrology will alter the amount and composition of organic matter exported by surface waters. Dissolved organic matter (DOM) is a crucial component of the carbon cycle, with the global DOM pool rivaling the amount of carbon stored in the atmosphere. The composition of DOM is fundamentally linked to its reactivity and, as such, partially determines whether mobilized DOM will be mineralized and released as greenhouse gases or stored on long time scales in marine systems. Understanding DOM dynamics in Arctic freshwater systems is thus crucial to understanding the impacts of climate change. This dissertation investigates DOM sources, molecular composition, and processing pathways across the pan-Arctic watershed and uses a suite of investigative tools, including optical measurements, Fourier transform ion cyclotron resonance mass spectrometry (FT-ICR MS), and spatial analysis, to investigate how a changing Arctic landscape may impact DOM dynamics. The research focused on four distinct areas: refining dissolved organic carbon (DOC) fluxes from the pan-Arctic watershed, characterizing the influences of peatland cover and permafrost on exported DOM, evaluating how DOM composition and microbial community influence the processing of DOM, and characterizing the composition and reactivity of DOM from non-vascular plant sources. DOM composition varied across ecosystems, reflecting the chemodiversity inherent to this carbon cycle component. In the Onega River, a relatively small and understudied high-latitude river, DOM exhibited a uniquely terrestrial signature throughout the year with muted seasonal changes, contrasting with the dramatic seasonality of DOM composition in larger watersheds. Scaling data from the Onega River increased the estimated pan-Arctic annual DOC flux by approximately 50% from previously reported estimates, suggesting that including smaller watersheds is important for improving pan-Arctic modeling estimates. The Onega River watershed is unique from the six largest Arctic rivers by being permafrost-free and having a large proportion of its area covered by wetlands; thus, its unique molecular signature is likely driven by these landscape features. The relationship between these landscape features and DOM composition is explicitly revealed through an analysis of DOM composition across a latitudinal gradient in West Siberia, demonstrating that peatland extent and permafrost influence have observable impacts on DOM exported by rivers. DOM composition from permafrost-free watersheds exhibited greater variability, higher molecular weight, and a more terrestrial signature than permafrost-influenced watersheds. Peatland extent explained much of the variance in measured variables, with watersheds with greater peatland extent exhibiting more heterogenous DOM composition. However, permafrost effectively acts as a switch on this peatland influence, and so these data demonstrate that DOM from previously permafrost-influenced watersheds may become more heterogeneous and exhibit a more terrestrial signature as permafrost thaw continues. A novel bioincubation experiment was conducted to explore further how these landscape features and their impacts on DOM composition affect DOM biolability and to determine whether the introduction of microbes from one type of soil to another impact DOC loss over time. Leachates created from two wetland depths of wetland soil and soil from two ages of permafrost at distinct filtration levels allowed for the simulation of the mobilization and potential mixing of DOM and microbes from these sources under continued permafrost thaw. Data from these bioincubations demonstrated that the source and composition of DOM, not the microbial community, was the factor that determined DOM biolability and processing. Pleistocene permafrost produced compositionally unique DOM that exhibited an approximately 70% DOC loss rate over time, highlighting the high bioavailability of DOM mobilized as these deposits thaw. Warming not only affects permafrost but impacts the distribution of vegetation on the landscape. Lignin phenol analysis and optical measurements of individual moss and lichen leachates were conducted to explore how shrub expansion and associated loss of moss and lichen cover in the Arctic may impact DOM dynamics. Moss leachates produced high concentrations of biolabile DOM enriched in p-hydroxy phenols; however, the general aromaticity of the DOM and not the phenol composition appeared to be the primary driver of DOC loss over time. Overall, these data characterized DOC export and DOM composition across a wide range of sources and regions in the pan-Arctic watershed and highlight the need for further research to continue elucidating DOM dynamics in the Arctic.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Physical Environmental Science.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 5, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Arctic biogeochemistry, dissolved organic matter, FT-ICR MS, peatlands, permafrost, surface water</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Robert G. M. Spencer, Professor Directing Dissertation; Stephanie Pau, University Representative; Eric P. Chassignet, Committee Member; Jeff P. Chanton, Committee Member; Kimberly P. Wickland, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014146">
      <mods:topic>Biogeochemistry</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92004048">
      <mods:topic>Environmental sciences</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027037">
      <mods:topic>Climatic changes</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Starr_fsu_0071E_18508</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
