<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>String Musicians' Perceptions of Baton Use as Compared to Choral and Band Musicians</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-5750-0047</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Whitehead</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">William Ryan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2015096684">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Bugaj</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kasia</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007052630">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Jiménez</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Alexander</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1963-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2003044981">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Jones</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Evan Allan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kvanweelden">
      <mods:namePart type="family">VanWeelden</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kimberly D.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kadams6">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Adams</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kari</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Music</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Music</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (90 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>The purpose of this study was to determine how choral, band, and orchestral string musicians perceive the clarity and expressivity of choral, band, and orchestral conductors based upon the use or non-use of the baton. This study aimed to address the following research questions: (1) Are there differences in collegiate choral, band, and orchestral string musicians' ratings of conductor clarity or expressivity dependent upon the presence or absence of the baton? (2) Are there differences in collegiate choral, band, and orchestral string musicians' ratings of conductor clarity or expressivity dependent upon the specialty of the conductor? (3) What aspects of conductor baton use or non-use influence collegiate choral, band, and orchestral string musicians' ratings of conductor clarity and expressivity? (4) Do collegiate orchestral string musicians' ratings of conductor clarity and expressivity align more closely to those of choral musicians, band musicians, or neither? I selected three highly expressive professional recordings of Morton Lauridsen's O Magnum Mysterium, one each of the original chorus composition, the band transcription, and the string orchestra transcription. I then invited a graduate orchestral conductor, graduate band conductor, and graduate choral conductor to conduct the recording that fit their specialty both with and without a baton. I then recorded each conductor as they conducted along to their recording with and without a baton and replaced the camera audio with the professional audio. Two 30 second to 45 second excerpts from each conducting recording were selected and anonymized. These excerpts where then placed into a survey asking participants to view each video, rate each video for conducting clarity and expressivity, and optionally provide feedback about how they arrived at their ratings. This survey was then distributed to several universities around the United States. Participants (N = 238) consisted of collegiate choral (n = 93), band (n = 74), and orchestral string (n = 71) musicians. Statistical analysis revealed significant main effects for baton use in ratings of expressivity as well as significant interactions between conductor specialty and baton use for ratings of clarity and expressivity and significant interactions between participant musician type and conductor specialty for ratings of clarity. No significant interaction between participant musician type and baton use was found. Participants overall found the bare hands to be more expressive than the baton, with no significant difference in clarity. Both the choral conductor and band conductor were found to be clearer with the baton, significantly more so than the orchestral conductor. Chorus musicians considered the choral conductor to be clearer than either the band or orchestral conductor, while band and orchestral musicians both agreed that the orchestral conductor was less clear than either the choral or band conductor. Band and orchestral string musicians tended to align on most metrics. Qualitative analysis of comments (N = 599) left by participants suggests that most participants were influenced by aspects of the conductors unrelated to the baton or right hand. Of those comments that did center on the baton or right hand, most were concerned with issues of technique, congruency of musical gestures with musical response, and overall quality. Only a small subset of comments specifically attributed their ratings to the presence or absence of the baton. Taken together, these findings have implications for both conducting research and applied conducting. In conducting research, the practice of generalizing findings of studies done with wind and percussion players to all instrumentalists, inclusive of string players, would appear to be valid. The converse may also be true: the findings of future conducting research done with orchestral string players may also be generalizable to wind and percussion players. For applied conducting, while the need to be comfortable both with a baton and without a baton has not been negated, it seems that as far as musicians in general are concerned, conductors may be able to take advantage of the increased expressivity of conducting without the baton without a significant loss of clarity given appropriate technique and training. However, further research on the use of the baton in a variety of styles and tempi is necessary.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the College of Music in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 26, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">baton use, conducting, perception</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Katarzyna (Kasia) Bugaj, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Alexander Jiménez, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Evan A. Jones, University Representative; Kimberly D. VanWeelden, Committee Member; Kari Adams, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85088796">
      <mods:topic>Music</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Instruction and study</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Whitehead_fsu_0071E_18640</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Music</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
