<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Talent Is Evenly Distributed, Opportunity Is Not</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Exploring the Role of the High School Partners Program on the College Choice Process among Black Students at Florida State University</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">tfwilliams</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Williams</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Terrell F.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/cmokher">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Mokher</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Christine G.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2011024781">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Jones</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Ithel</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lperezfelkner">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Perez-Felkner</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Lara</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/wecton">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Ecton</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Walter</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2024</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (97 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>While Black students have experienced significant growth in college enrollment since the passage of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 and Higher Education Act of 1965, they are still less likely than their white counterparts to attend and graduate from a post-secondary institution (Ryan &amp; Bauman, 2016). There have been previous studies on college access programs that aim to combat the challenges contributing to the college access gap for Black students, such as percentage plans, admissions lotteries, and admissions preferences for low socioeconomic students. Although the aim was to promote equality, race-neutral and objective admissions policies perpetuate patterns of power, privilege, and racial inequity by assuming that all educational resources are equal (Bonilla-Silva, 2010). In an effort to address educational disparities, the Florida State University Office of Admissions, Center for Academic Retention and Enhancement (CARE), and Office of Financial Aid joined forces in 2015 to launch the High School Partners Program, a new college access initiative. Students from eight (8) public high schools located in three counties along the eastern and western corridor of Interstate 10 in Florida receive support with college applications and enrollment through the High School Partners Program (Florida State University, 2021). Increasing the percentage of students from underfunded public high schools who applied and were accepted to Florida State University was the objective of the High School Partners Program. All students at participating high schools are eligible for the High School Partners Program, regardless of their financial situation or status as first-generation students, although most of them come from historically underserved backgrounds. The purpose of this study was to explore the role of the High School Partners Program in the college choice process among Black students who enrolled at Florida State University through the general admissions process. This study is supported by research on factors associated with Black students' postsecondary enrollment patterns and chances to improve the pipeline and yield of students from high schools with inadequate resources. Hossler and Gallagher (1987) created a college choice model that outlined three stages (predisposition, search, and choice) that students go through while selecting a college, and this model had an influence on the research framework. The study explored a range of factors that influence students' decision-making through semi-structured interviews. The sample consisted of seven Black students who were enrolled in Fall 2023 and were alumni of a school that was affiliated with the High School Partners Program. According to the study's findings, Black students' enrollment in the predisposition or search stages of the Hossler and Gallagher College Choice Model (1987) was not significantly impacted by the High School Partners Program. Comparable to previous studies, family, college reputation, geographic location, cost, and availability of financial aid shaped Black students' pre-college experiences (Bers &amp; Smith, 1989; Clayton et al., 2023; Comeaux et al., 2020; Sevier, 1992; Weiler, 1994). However, the study indicated that the High School Partners Program played an influential role in the choice stage. Students gave a variety of reasons for choosing to enroll, including scholarship funding, interactions with Black FSU personnel, a different academic and cultural setting from their high schools, household structure, and family member accessibility. The findings also revealed that the High School Partners Program is positively correlated with postsecondary enrollment at FSU for Black student populations that were previously overlooked in the admissions process. These populations include first-generation students who are not eligible for Pell grants and second-generation students who are eligible for Pell grants, who each represent only 9.7% of the university's total FTIC Black student body in Fall 2023 (FSU Office of Institutional Research, 2024). Participants suggested that in order to improve the FSU High School Partners Program, the admissions staff should consider three primary modifications: 1) increase awareness of the High School Partners Program; 2) provide more opportunities to build relationships with FSU representatives; 3) assist in integrating students from partner schools into the FSU community. Further research is imperative to determine the High School Partners Program's viability as an approach to Black student recruitment and to obtain a better understanding of the student populations that stand to benefit the most from involvement.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Education.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 5, 2024.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">At-risk students, Black students, College access, College choice, College enrollment</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Christine Mokher, Professor Directing Dissertation; Ithel Jones, University Representative; Lara Perez-Felkner, Committee Member; Walter Ecton, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041065">
      <mods:topic>Education, Higher</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Williams_fsu_0071E_18562</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Education</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-08-19T12:02:22.846834-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
