<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Student Perceptions of and Preferences for Online Instructor Course Introductions</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-4692-0748</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Arslan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Ömer</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2012011678">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Dennen</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Vanessa P.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1970-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2005077563">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Rutledge</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Stacey A.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/eyoon">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Yoon</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Eunhui</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Education</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Educational Psychology and Learning Systems</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Online instructors utilize instructional strategies to mitigate challenges that arise from transactional distance. These strategies can also facilitate establishing instructor social presence and identity, which is a common concern in online learning contexts. Effective online course introductions provide an opportunity for instructors to introduce themselves to online learners and model effective self-disclosures early in the course. Introductions help online learners know more about their course instructors and help them have a sense of what kind of an instructor they will be engaging in learning interactions with. Although course introductions are common first-day-of-the-class activities, there is limited empirical research on what students like to know about their instructors at the start of a course. Furthermore, previous studies demonstrate inconsistent findings regarding student perceptions of and preferences for the timing and type of instructor self-disclosures that are appropriate in an educational context. This exploratory study uses survey design to examine undergraduate and graduate students' perceptions of and preferences for online instructor course introductions. Participants were recruited from a university's research pool. The data set included 110 responses that were analyzed using descriptive statistics and content analysis. Findings show that it is important for online learners to know about their instructors, preferably their professional qualifications. When the instructor feels like a real person, students feel like they learn more. Most students turn to multiple different sources to learn more about their instructors even before a class begins. Reading the instructor's course introduction is the most common approach to learning more about the instructor, while looking up the instructor on social media is the least common approach. Aligned with knowing more about the instructor's professional qualifications, students find instructor self-disclosures about professional qualifications (e.g., course information, prior professional experience, college experiences, prior education, and hobbies) more appropriate than personal life details (e.g., personal opinions, relationship information, religious affiliation, socio-economic status, political affiliations, and financial information). Course information related disclosures had the highest approval ratings, while financial information had the least. Most students like to know what their online instructors look and sound like. Sharing instructor photos and videos as part of online course introductions had high approval ratings. Participants prefer instructor photo as a professional photo or headshot more than an informal photo or snapshot and a selfie. Moreover, instructor photos related to profession had the highest approval ratings in terms of types of photos that an instructor can add as part of course introduction, followed by pets, travel, family, and food. Introduction videos should be shot in the instructor's office, followed by in a classroom, in their home, and outdoors. When asked how they perceive an online instructor based on a course introduction with no self-disclosure and with prior professional experiences and hobbies self-disclosures, students perceive the latter as more friendly, approachable, interested in their learning, and interested in the class. Moreover, they reported higher ratings of willingness to email the instructor and visit the instructor in office hour. This finding suggests that appropriate self-disclosures early at the start of a course might help instructors reduce tensions around transactional distance and help them be perceived as real, and increase student willingness to interact with their instructors. The findings of this study challenge instructional practices in which instructors self-disclose personal and vulnerable information early in the course and personal information in general. Overall, this exploratory study provide additional insights to the literature on social presence and identity as well as instructor self-disclosure in online learning contexts. Limitations were presented and implications for theory, research, and practice were discussed.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Psychology and Learning Systems in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 03, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Vanessa Dennen, Professor Directing Dissertation; Stacey Rutledge, University Representative; Eunhui Yoon, Committee Member; Secil Caskurlu, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066762">
      <mods:topic>Instructional systems</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Design</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Arslan_fsu_0071E_17823</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Psychology and Learning Systems</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
