<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Situated Knowledges in Different World Regions</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Reflecting on Mosquito Control and Malaria Prevention Knowledge and Curricular Approaches to Bring Diverse Global Knowledges into World Regional Geography</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-4353-4497</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Bandzuh</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">John T.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="termsOfAddress">IV</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/cuejio">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Uejio</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Christopher K.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2019070869">
      <mods:namePart type="family">McCreary</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Tyler</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/FSUID">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Mukherjee</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Tathagata</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/FSUID">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Wong</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Sandy</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr90000461">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Doel</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Ronald Edmund</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Geography</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>The primary objective of this dissertation is to scrutinize knowledge production. We recognize the work produced and shared by feminist geographers such as Donna Haraway and Gillian Rose that have asserted systemic biases in how knowledge is produced and reproduced. This work, like others before, will push beyond the 'vantage point of master subject' (Haraway 1988) and engage a variety of participants and research methodologies to answer our research questions. In doing so, this dissertation aims to add a mixed methods approach to the growing body of literature to probe the partiality of knowledge (Nightingale 2003). This dissertation utilizes multiple methodologies to conduct research to demonstrate the importance of recognizing the multitude of knowledge sources when conducting research and aims to amplify situated and local knowledge, particularly from the Global South. To date, there remain significant barriers for underrepresented perspectives and voices to reach academia and the published literature (Hedding and Breetzke 2021), for which this dissertation hopes to improve. Malaria remains the world's deadliest vector-borne disease, resulting in over 200 million human cases and more than 400,000 deaths annually. While some progress has been made in combating malaria, Sumba Island, Indonesia has lagged much of the rest of Indonesia and the region in lowering malaria infections. Chapters 2-3 survey communities of East Sumba Island, Indonesia to understand knowledge, attitudes, and practices of mosquito control and malaria prevention. Chapter 2 employs a qualitative approach to investigate knowledge, attitudes, and practices surrounding mosquito control and prevention methods in East Sumba Regency, Indonesia. While malaria is under control in much of Indonesia, transmission in Sumba Island remains high, with an incidence as high as 500 cases per 1000 people per year in some areas. This chapter explores the use of insecticide treated nets (ITNs), traditional Sumbanese mosquito control methods, as well as the role of community-based health workers (kaders) and integrated health service posts (posyandu), to combat malaria. Focus group discussions (n = 7) and key informant interviews (n = 14) were conducted with religious leaders, health workers, and women's group leaders and were stratified by urban/rural location and malaria incidence. Results indicate that environmental conditions, such as high temperatures, were deterrents to regular use. Furthermore, our results suggest that community-embedded health workers, kaders, and health service posts, posyandu, play an important role in information dissemination related to mosquitoes and mosquito-borne diseases as well as the distribution and use of ITNs. Chapter 3 aims to investigate local knowledge, attitudes, and practices related to mosquito control and malaria prevention in East Sumba Island, Indonesia through a cross-sectional household survey (n = 757) informed by previously collected qualitative data found in Chapter 2. The cross-sectional household surveys were conducted across six study sites in East Sumba Regency, Indonesia in urban and rural areas with both high and low malaria incidence. Logistic/multinomial regressions examined sociodemographic relationships to themes found within the household surveys. Further, this study utilizes and expands the traditional Health Belief Model to understand mosquito control and malaria prevention behaviors, particularly as they are impacted by gender, socioeconomics, and geographic location. This study uncovered survey respondents' attitudes, perceptions, and acceptance of the novel spatial repellent use (n = 719) with 95% of study participants expressing a likelihood of using spatial repellent. This demonstrated early buy-in to novel techniques to control mosquitoes. Additionally, results from this study include the influence of risk perception on a willingness to take actions to control mosquitoes to prevent malaria such as clearing tall grass and/or brush, eliminating mosquito breeding habitats, willingness to sell or deliver mosquito control products, and a willingness to educate the community about such measures. Chapter 4 investigates the role of films used as a key component for World Geography (GEA 1000), an undergraduate course that completes a university-wide cross-cultural studies requirement. Utilizing films, particularly those sourced from underrepresented regions, introduced students to local and situated knowledges outside their typical perspectives and lived experiences. The course was taught remotely during a six-week Summer session in 2020 during the SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) pandemic. The films used cover a wide range of topics such as poverty, war, climate change, migration, and other key subjects. Upon watching the films, students were then instructed to take a short assessment to evaluate their comprehension of the film content. At the completion of the course, students expressed (through course evaluations) that this format helped contextualize geographic themes and world events as well as served as a learning tool in addition to more traditional methods.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Geography in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">February 17, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Christopher K. Uejio, Professor Directing Dissertation; Tyler McCreary, Committee Member; Sandy Wong, Committee Member; Ronald E. Doel, University Representative.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85053986">
      <mods:topic>Geography</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Bandzuh_fsu_0071E_17690</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Geography</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
