<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Teacher Experiences during Covid, Their Perceptions of Morale, and Influential School Support</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7397-746X</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Donahue</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Deborah M.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2003057796">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Akiba</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Motoko</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kwhalon">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Whalon</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kelly J.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n97036418">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Herrington</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Carolyn D.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2005077563">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Rutledge</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Stacey A.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Education</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>This study sought to explore the experiences of teachers during Covid-19, their sense of morale, and the supports that were influential to that sense of morale. Three research questions were explored to better understand how teachers experienced teaching during Covid-19: (1) How do middle school teachers describe the experience of teaching during Covid-19?, (2) How do middle school teachers perceive their sense of morale during the Covid-19 pandemic?, and (3) What supports do these teachers describe as influential for their sense of morale? I conducted an exploratory, qualitative, single case study using semi-structured interviews of five participants selected in a purposeful sample. It was found that teachers experienced a number of challenges from March 2020 through May 2021 including ineffective communication and a lack of training, purchasing technology and materials out of pocket, a loss of control through technological difficulties and student disengagement. From August 2021 through May 2022 teachers experienced challenging student behaviors, loss of learning and social skills in students, and a significant learning loss in economically disadvantaged students which exacerbated inequity. An analysis of these five teachers' experiences and feelings during Covid-19 indicates that their sense of morale was fluid. All five participants had times when their state of morale could best be described as low; however, all five participants also had times when their state of morale could best be described as having mixed levels of morale. The positive influences on their state of morale varied by participant. Four of the five cited support from coworkers as a positive influence on morale. Another cited the relationships with their students and their love of teaching as positive influences. Another cited working from home as her safety needs were being met. Two of the participants cited student behaviors during the hybrid year. One of the two that cited student behaviors focused on the lack of negative student behavior. The other participant explained she had increased student engagement and smaller class sizes. The negative influences on their sense of morale included technological difficulties for all the participants at some point during hybrid learning or remote teaching, student disengagement, and lack of communication. All five also discussed the negative influence on their sense of morale from student behaviors once all students returned to in-person instruction. Another negative influence on three participants was a reduced sense of safety on campus when all students returned. Finally, teachers value both instructional and social-emotional support from their colleagues more than administrative support. Based on these findings, five recommendations are offered. First, it is recommended that districts plan for effective communication for a future crisis. Second, it is important to address student behaviors after a school closure due to a crisis ending to ensure learning is not interrupted. Third, it is essential to provide teachers with the technology needed to perform their jobs in remote and hybrid teaching. Fourth, the disproportionate learning opportunities for economically disadvantaged students need to be addressed by providing access to needed technology and online connectivity and communication with parents during remote learning and allocating additional resources to support their learning when they return to school. Finally, teacher collaboration should be promoted, and teacher leaders must be recognized and rewarded for their efforts to support their colleagues.  </mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Education.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 9, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Covid-19, Supports, Teacher Experiences, Teacher Morale</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Motoko Akiba, Professor Directing Dissertation; Kelly Whalon, University Representative; Carolyn Herrington, Committee Member; Stacey Rutledge, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001254">
      <mods:topic>Educational leadership</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Donahue_fsu_0071E_17707</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Education</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
