<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Effects of Staccato and Legato Conducting Gestures on Perceptions of Note Duration</mods:title>
      <mods:nonSort>The</mods:nonSort>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-6779-8286</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Doshier</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Nickolas Michael</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dgspringer">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Springer</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">D. Gregory  (Douglas Gregory)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2008046845">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Drew</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">John Robert</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1951-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n99036353">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Dunnigan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Patrick</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1957-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2008036741">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kelly</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Steven N.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jgeringer">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Geringer</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">John M.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Music</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Music</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>The purpose of this study was to examine the effects of staccato and legato conducting gestures on perceptions of note duration. I also investigated how the effects of conductor gesture might differ for participants with and without conductor training. In addition, I explored whether participants believed that watching the conductor influenced their ratings of note duration. The participants (N = 173) for this study were collegiate musicians who observed four brief video recordings of a conductor demonstrating short and long gestures synchronized with audio recordings of a wind ensemble performing short and long notes. All possible pairings were used for audiovisual stimuli, including two congruent (i.e., short conducting gestures with short performance audio and long conducting gestures with long performance audio) and two incongruent stimuli (i.e., short conducting gestures with long performance audio and long conducting gestures with short performance audio). Participants were randomly assigned to one of four unique presentation orders. After observing each recording, participants rated the overall note duration of the excerpt by manipulating a slider anchored by 1 (extremely short) and 101 (extremely long). The numeric values were not visible to participants, and the slider was positioned in the center prior to the participants' rating. After viewing and responding to the four recordings, participants were asked if they believed that watching the conductor influenced their ratings of note duration. They also answered a free-response question where they explained their answer. Results indicated a significant main effect for performance audio (h2p = .823) and conducting gestures (h2p = .264) for participants' ratings of note duration. There was also a significant three-way interaction between conducting gesture, performance audio, and presentation order, F(3, 169) = 16.505, p &lt; .001, h2p = .227. Participants rated the note duration of congruent audiovisual recordings as expected, with staccato notes being rated shortest in duration and legato notes being rated longest in duration. Participants' ratings of the incongruent audiovisual recordings, however, highlighted the fact that their ratings of note duration were not independent of the visual gestures displayed by the conductor. More specifically, short performance audio excerpts were rated as longer when paired with long conducting gestures than with short conducting gestures, and long performance audio excerpts were rated as shorter when paired with short conducting gestures than with long conducting gestures. Further, participants' ratings indicated that the influence of visual conducting gestures on ratings of note duration were similar between both conditions—staccato and legato. In response to the question "Did watching the conductor influence your perception of note duration?" significantly more participants reported yes (n = 79) or no (n = 69) over "I am not sure" (n = 25, p &lt; .001). Participants' free responses to the question "Please explain your answer" helped to contextualize these findings. The coding categories for the open-ended question were (a) awareness, (b) audio priority, (c) visual priority, (d) interaction, (e) conducting gesture, and (f) other. The overall percentage of coded responses that mentioned visual (19.94%; visual priority and conducting gesture categories combined) or auditory (20.60%; audio priority) elements occurred with similar frequency. In the interaction category (14.29%), many participants explicitly commented on the influence of visual conducting gestures on their perceptions of audible note duration with comments such as "the longer motions did stretch out the notes somewhat, or rather it felt that way." The awareness category (34.22%) highlighted participants' sensitivity to observing the incongruent audiovisual stimuli. The influence of visual conducting gestures on ratings of note duration were similar between musicians with and without prior conductor training, and those similarities were consistent across all audiovisual pairings. However, prior conducting experience did seem to influence musicians' opinions regarding the visual role of the conductor when rating ensemble note duration. Specifically, a greater percentage of participants with conductor training reported that the conductor did not influence their ratings of note duration as compared to untrained conductors. Therefore, it seems that participants' perceptions of note duration were inconsistent with their actual ratings of note duration. Conducting training might have increased participants' confidence in explicitly rating the sound of an ensemble, despite the fact that participants' actual ratings of note duration demonstrated a significant influence based on visual conducting gestures. The findings from this study add to the body of literature on audiovisual sensory interactions and perceptions of conductors. Implications for music educators and suggestions for future research are discussed.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the College of Music in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 28, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">audio-visual interaction, conducting, duration, music ensembles, music performance, perception</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">D. Gregory Springer, Professor Directing Dissertation; John Drew, University Representative; Patrick Dunnigan, Committee Member; Steven N. Kelly, Committee Member; John M. Geringer, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85088796">
      <mods:topic>Music</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Instruction and study</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Doshier_fsu_0071E_17798</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Music</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
