<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Critical Look at a Community Art Education Program</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Is Inclusion Just a Myth?</mods:subTitle>
      <mods:nonSort>A</mods:nonSort>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-2878-8480</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Gerardi</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Debbie K.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007010325">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Broome</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jeffrey L. (Jeffrey Lynn)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kwhalon">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Whalon</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kelly J.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="viaf"
              authorityURI="http://viaf.org/viaf/"
              valueURI="http://viaf.org/viaf/1152380012501761724">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Fendler</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Rachel Loveitt</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2016062968">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Love</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Ann Rowson</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1967-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Fine Arts</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Art Education</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Is inclusion in the arts just a myth? Research has shown there are few peer reviewed journal articles and books published about inclusive programs in community art centers for adults with disabilities. This qualitative single case study critically reviewed the inclusive programs offered at a Midwestern community visual art center. During the literature review, this author discovered a Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts VSA report identifying specific priority areas to advance inclusion in the artsleading to this study's research question: What does inclusive community arts education look like in practice for a selected arts center? This overarching concern was followed by several supporting questions; How can the arts promote inclusive learning opportunities? How does an informal creative arts center establish and promote inclusive programs for people with disabilities? How do members (instructors/facilitators) of a selected community arts education center perceive inclusive practices? The conceptual framework of this inquiry was constructed by researching the medical, social, and affirmative disability models associated with the foundations of disability studies. A resulting review of related literature focused on the historical background of the intersection of disability studies with art education, notable people in the field, and the potential power the arts have in building cultural bridges and a sense of belonging. This literature review revealed that most research addressing the intersection of art education with disability studies focuses on children from five through eighteen years old within K-12 educational settings. Therefore, additional exploration is needed to bridge the gap on research about adults with disabilities making art in inclusive community centers. Research methods included interviewing, observing, and qualitative case study analysis. Additionally, the author enriched the data with thick and rich autoethnographic passages describing experiences with inclusion, inclusionism, disability, and identity from a parent's, educator's, and introspective viewpoint. After selecting Visionaries and Voices (V+V) in Cincinnati as the case study site, the researcher spent 12 days making field observations in the fall and winter of 2021-2022. During that time, the researcher conducted nine semi-structured in-person interviews exploring the staff's opinions about inclusion and programming, plus revealing new emergent topics. The research findings took an emic approach that involves telling the story from participants' perspectives, in addition to the researcher's own insider's view as a mother and experienced art educator devoted to disability studies. Quality and rigor were built into this research through triangulation, member checking, and other methods increasing the trustworthiness, credibility, and dependability of the study. The findings and analysis of this case study revealed V+V is a warm, family like atmosphere with friendships based on mutual respect. Analysis revealed commonalities in staff member's perceptions toward inclusion. V+V has two well-established and successful inclusionary programs. Established in 2009, Double Vision is a collaborative art making program which culminates in an annual live auction fundraiser. The Teaching Artist Program provides a unique comprehensive instructional and leadership curriculum that supports artists with disabilities in public speaking and teaching art in the community. Staff members expressed the need for the improvement of physical accessibility in the V+V environment and updating the van currently used to transport the artists. Like most 501(c)(3) nonprofit art organizations, funding is an issue for V+V. This art studio receives limited funding, primarily from SSDI and Medicare. V+V is modeled after Creative Growth, a progressive art studio created by F. Ludins-Katz and E. Katz. Today, V+V appears to be a leader in the progressive art studio movement. They collaborate with other progressive studios and galleries worldwide, participate in symposiums, and have emerged as a valuable resource for those interested in starting a like-minded art studio space. There are four recommendations based on the findings of this study. (a) Inclusive art programs should use the Universal Design for Learning table as a guide to routinely assess accessibility, program effectiveness, and artists' comfort levels. (b) The findings of this study suggest the need for additional staff positions, either paid or volunteer, full or part-time, updated training and clarification of work duties. (c) Inclusive art programs should offer art career instruction and guidance to their participating artists. (d) Inclusive art programs should offer workshops on inclusivity and collaborative artmaking methods to the surrounding community. This research inquiry concluded that art not disability is the foundation for studios for people with disabilities. There are too few inclusive community art centers in the United States. It is possible that inclusive community art education programs could serve as a natural pathway to foster society's viewpoint of people with disabilities as successful contributing members of society.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Art Education in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Education.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 4, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Art Education, Disability Art, Disability Studies, Inclusion, Outsider Art, Progressive Art</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jeffrey Broome, Professor Directing Dissertation; Kelly Whalon, University Representative; Rachel Fendler, Committee Member; Ann Rowson-Love, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007505">
      <mods:topic>Art</mods:topic>
      <mods:topic>Study and teaching</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046212">
      <mods:topic>Special education</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Gerardi_fsu_0071E_17803</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Education</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Art Education</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
