<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>String Quartet No. 2 "Geometric Roses"</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0003-6167-0016</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Grice</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jacob</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lugay">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Ugay</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Liliya</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing thesis</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no00018481">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Callender</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Clifton</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Music</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Music</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Writing a string quartet has always been on my compositional bucket list. While the first multi-movement composition I ever wrote was a string quartet in the freshman year of my undergraduate degree, I thought it would be fitting to write another one as the final piece of my master's degree. My first string quartet adhered strictly to traditional forms, utilized harmony and counterpoint consistent with what I had begun to learn in theory, and was heavily influenced by some of my favorite romantic-era composers. My second string quartet uses similar compositional techniques to my first, but updates them with everything I have learned from my classes and lessons at both schools and all of the new music I have become more exposed to. This piece uses traditional forms, but I take much more liberty with how I treat the themes and recurring sections, rather than the strict framework I used before. My harmonic language has drastically changed since then as well; although I consider my music to be more on the tonal side of the spectrum, I use unconventional ways to achieve that tonality through modal and synthetic scales, as well as inverting and transposing atonal sets in ways similar to dominant-tonic motion. My inspiration is no longer romantic-era composers, but for this piece, I listened to a lot of Bartok's string quartets, which especially influenced the first movement, Ligeti's piano etudes, and even some progressive rock, which influenced the final movement. The first movement begins with a short, somber melody played by the viola that will serve as the connecting motif between each movement. From this melody, centered around G, I construct a large canon which ultimately forms a substantial introduction before the first movement truly begins. The intro theme, as well as the fiery allegro and sultry secondary theme, are used in traditional sonata form for the entirety of the movement. The second movement is a scherzo and trio featuring varying ostinatos in different time signatures before a warm cello melody is introduced. First, the second violin begins in what feels like 2/4, before the first violin enters in 6/8. The viola then enters in 3/4 before the cello melody enters in 3/4 as well, finally solidifying the time signature. The rest of the movement plays with these different beat emphases, mixing and matching them so they don't quite line up all the time. The third movement is a short, heartfelt love letter to my instrument, the viola. Beginning with chords that somewhat resemble a progression that perhaps Vaughan Williams would write, they are blurred by clusters, and later, techniques such as sul ponticello. It is not until the very end of the movement after the folk-sounding melody, where we hear the chord progression finally unveiled in the lower strings. The final movement is meant to be fast, groovy, and fun for the performers. It is in a sort-of sonata rondo form featuring two highly contrasting themes, with a development section that fragments themes from previous movements, rather than material from this one. It ends triumphantly on a G major chord which completes our harmonic journey from the con dolore theme in the first movement.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Music in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of Music.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">April 10, 2023.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Classical Music, Composition, Geometric Roses, Music, String Quartet, Viola</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Liliya Ugay, Professor Directing Thesis; Clifton Callender, Committee Member; Osman Eren Gumrukcuoglu, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85088826">
      <mods:topic>Composition (Music)</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Grice_fsu_0071N_17991</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Music</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>College of Music</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
