<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Path Analysis of the Relationships among Mindsets, Academic Writing Anxiety, and Self-Satisfaction with Academic Writing of Chinese Graduate Students</mods:title>
      <mods:nonSort>A</mods:nonSort>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6201-4721</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Liang</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Fang</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jeturner">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Turner</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jeannine E.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/gsunderm">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Sunderman</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Gretchen L.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/yyang3">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Yang</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Yanyun</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2001090777">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Roehrig</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Alysia D.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1975-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Education</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Educational Psychology and Learning Systems</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (125 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Extant literature indicates that Chinese graduate students experience academic writing anxiety when writing with English as their second language (Cheng, 2014b; Ho, 2016; Huang, 2014; Liang &amp; Turner, 2021). Writing anxiety exerts negative impacts on students' engagement with writing (Daly &amp; Miller, 1975), has negative association with writing self-efficacy (Pajares &amp; Johnson, 1994) and the quality of writing (Daly, 1978), and negatively predicts self-regulated writing strategy use (Paul et al., 2021; Stewart et al., 2015; Wang &amp; Zhan, 2020). Therefore, it is important to further understand academic writing anxiety with English as a second language (L2) so that Chinese graduate students have successful learning experiences in the American educational setting. However, few theories account for language learning anxiety, including such skill-specific anxieties as writing anxiety. Besides, previous studies did not link the antecedents and consequences of writing anxiety together. To address these gaps, this dissertation study investigated the relationships among Chinese graduate students' L2 academic writing mindsets (students' beliefs about whether they can increase their academic writing competence or not), their perceived academic writing competence, academic writing anxiety, academic writing self-efficacy, self-regulated writing and students' self-satisfaction with their own academic writing. The participants (n=223) were Chinese international students enrolled in various graduate programs in American universities. All the data for this dissertation study were collected through an online survey questionnaire. A path analysis was conducted to investigate the relationships among the antecedents and consequences of Chinese graduate students' academic writing anxiety. Results of data analysis showed that when students endorsed fixed mindset, they tended to have higher levels of writing anxiety, as well as lower levels of academic writing self-efficacy. On the contrary, when students had a stronger endorsement of growth mindset, they tended to have higher levels of academic writing self-efficacy. However, students' growth mindset was not significantly associated with their levels of academic writing anxiety. Students' perceived competence for academic writing had a significant moderation effect on the relationship between growth mindset and writing self-efficacy. When students perceived higher competence for academic writing, the relationship between growth mindset and writing self-efficacy became weaker. When students had lower levels of perceived competence, the relationship between growth mindset and writing self-efficacy was stronger. Both students' perceived competence and their writing self-efficacy accounted for students' use of self-regulated strategies. That meant, when students had higher perceived competence and/or higher writing self-efficacy, they tended to use self-regulated writing strategies more often. In turn, students' use of self-regulated writing strategies, together with perceived competence, was positively associated with students' self-satisfaction with their academic writing. The dissertation study had both theoretical and pedagogical implications. The study provided valuable information on mindsets, perceived competence, and writing anxiety, which is relevant for Chinese international graduate students, graduate students experiencing writing anxiety, professors, academic advisors, and writing center staff. The findings of the study underlined the importance of overcoming fixed mindset and cultivating growth mindset, as well as improving writing competence and using self-regulation. The present study can also help pave the path for future research on related topics. Keywords: writing anxiety; growth mindset; fixed mindset; writing self-efficacy; self-regulated writing; perceived competence for writing; self-satisfaction with academic writing; writing with English as second language</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Psychology and Learning Systems in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">November 15, 2022.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">mindset, perceived competence for writing, self-regulated writing, writing anxiety, writing self-efficacy, writing with English as second language</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jeannine E. Turner, Professor Directing Dissertation; Gretchen Sunderman, University Representative; Yanyun Yang, Committee Member; Alysia Roehrig, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041141">
      <mods:topic>Educational psychology</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Liang_fsu_0071E_17554</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Psychology and Learning Systems</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
