<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>FMRP Mechanism of Circuit Development and Dynamics in the Auditory Brainstem</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-4877-0114</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Yu</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Xiaoyan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2012060736">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Grzywacz</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Joseph G.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n89663601">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hyson</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Richard Lee</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/yz15e">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Zhou</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Yi</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Graduate Research Assistant)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rtomko">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Tomko</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Robert J.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="termsOfAddress">Jr.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Medicine</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Biomedical Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (185 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Fragile X syndrome (FXS) is a leading monogenetic cause of intellectual disability and autism. It is caused by transcriptional silencing of the FMR1 gene and the resultant loss of its product, Fragile X mental retardation protein (FMRP). Individuals with FXS display prominent sensory dysfunction including acoustic hyperactivity and compromised hearing in noise, which emerge at young ages. Animal studies have revealed maladaptive developmental events caused by the absence of FMRP, including delays in axonal and synaptic development as well as alterations in experience-dependent neuronal plasticity. These cellular abnormalities may underlie sensory processing deficits in FXS but show high regional- and time-specificity. Thus, whether and how individual developmental events contribute to the emergence and progress of circuit alterations are largely unknown. In addition, the precise sites of FMRP action in regulating these cellular and circuit pathophysiology remain elusive. In this dissertation, we dissected the role of FMRP in synaptic tonotopic development, afferent regulation of neuronal dynamics during developmental critical periods, and the association with the emergence of auditory processing problems by focusing on the auditory brainstem circuit using mouse and chicken as model organisms. In Chapter 2, we characterized the developmental distributions of key presynaptic neurotransmitter-releasing machinery in the mouse developing medial nucleus of the trapezoid body, a major auditory nucleus receiving excitatory inputs from the cochlear nucleus and serving as an inhibitory station for further processing. We identified novel tonotopic gradients of selective presynaptic proteins in immature auditory synapses in the first postnatal week, which gradually flattened before the onset of hearing (around postnatal day 12-14). In Fmr1 (human FMR1 homolog) knockout (KO) mice, a mouse model of FXS, progress to achieve the mature-like organization was selectively altered in some presynaptic proteins. These results provide a potential mechanism that may contribute to tonotopic differentiation of neurotransmission in the auditory system during normal and abnormal development. In Chapter 3, we examined how afferent deprivation affects the cellular FMRP dynamics and the association with neuronal reorganizations in the chicken cochlear nucleus, an auditory nucleus receiving afferent inputs from the cochlea. We observed rapid aggregation of FMRP immunoreactivity into large granular structures in a subset of neurons following afferent deprivation, and the persistent FMRP aggregation was associated with neuronal cell death in these neurons. In the surviving neurons, FMRP level was correlated with multiple types of neuronal responses and synaptic rearrangements, suggesting a potential role of FMRP in afferent-regulated neuronal dynamics. In Chapter 4, we investigated how loss of FMRP affects the afferent regulation of neuronal dynamics within a critical period in the mouse ventral cochlear nucleus (VCN), identified the relationship between the closure of the critical period and the onset of auditory experience, and determined a peripheral site of FMRP in regulating these events. We found that a critical period for VCN neuronal loss in response to deafferentation was preserved in Fmr1 KO mice, and within this critical period, the degree of neuronal loss was unchanged. However, the closure of the critical period for neuronal cell death was delayed and temporally coincidental with reduced hearing sensitivity in the absence of FMRP. Furthermore, selective deletion of FMRP expression in spiral ganglion neurons recapitulated the delay in VCN critical period closure, similar to Fmr1 KO mice. This study identified a novel involvement of cochlear FMRP in shaping the temporal features of neuronal critical periods in the brain, and highlighted a peripheral mechanism of neurodevelopmental pathogenesis.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Biomedical Sciences in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">October 26, 2022.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">afferent influence, brain development, critical period, Fragile X syndrome, hearing onset, synaptic maturation</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Yuan Wang, Professor Directing Dissertation; Joseph G. Grzywacz, University Representative; Richard L. Hyson, Committee Member; Yi Zhou, Committee Member; Robert J. Tomko, Jr., Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91006099">
      <mods:topic>Neurosciences</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">Yu_fsu_0071E_17537</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Biomedical Sciences</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-11-21T09:18:06.375442-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
