<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>That's Not That Bad</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Epistemic Injustice, Moral Testimony, and the Harm in Dismissing Judgments of Wrongdoing</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Amoroso</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Rachel</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ehinchman">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hinchman</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Edward</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/smay">
      <mods:namePart type="family">May</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Simon Căbulea</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Philosophy</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_bdcc">master thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (40 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>In "Epistemic Injustice: Power and the Ethics of Knowing", Miranda Fricker offers a framework of the ways in which an agent can be wronged in her capacity as a knower. According to Fricker, epistemic injustice comes in two interrelated forms: testimonial injustice and hermeneutical injustice. Testimonial injustice consists in a hearer assigning a "deflated level of credibility" to a speaker's word, owing to a negative identity prejudice the hearer holds about the speaker. Hermeneutical injustice is purely structural and consists in a speaker's inability (or difficulty) to render their experiences intelligible to others. This paper expands on Fricker's view by distinguishing between descriptive testimony and prescriptive (moral) testimony. I argue that Fricker's view limits itself to cases of descriptive testimony, and therefore fails to track wrongs unique to cases of testimonial injustice involving moral claims. I go on to define the main harm in dismissing moral claims as moral objectification and argue that it wrongs a speaker by treating them as lacking the capacity to reliably form moral judgments. This in turn, excludes them from the community of moral agents with standing to make demands. To illustrate how this form of testimonial injustice has distinct wrong-making features, I discuss Professor Anita Hill's historic testimony during Justice Clarence Thomas's 1991 confirmation hearing. Hill's testimony does more than offer a report about the sexual harassment she faced while working with Justice Thomas. It also evaluates his behavior as wrong and issues a demand on the committee members to factor her testimony into their own evaluation of Thomas's character. In assigning a credibility deficit to the prescriptive component of Hill's testimony, this demand is thwarted and Hill's testimony is denied the appropriate normative force. Hill herself is also treated as though she cannot accurately judge the normative content of her own experiences. Fricker's framework does not have the machinery to fully capture the epistemic injustice perpetrated in cases of moral testimony like Anita Hill's. Distinguishing between descriptive vs. prescriptive testimony equips Fricker's view with the tools to track more cases of testimonial injustice and expand on the wrong-making features of epistemic injustice. To illustrate how this form of testimonial injustice has distinct wrong-making features, I discuss Professor Anita Hill's historic testimony during Justice Clarence Thomas's 1991 confirmation hearing. Hill's testimony does more than offer a report about the sexual harassment she faced while working with Justice Thomas. It also evaluates his behavior as wrong and issues a demand on the committee members to factor her testimony into their own evaluation of Thomas's character. In assigning a credibility deficit to the prescriptive component of Hill's testimony, this demand is thwarted and Hill's testimony is denied the appropriate normative force. Hill herself is also treated as though she cannot accurately judge the normative content of her own experiences. Fricker's framework does not have the machinery to fully capture the epistemic injustice perpetrated in cases of moral testimony like Anita Hill's. Distinguishing between descriptive vs. prescriptive testimony equips Fricker's view with the tools to track more cases of testimonial injustice and expand on the wrong-making features of epistemic injustice. Chapter one of this paper will outline Fricker's account of epistemic injustice and the cases she uses to illustrate how it is perpetrated in linguistic exchange. Chapter two will focus on the distinction between descriptive, Fricker-style testimony and prescriptive testimony. I will analyze Anita Hill's statement to the Senate Judiciary Committee in the context of testimonial injustice and isolate the morally relevant ways in which it differs from the examples of epistemic injustice Fricker's account offers. Chapter three will explain why it is useful for a theory of epistemic injustice to distinguish between testimonies issuing reports and testimonies issuing moral judgments that place demands on a hearer. Here I will also consider some potential objections Fricker might raise against my view that dismissal of prescriptive testimony consists in wrong-making features distinct from those she picks out her own framework. Chapter four will outline my concept of moral objectification, a harm that results from the discrediting of moral testimony. I will discuss how this concept maps on to certain abuse tactics already being discussed within feminist discourse out in the world. I conclude by further elucidating the upshot of my proposed distinction between prescriptive and descriptive testimony and how it bears on other discussions of power-based harm within feminist philosophy more broadly.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Thesis submitted to the Department of Philosophy in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Masters of Arts.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Summer Semester 2019.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 21, 2019.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Anita Hill, Epistemic Injustice, Feminist Philosophy, Miranda Fricker, Moral Psychology, Social Epistemology</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Andrea Westlund, Professor Directing Thesis; Edward Hinchman, Committee Member; Simon May, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85045096">
      <mods:topic>Ethics</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85072732">
      <mods:topic>Knowledge, Theory of</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85147771">
      <mods:topic>Women's studies</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2019_Summer_Amoroso_fsu_0071N_15359</identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Master of Arts</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Masters</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Philosophy</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2020-01-08T16:41:25.408-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
