<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo xmlns="" lang="eng">
      <title>Curriculum Delivered, a Curriculum Remembered</title>
      <subTitle>An Alumni Study of an Undergraduate Concentration in Writing and Rhetoric</subTitle>
      <nonSort>A</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name xmlns="" type="personal" authority="local">
      <namePart type="family">Maynard</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Travis</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name xmlns=""
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n91108860">
      <namePart type="family">Yancey</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kathleen Blake</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1950-</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name xmlns=""
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2012011678">
      <namePart type="family">Dennen</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Vanessa P.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1970-</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name xmlns=""
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2010050868">
      <namePart type="family">Neal</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Michael R.</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name xmlns=""
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n98010396">
      <namePart type="family">Graban</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Tarez Samra</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name xmlns=""
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name xmlns="" type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name xmlns="" type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of English</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource xmlns="">text</typeOfResource>
   <genre xmlns="" authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre xmlns=""
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo xmlns="">
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language xmlns="">
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription xmlns="">
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (294 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract xmlns="">This dissertation explores the impact and influence of undergraduate major programs in writing and rhetoric on the lives of their students through an alumni study of the Editing, Writing, and Media (EWM) major at Florida State University. Building on prior alumni studies in the field of Rhetoric and Composition, this study captures a capacious portrait of alumni lives prior to, during, and after their time within the EWM program. Framing this portrait is Kathleen Blakey Yancey's three-part curricular framework of the delivered curriculum (the institutional materials that instantiate a course of study), lived curriculum (students' prior knowledge and experience they draw upon in a course or program) , and experienced curriculum (a student's unique set of experiences in a major program). In order to account for alumni lives following graduation, this project theorizes a fourth curriculum known as the remembered, comprised of the elements of a student's experienced curriculum that influence their subsequent lives of alumni. Three questions guide this study: 1) How do alumni retrospectively perceive their experience and knowledge prior to enrolling in a major program as influencing their experiences in an undergraduate writing major? 2) What elements of an undergraduate major curriculum do alumni perceive and report as contributors to their lives after graduation? 3) How do alumni of this undergraduate writing major perceive and report the influence of their experiences in an undergraduate writing major on their lives after graduation? To address these research questions, the study relies on an alumni survey and three interview case studies, with each case study containing two mapping activities. The survey collects demographic information from EWM alumni, alongside their reasons for enrolling in the major (lived curriculum), their perceptions of their learning within the EWM program (experienced curriculum), their academic and professional experiences following graduation, current writing tasks, perceptions of how the EWM program has influenced those experiences, and perceptions of how well the EWM program prepared them to meet the program's outcomes (remembered curriculum). The interview protocol asks alumni to create two maps of their a) experiences at Florida State University and b) current writing tasks, and document their perceived connections among the elements within each map; after alumni the complete those maps, I ask them semistructured interview questions about their perceived relationships between and among their lived and experienced curricula and how they influence the remembered curricula in their current lives. The data generated by the survey and case studies provide insight into the lived, experienced, and remembered curricula of EWM alumni. The lived curriculum is most prominently defined by two factors: first, alumni's prior writing experiences, and second, their aspirations to pursue careers related to writing. Alumni cite structured writing environments like courses and/or co-curricular activities and self-sponsored writing tasks like fiction and/or blogging as both leading them to enroll in the program and shaping their course projects. Further, a large portion of alumni believe the EWM program would prepare them to write within professional environments including but not limited to the publishing industry. The experienced curriculum shows that alumni benefit from the gateway courses of Writing and Editing in Print and Online (WEPO) and Rhetoric and their required internship, as these experiences prepare them to compose rhetorical texts for a variety of contexts and within multiple genres. However, alumni feel they were less prepared to engage with the visual dimensions of composing and work within advanced composing technologies. Additionally, alumni consistently rely on a sense of pragmatism to identify elements of the EWM program that they retrospectively value, frequently benefitting from experiences they are able to adapt into their own writing. The remembered curriculum shows that the EWM program prepares alumni to enter into a range of academic and professional opportunities, with 40% entering postgraduate study and 93.7% finding employment following graduation; alumni consistently feel the EWM program positively influences these experiences. Personal and professional writing are the most frequent types of writing alumni complete, with 78% completing some form of self-sponsored writing and 70% writing more than ten hours a week for their occupations. In describing their current writing processes, alumni exhibit varying degrees of rhetorical awareness, with their explanations tethered to concepts such as context, audience, and genre guiding their rhetorical decision-making processes. Together, these results illustrate the influence of alumni's prior writing on their rhetorical education within undergraduate majors, emphasize the importance of praxis for alums' experienced curricula, and exhibit the varying ways in which undergraduate major programs can influence the writing lives of its alumni.</abstract>
   <note xmlns="" displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of English in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note xmlns="" displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Summer Semester 2019.</note>
   <note xmlns="" displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 14, 2019.</note>
   <note xmlns="" displayLabel="Keywords">Alumni Study, Rhetoric and Composition, Undergraduate Majors, Writing and Rhetoric</note>
   <note xmlns="" displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note xmlns="" displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Kathleen Blake Yancey, Professor Directing Dissertation; Vanessa Paz Dennen, University Representative; Michael Neal, Committee Member; Tarez Samra Graban, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject xmlns=""
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113628">
      <topic>Rhetoric</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier xmlns="" type="IID">2019_Summer_Maynard_fsu_0071E_15302</identifier>
   <extension xmlns="">
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>English</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo xmlns="">
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2020-01-08T16:41:25.408-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
