<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Re-Defining Fatherhood</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Examining the Multidimensionality of Black Fatherhood and Its Association to Child Misconduct and Father-Child Relationship Quality</mods:subTitle>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Armstrong</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Joslyn C. (Joslyn Chevette)</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n90646756">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Rehm</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Marsha Lynn</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Professor Directing Dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/fjordan">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Jackson</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Felecia Jordan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">University Representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2010019434">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Cui</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Ming</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="termsOfAddress">1971-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jkimmes">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Kimmes</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Jonathan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2003032850">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Harris</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Gregory</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Human Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Family and Child Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (120 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Black Fatherhood is an understudied area of inquiry within the fatherhood literature. Historically father involvement was examined through three primary dimensions of responsibility, accessibility, and engagement. However, Black father involvement differs in terms of contact, support, and residency in comparison than other racial-ethnic fathers. They face distinct barriers in education, income, incarceration, employment, residency, and depression factors. All of these contextual and structural factors have been shown to influence father involvement. Researchers have yet to define father involvement for Black men including structural dimensions. Researchers have begun to examine father involvement from a multi-faceted perspective. Additionally, researchers have begun to include multidimensional conceptual models grounded in theory when measuring fatherhood. Researchers will need to continue to integrate cultural, economic, and social dimensions to Black fatherhood experiences. Thus, the purpose of this dissertation was to explore expanding the definition of father involvement for Black men to include relational and structural dimensions. The conceptual model was guided by both masculinity and feminist theories and the cultural ecological theory. The theories on gender were used to validate the inclusion of defining fatherhood traditionally with the provider role as well as validate that Black fatherhood was marginalized by traditional fatherhood expectations. The cultural ecological theory supported use of a contextual and ecological perspective using the structural dimensions that were culturally specific to Black father experiences. The research questions for the dissertation were: 1) what is the factor structure underling the 30 items of: relational dimensions of accessibility, contact, and responsibility; and structural dimensions of incarceration history, depression, employment, income, education, and residency status?; 2) what is the association between father interaction and financial provider with child misconduct?; and 3) what is the association between father interaction and financial provider with father-child relationship quality? The researcher conducted an exploratory factor analysis to address research question one that suggested a possible four factor structure for the definition of father involvement for Black men. However, the reliability and correlations for the structural dimensions within the father involvement variable were below standard requirements. Thus, according to the results, there was not enough statistical support to validate the need for a multidimensional definition for Black father involvement. Black father involvement was not defined using structural components. However, the results suggested that Black fatherhood could be defined by contextual and structural components, even if there were minimal percentages. Additionally, the relational factors were used to uncover their association with child misconduct and father-child relationship quality. The researcher conducted two multiple regression analysis models to address research questions two and three. Father interaction and financial provider were significant predictors of child misconduct. The covariates of incarceration, employment, education, and income were significantly associated with child misconduct. Then, father interaction and financial provider were significant predictors of father-child relationship quality. Income was significantly associated with father-child relationship quality. Implications for researchers and clinicians were addressed.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Family and Child Sciences in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Spring Semester 2019.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 26, 2019.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Black Fatherhood, Child misconduct, Cultural Ecological Theory, Father-child relationship quality, Father involvement, Feminist Theory</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Marsha Rehm, Professor Directing Dissertation; Felecia Jordan Jackson, University Representative; Ming Cui, Committee Member; Jonathan Kimmes, Committee Member; Gregory Harris, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <identifier type="IID">2019_Spring_Armstrong_fsu_0071E_15017</identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Family and Child Sciences</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2019-10-14T16:36:31.241-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
