<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>M-DCPS iHEAT Experience</mods:title>
      <mods:subTitle>Teacher Perceptions of the Relationship between the Program and Instructional Practices</mods:subTitle>
      <mods:nonSort>The</mods:nonSort>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Pham</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Kathleen T.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/szuilkowski">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Zuilkowski</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Stephanie Simmons</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Professor Directing Dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n96043409">
      <mods:namePart type="family">McDowell</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Stephen D.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="termsOfAddress">1958-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">University Representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2003057796">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Akiba</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Motoko</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n83046519">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Schwartz</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Robert A.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">Committee Member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Education</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (122 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>This qualitative case study examined the professional development practices at 2 of the 9 schools involved in the Incentives for Highly Effective Administrators and Teachers (iHEAT) Program in Miami-Dade County Public Schools from 2013-2017. The iHEAT Program was funded through a Teacher Incentive Fund (TIF) grant and provided participating schools with Peer Review Teachers who were fully released from classroom duties and served as full time instructional coaches, and provided job-embedded professional development. The program also awarded stipends for certain professional development activities and for highly effective teaching performance, as measured by the district’s teacher evaluation system. This research was conducted to determine how the teachers who participated in the program both experienced the program and perceived the relationship between those experiences and their instructional practices. Background on the history of professional development, important definitions, and current professional learning standards are all provided. The literature review starts with studies giving the definition and history of professional development in the United States. It then builds on that information by summarizing research on the current state of professional development in the United States and in other countries. The review also provides a local context, by explaining the state of professional learning in Florida generally, and in Miami-Dade County Public Schools, specifically. Finally, it explores the research on the importance of the teacher as a factor in instructional effectiveness. Some gaps in the literature on professional learning are identified. iHEAT participating teachers were interviewed, and the data collected illustrate the experiences and perceptions of the teachers. An analysis of these data shows the teachers’ perceptions of the relationship between those experiences and their instructional practices. Administrators at the 2 schools, including both principals and assistant principals, also participated in interviews designed to determine how they viewed the program and the teachers’ experiences, as well as whether they perceived a relationship between the teachers’ participation and their instructional practices. The interview data indicate that the iHEAT Program was positively received in the schools, that teachers learned and grew from their experiences, and that there are some practices which will continue in the schools after the conclusion of the program. Teachers and administrators noted improvements in the school culture and collaboration. They also provided examples of differentiation and increased use of data analysis in their practice. In addition, the educators reported aspects of the educational practices implemented during iHEAT that remain in the schools and contribute to the ongoing professional growth of the teachers. This study also provides lessons learned and conclusions about what aspects of the iHEAT professional development practices might be useful for educators in other contexts. District staff considering peer review programs, teacher leaders developing professional learning experiences, and classroom teachers involved in coaching programs all might find the results of this study relevant. As educational institutions shift from traditional professional development models to more collaborative modes of learning, for both teachers and students, a new approach is needed, and this study will suggest policies and practices that might be studied further or replicated.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Leadership and Policy Studies in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Education.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Spring Semester 2019.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">February 19, 2019.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">peer review, professional development, professional learning, professional learning communities, teacher evaluation, teacher quality</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Stephanie Zuilkowski, Professor Directing Dissertation; Stephen McDowell, University Representative; Motoko Akiba, Committee Member; Robert A. Schwartz, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989">
      <mods:topic>Education</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86007568">
      <mods:topic>Educational evaluation</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001254">
      <mods:topic>Educational leadership</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2019_Spring_Pham_fsu_0071E_14987</identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Education</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Leadership and Policy Studies</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2019-10-14T16:36:31.241-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
