<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Regulation of DNA Replication Initiation, DNA Stress Response, and Mitotic Exit in Budding Yeast</title>
      <nonSort>The</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-0399-1749</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Haluska</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Cory M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ywang8">
      <namePart type="family">Wang</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Yanchang</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Biomedical Sciences Professor)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/hyu">
      <namePart type="family">Yu</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Hong-Guo</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rtomko">
      <namePart type="family">Tomko</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Robert J.</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">Jr.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/agunjan">
      <namePart type="family">Gunjan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Akash</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Medicine</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Biomedical Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (114 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Tight regulation of the cell cycle is essential to maintain genome integrity. Errors at any stage during cell cycle, including replication, chromosome segregation, and mitotic exit, can lead to genome instability, which has been shown to contribute to tumorigenesis or cell death. Despite the importance of these cellular processes, many of their molecular mechanisms are still not fully understood. We used budding yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae as a model organism to investigate cell cycle regulation because this organism is genetically tractable and much of the processes during cell cycle are conserved from yeast to humans. In budding yeast, Mcm10 is an essential DNA replication factor that interacts strongly with the Mcm2-7 complex, a conserved helicase in all eukaryotes. Within the Mcm2-7 complex, Mcm10 has been shown to interact with both the Mcm2 and Mcm6 subunits. We have been able to show that Mcm10 has DNA binding capability but the function of this binding has yet to be determined. Additionally, we have shown that Mcm10 is able to bind to RPA, the single-stranded DNA (ssDNA) binding protein, and this interaction is strengthened in the presence of ssDNA. Assembly of the DNA replication machinery, replisome, at replication origins is largely driven by the phosphorylation imposed by Dbf4-dependent kinase (DDK) and cyclin-dependent kinase (CDK). Inactivation of DDK via a cdc7-1 mutant disrupts the interaction between Mcm10 and Mcm2, indicating a potential earlier role during replication for Mcm10 than previously anticipated. Selective depletion of Mcm10 via an iAID (auxin-induced degradation) system decreases Mcm2 chromatin association. Therefore, we speculate that Mcm10 functions during the early stage of DNA replication initiation by maintaining the stable chromatin association of the Mcm2-7 helicase. DNA replication stress activates the S-phase checkpoint that arrests the cell cycle, but it is poorly understood how cells recover from this arrest. CDK and Protein Phosphatase 2A (PP2A) with the B regulatory subunit Cdc55 (PP2A^(Cdc55)) are key cell cycle regulators in budding yeast. We found that yeast cells lacking functional PP2A^(Cdc55) showed slow growth in the presence of hydroxyurea (HU), a DNA synthesis inhibitor, without obvious viability loss. Moreover, PP2A mutants exhibited delayed anaphase entry and sustained levels of anaphase inhibitor Pds1 after HU treatment. A DNA damage checkpoint Chk1 phosphorylates and stabilizes Pds1. We showed that chk1Δ and mutation of the Chk1 phosphorylation sites in Pds1 largely restored efficient anaphase entry in PP2A mutants after HU treatment. In addition, deletion of SWE1 that encodes the inhibitory kinase for CDK or mutation of the Swe1 phosphorylation site in CDK (cdc28F19) also suppressed the anaphase entry delay in PP2A mutants after HU treatment. Our genetic data suggest that Swe1/CDK acts upstream of Pds1. Surprisingly, cdc55Δ showed significant suppression to the viability loss of S-phase checkpoint mutants during DNA synthesis block. Cell cycle-regulated protein modifications, such as phosphorylation and ubiquitination, are critical for a successful cell duplication. Protein SUMOylation is a biochemical process that adds a small ubiquitin-like modifier (SUMO) to protein lysine residues. Elimination of SUMOylation in yeast cells results in cell cycle arrest, indicating the essential role of this modification in the cell cycle. Protein poly-SUMOylation has been shown to trigger its ubiquitination, and the subsequent extraction and/or proteasomal degradation. Cdc14 phosphatase not only antagonizes the phosphorylation imposed by CDK but also triggers CDK inactivation. Therefore, Cdc14 is essential for mitotic exit, a process that inactivates CDK. Prior to anaphase entry, Cdc14 is sequestered within the nucleolus through two anchor proteins Tof2 and Net1. Interestingly, these two proteins are subjected to SUMOylation. Our results indicate that SUMOylation does not play a role in Cdc14 nucleolar localization, but polySUMOylation appears to promote nucleolar delocalization of Net1 and Tof2. Additionally, we found that Tof2 degradation is dependent on the ubiquitination mediated by both SUMO-targeted ubiquitin ligase (STUbL) and Anaphase Promoting Complex (APC), a E3 ubiquitin ligase essential for anaphase entry. These observations support a two-step ubiquitination model for the degradation of SUMOylated proteins as well as a potential role for polySUMOylation in mitotic exit by triggering Cdc14 release from the nucleolus. Taken together, our results have identified Mcm10 as a potential scaffold protein ensuring chromatin association of the Mcm2-7 helicase during single strand extrusion, a process essential for the initiation of DNA replication. We have uncovered a PP2A-Swe1-CDK-Chk1-Pds1 axis that promotes recovery from DNA replication stress. Lastly, our results indicate that polySUMOylation may promote mitotic exit by delocalizing Cdc14 anchor proteins Tof2 and Net1 from the nucleolus. Furthermore, our results indicate that STUbL and E3 ligase APC are likely involved in proteasomal degradation of nucleolar protein Tof2, supporting a model that two-step ubiquitination of SUMO substrates promotes their proteasomal degradation. The findings presented in the thesis demonstrate several new layers of cell cycle regulations, which may provide new therapeutic strategies with regards to cancer and other cell-based therapies.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Biomedical Sciences in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">November 16, 2021.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">DNA Replication, Mcm10, Mitotic exit, PP2A, SUMO, Swe1</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Yanchang Wang, Professor Directing Dissertation; Hong-Guo Yu, University Representative; Robert J. Tomko, Jr., Committee Member; Akash Gunjan, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85035240">
      <topic>Cytology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086577">
      <topic>Molecular biology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014171">
      <topic>Biochemistry</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">2021_Fall_Haluska_fsu_0071E_16863</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Biomedical Sciences</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-05-23T16:09:53.352975-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
