<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Structural Equation Modeling Analysis of Chinese Undergraduate English Language Learners' Classroom Engagement</title>
      <nonSort>A</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-1960-5347</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Wei</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Maipeng</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jeturner">
      <namePart type="family">Turner</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jeannine E.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/gsunderm">
      <namePart type="family">Sunderman</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Gretchen L.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/yyang3">
      <namePart type="family">Yang</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Yanyun</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/phiver">
      <namePart type="family">Hiver</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Philip V.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Education</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Educational Psychology and Learning Systems</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (188 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Previous studies have suggested that students' classroom engagement (i.e., their involvement in a class, Lin, 2012) is one significant factor that could explain their academic achievement (Skinner et al., 2009). Both students' individual factors and classroom environmental factors play important roles in explaining their classroom engagement (Bundick et al., 2014). The present study integrated and analyzed both types of factors to provide a comprehensive understanding of Chinese undergraduate English-as-a-Foreign-Language students' classroom engagement. Students' individual factors in the present study included their learning-motivations at different levels of proximity to their classroom engagement (i.e., distal motives and proximal motivations). The distal motives included four dispositional tendencies, i.e., their hope for success (i.e., the desire to achieve success, Thrash &amp; Eliot, 2002), fear of failure (i.e., the tendency to avoid failure, Thrash &amp; Eliot, 2002), growth-seeking tendency (i.e., a tendency towards self-improvement and self-growth, Dykman, 1998) and validation-seeking tendency (i.e., a tendency to prove basic worth, self-competence, and likability, Dykman, 1998). The proximal motivations were domain-specific, specifically including students' subjective value of learning English and their self-efficacy (i.e., perceived abilities) for accomplishing English tasks). Two classroom environmental factors were also involved in the present study, including students' perceptions of mastery goal structure (i.e., a classroom in which mastery of skills and self-improvement are emphasized, Diseth &amp; Samdal, 2015) and performance goal structure (i.e., a classroom in which achievement and performance-comparisons among students are emphasized, Diseth &amp; Samdal, 2015). Using online surveys, the present study included Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) analysis to investigate 1) individual and classroom environmental factors as antecedents, 2) academic achievement as the important outcome of students' classroom engagement, and 3) the classroom environmental factors as moderators of the relationships among students' proximal motivations (i.e., examples of individual factors) and classroom engagement. A total of 2,982 freshmen and sophomores from six universities in China participated in the present study. The results revealed that students' proximal motivations (i.e., the subjective value of learning English and self-efficacy for accomplishing English tasks) directly predicted their classroom engagement. Students' distal motives did not directly predict their classroom engagement. Students' subjective value of learning English fully mediated the relationship between their hope for success and classroom engagement as well as the relationship between their growth-seeking tendency and the classroom engagement. Students' self-efficacy for accomplishing English tasks completely mediated the relationship between their hope for success and classroom engagement and the relationship between their fear of failure and classroom engagement. Students' validation-seeking tendency did not predict their classroom engagement, neither directly nor indirectly. Furthermore, students' classroom engagement positively predicted their academic achievement. In addition, the two classroom environmental factors (i.e., students' perceptions of classroom goal structures) directly explained their classroom engagement. However, the relationships of students' proximal motivations and classroom engagement were not significantly different when comparing students who rated classroom goal structures (mastery goals, performance goals) high and those who rated classroom goal structures low.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Educational Psychology and Learning Systems in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">November 17, 2021.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jeannine E. Turner, Professor Directing Dissertation; Gretchen Sunderman, University Representative; Yanyun Yang, Committee Member; Phil Hiver, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041141">
      <topic>Educational psychology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">2021_Fall_Wei_fsu_0071E_16888</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Educational Psychology and Learning Systems</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-05-23T16:09:53.352975-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
