<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Diffractive Ethnography of Becoming Reggio-Inspired Teachers in Taiwan</title>
      <nonSort>A</nonSort>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-2449-4741</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Yang</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Hsiu-Chun</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007010325">
      <namePart type="family">Broome</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jeffrey L. (Jeffrey Lynn)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="viaf"
         authorityURI="http://viaf.org/viaf/"
         valueURI="http://viaf.org/viaf/1152380012501761724">
      <namePart type="family">Fendler</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Rachel Loveitt</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2011024781">
      <namePart type="family">Jones</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ithel</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/skshields">
      <namePart type="family">Shields</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Sara Scott</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Fine Arts</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Art Education</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (342 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Due to the greater attention on child-centered and creative pedagogies, the Reggio Emilia approach (REA) has become a famous and favored approach worldwide since 1991. More and more educators apply REA to foreign contexts and realize the adaptations are necessary outside of Italy. This study investigates the possibilities of implementing REA with concerns of adaptations in Taiwan, especially in art education. Studying the roles of art and the story of becoming Reggio-inspired are the primary foci for the REA adaption investigation. REA is an intra-active pedagogy that emphasizes material engagements and the agential flow between humans and non-humans. In line with the intra-active disposition, this study employs a diffractive ethnography to inquiry a Reggio-inspired preschool, Little Heart (LH), in Taiwan. This study was conducted from August 2018 to July 2019. The participants were three classroom teachers in the kindergarten class and the principal in LH. Observation, intraview, and diffractive journaling are the applied research methods in this diffractive ethnography. The investigation can divide into two phases. The first phase was mainly to understand the LH's Reggio-inspired history through observing the teachers' teaching, intraviewing the stories of being LH teachers, and creating artworks about their teaching philosophy. The investigation shows that LH marks the learning values on child-centeredness, emergent curriculum, learning autonomy, collaboration, and reflection. Among the values, LH manifests the roles of art in documentation, experiential learning, and reflective thinking. Nevertheless, the researcher discovered several conflicts about knowledge examination and material usages in a hierarchical relationship between adults and children, verbal and graphics. To ease the conflicts, the researcher, as an art education consultor, co-worked with the three classroom teachers to search for the possibility of being Reggio-inspired at the subsequent investigation. The co-working experiences were the entangled efforts between the three teachers and the researcher working in a dialogical situation. The entangled efforts discovered that when teachers treat the examined concept as an open question, both the teacher and the students can construct knowledge by learning from others in the project. Moreover, materials could be implemented for improving knowledge examination by serving materials as communicating and connecting relations instead of only documenting the learning results. The space that the researcher, the principal, and the three teachers created can inform several possibilities of becoming Reggio-inspired. A space for becoming Reggio-inspired can build a sense of belonging and a two-way relationship, meet others, and welcome to become different. Moreover, the visual diary practices positively influenced for teachers to become Reggio-inspired through involving in concepts, materials, and emotion. The inventive findings at the second phase indicate a grassroots model as feasible to adapt REA in Taiwan. Building a flexible and dialogical environment is significant for the leaders to consider the school operation. Individual teachers could keep mind-open toward being Reggio-inspired by questioning the concept and innovating material usages. Further studies are required to go deep and wide for the REA adaptations in Taiwan or other contexts.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Art Education in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">November 9, 2021.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">art education, diffractive ethnography, early childhood art education, Reggio Emilia approach, Reggio-inspired</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jeffery Broome, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Rachel Fendler, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Ithel Jones, University Representative; Sara Scott Shields, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007505">
      <topic>Art</topic>
      <topic>Study and teaching</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">2021_Fall_Yang_fsu_0071E_16878</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Art Education</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-05-23T16:09:53.352975-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
