<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Impact of Creatine Supplementation on Vascular Endothelial Function, Blood Flow and Functional Capacity in Older Adults</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-3276-596X</mods:nameIdentifier>
      <mods:namePart type="family">Clarke</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Holly Elizabeth</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/rhickner">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hickner</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Robert C.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="date">1962-</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/williams">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Williams</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Diana L.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016106104">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Ormsbee</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Michael J.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/bsgordon">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Gordon</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Bradley S.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Health and Human Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Nutrition and Integrative Physiology</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2021</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (216 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>INTRODUCTION: Cardiovascular disease (CVD) remains the leading cause of mortality in United States (US) [1], and the inevitable process of aging, or one's age, remains the primary unmodifiable risk factor and independent predictor of CVD events across the lifespan [2]. With aging comes a progressive deterioration in vascular health, characterized by arterial stiffening and endothelial dysfunction (ED) [3-5]. Furthermore, oxidative stress, marked by an accumulation of reactive oxygen species (ROS), increases with age and is a prominent feature of vascular disease [6]. These vascular changes, in addition to other age-related declines in strength and cognition, all contribute to reduced functionality in many older adults. While popular dietary interventions have been applauded for their benefits upon cardiovascular health [7, 8], there is emerging evidence that suggests creatine supplementation may also serve as a therapeutic supplement [9]. Although well known for its metabolic properties, recent research has exposed a much broader application for creatine in clinical populations, acting as an antioxidant, energy shuttle and neuroprotective compound [10-12]. Despite these benefits however, there is scarce information on the application of creatine for vascular health and functional capacity in older adults. PURPOSE: Thus, the purpose of this study was to determine the effects of 4 weeks of creatine monohydrate supplementation, as compared to placebo, on vascular endothelial function, blood flow, oxidative stress, and functional capacity in older adults. Methods: Twelve, healthy older adults (M = 6, W = 6, age: 58 ± 3 years, BMI: 26 ± 6) participated in this randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled crossover study. Eligible participants completed 4 official study visits: Pre-Testing 1, Post-Test 1, Pre-Testing 2, Post-Test 2. At every study visit participants were fasted and completed anthropometric assessments (height, weight, BMI), body composition [dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry (DXA)], and venous blood draw. Participants then completed assessments of vascular function [flow mediated dilation (FMD%), brachial-ankle pulse wave velocity (baPWV), pulse wave analysis (PWA), near-infrared microvascular reperfusion (NIRS MOXY)], cognitive function [forward digit span test (FDS), backward digit span test (BDS), trail making test part A (TMT-A) and B (TMT-B)], and physical function [6-minute walking test (6MWT), BioDex assessment of isometric muscle strength and endurance]. Once all Pre-Testing assessments were complete, participants were randomized to receive one of two blinded supplements: placebo (maltodextrin) or creatine monohydrate. Participants were asked to consume supplements for the following 4 weeks (4 x 5 g/day for 5 days, followed by 1 x 5g for 23 days). Following supplementation, participants returned for Post-Testing. During this visit, all procedures from the Pre-Testing Visit were repeated. Participants were then asked to return to their normal daily lifestyles for a 4-week "wash-out" period. After the washout, participants returned for their second Pre-Testing visit. Following this, participants were given their remaining supplement. Following the final supplementation, participants returned to the lab to complete their final Post-Test visit. Results: After creatine supplementation there was a significant improvement in FMD% (Pre: 7.68 ± 2.25 %, Post: 8.9 ± 1.99 %; p &lt; .005), absolute change in diameter (Pre: 0.33 ± 0.12 mm, Post: 0.38 ± 0.12 mm; p &lt; .05), normalized FMD% (Pre: 2.57E-04 ± 1.03E-04 %/SSAUC, Post: 3.42E-04 ± 1.69E-04 %/SSAUC; p &lt; .05), and microvascular reperfusion (Pre: 2.29 ± 1.42 %/sec, Post: 3.71 ± 1.44 %/sec; p &lt; .05); however, there were no significant changes in baPWV or PWA compared to placebo. There were no significant interactions found for any of the blood biomarkers; however, there was a significant effect of time for oxLDL (p &lt; .05), and a trending toward significant effect of treatment for MDA (p = 0.055). There were significant improvements seen in both FDS (Pre: 7.08 ± 0.99, Post: 7.83 ± 1.27; p &lt; .05) and BDS (Pre: 4.83 ± 1.64, Post: 5.83 ± 1.27; p &lt; .05) following creatine, but no significant changes in TMT-A or TMT-B following either creatine or placebo. There were also no significant changes in 6MWT distance covered or isometric muscle strength; however, isometric muscle endurance, as indicated by total torque produced per set, improved for Set 1 (Pre: 2046.03 ± 823.78 Nm, Post: 2341.92 ± 896.02 Nm, p &lt; .001), Set 2 (Pre: 1753.3 ± 484.26 Nm, Post: 1892.78 ± 583.18 Nm, p &lt; .05), and Set 3 (Pre: 1642.35 ± 463.76 Nm, Post: 1745.7 ± 522.5 Nm, p &lt; .05) following creatine, but not placebo. Conclusion: Our findings indicate that 4 weeks of creatine supplementation, but not placebo, improves endothelial function and microvascular reactivity in older adults; however, there was no benefit for arterial stiffness. Creatine supplementation, in comparison to placebo, can also improve markers of short-term memory and isokinetic muscle endurance, but neither creatine or placebo improved visuospatial awareness or isokinetic muscle strength. However, findings indicate that these improvements were not mediated by any creatine-dependent antioxidant effects. Further research is warranted to determine the mechanism in which creatine elicits these reported vascular benefits in older adults.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Nutrition and Integrative Physiology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">October 22, 2021.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Creatine, Endothelial Function, Functional Capacity , Older Adults, Vascular Health</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Robert C. Hickner, Professor Directing Dissertation; Diana L. Williams, University Representative; Michael J. Ormsbee, Committee Member; Bradley S. Gordon, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85101679">
      <mods:topic>Physiology</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093451">
      <mods:topic>Nutrition</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:identifier type="IID">2021_Fall_Clarke_fsu_0071E_16819</mods:identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Nutrition, Food, and Exercise Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-05-23T16:09:53.352975-04:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
