<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Essays in Development Economics</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-7267-6091</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Rooney</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Timothy</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no95016942">
      <namePart type="family">Kantor</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Shawn Everett</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="viaf"
         authorityURI="http://viaf.org/viaf/"
         valueURI="http://viaf.org/viaf/300263260">
      <namePart type="family">Kitchens</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Carl T.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ecoleman">
      <namePart type="family">Coleman</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Eric A.</namePart>
      <namePart type="termsOfAddress">(Professor of Political Science)</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/lprodgers">
      <namePart type="family">Rodgers</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Luke P.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2014069337">
      <namePart type="family">Schmertmann</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Carl P.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Economics</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (171 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >This dissertation is composed of three papers, all using natural experiments from developing countries to examine critical issues in the lives of individuals in the developing world. In the first chapter, I combine data from a national high school entrance exam linked to individual tax records in Jamaica to examine the short and long-run impact of several key aspects of secondary education. The second chapter examines the impact of education on short and long-term academic outcomes in the country of Colombia. The final chapter examines the impact political connections play in the provision of public amenities in China. The first chapter, "High School Never Ends: Secondary School Attributes on Formal Sector Earnings" examines what features of secondary education lead to increased formal sector earnings. Five hundred million children are enrolled in secondary education in developing countries, over five times that in developed nations. However, little is known about what features of secondary education matter the most for short-term academic or long-term labor market outcomes in developing countries. In this paper, I combine data from a national high school entrance exam linked to individual tax records in Jamaica to examine several key aspects of secondary education. First, the eligibility cutoff in Jamaica allows me to employ a regression discontinuity design to estimate credible causal effects of access to a school with additional years of secondary education. Second, through a similar design, I am able to obtain a credible causal estimate of peer quality on short and long-term outcomes. Finally, using idiosyncratic variation in gender composition, I am able to analyze a school's gender composition on short and long-term outcomes. Access to a school with additional years of education increases formal sector earnings by 2,900 USD PPP per year from ages 22 to 31. However, I find no short or long-term effects from higher quality peers. Finally, I find large academic benefits from having a larger share of same-sex peers but no long-term labor market benefits. The second chapter, "What is the Impact of Educational Spending on Short and Long Term Outcomes? Evidence from Colombia" examines the impact of both lower and higher local education spending on short-term and long-term academic outcomes. The goal of the chapter is to answer the question, "does education spending impact student outcomes in developing countries?" I leverage two separate natural experiments to answer the question. First, I exploit the repeal of a program in Colombia that allocated a portion of oil royalties to per capita education spending in the municipalities where the oil was extracted. Using a rich administrative data set containing more than 1.2 million students, I estimate that a 25 percent drop in education spending results in a 0.05 standard deviation decline in language standardized test scores and a 0.04 standard deviation decline in math standardized test scores. I document that children impacted by the spending cuts are 2.5 percentage points less likely to graduate from a university (8 percent relative to the mean). Moreover, I find the most severe learning losses for women, low-income individuals, and those with less-educated parents. Second, I utilize the institutional feature before the reform linking local education expenditure to oil royalties. I then instrument education expenditure with international oil prices interacting with fixed oil production. I find short-term educational spending increases lead to a rise in the number of students finishing high school and improvements in language scores. The third chapter, "What is the impact of political connections on the provision of public amenities? Evidence from China's primary land markets," measures the effect of political connections on the provision of public amenities. My coauthor (Jing Feng) and I use over two million land transactions from China's primary land market during the period 2001 to 2019. Using a spatially matched sample, we find that connected firms are nearly two percentage points (30 percent) more likely to receive a kindergarten, elementary, or middle school in the immediate vicinity of their purchase. We find suggestive evidence of firms receiving more doctor's offices and hospitals. We then exploit the timing of an anti-corruption crackdown in China; we find the benefits of political connections disappear following the crackdown.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Economics in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">June 3, 2022.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Economics</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Shawn Kantor, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Carl Kitchens, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Eric Coleman, University Representative; Luke Rodgers, Committee Member; Carl Schmertmann, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040850">
      <topic>Economics</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Summer 2022_Rooney_fsu_0071E_17300</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Economics</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2023-01-27T10:52:08.836275-05:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
