<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <mods:titleInfo lang="eng">
      <mods:title>Mechanisms of Oxytocin Regulation of Sensory Processing and Sociality in Mice and Humans</mods:title>
   </mods:titleInfo>
   <mods:name type="personal" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Tabbaa</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Manal</mods:namePart>
      <mods:affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</mods:affiliation>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ehammock">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Hammock</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Elizabeth Anne Dunn</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/agunjan">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Gunjan</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Akash</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2005015125">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Patrick</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Christopher J.</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/zwang">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Wang</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Zuoxin</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="personal"
              authority="etd-naf"
              authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
              valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/gstanwood">
      <mods:namePart type="family">Stanwood</mods:namePart>
      <mods:namePart type="given">Gregg</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate"
              authority="naf"
              authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
              valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <mods:namePart>Florida State University</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <mods:namePart>Department of Psychology</mods:namePart>
      <mods:role>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</mods:roleTerm>
         <mods:roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</mods:roleTerm>
      </mods:role>
   </mods:name>
   <mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
   <mods:genre authority="rdacontent">text</mods:genre>
   <mods:genre authority="coar"
               authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
               valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</mods:genre>
   <mods:originInfo>
      <mods:place>
         <mods:placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</mods:placeTerm>
      </mods:place>
      <mods:dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2019</mods:dateIssued>
      <mods:publisher>Florida State University</mods:publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </mods:originInfo>
   <mods:language>
      <mods:languageTerm type="text">English</mods:languageTerm>
      <mods:languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</mods:languageTerm>
   </mods:language>
   <mods:physicalDescription>
      <mods:form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</mods:form>
      <mods:form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</mods:form>
      <mods:extent>1 online resource (167 pages)</mods:extent>
      <mods:digitalOrigin>born digital</mods:digitalOrigin>
      <mods:internetMediaType>application/pdf</mods:internetMediaType>
   </mods:physicalDescription>
   <mods:abstract>Social behaviors are foundational to our society and quality of life while social behavioral deficits are core symptoms in a variety of psychopathologies. Yet, despite the significance for human health, the neural mechanisms that regulate social behavior are incompletely characterized. Oxytocin (OXT) is a neuro-active hormone that has been well-studied over the last several decades and shown to regulate social behaviors. The OXT system interacts with early life environment and an individual's genotype to regulate social behaviors in a sexually dimorphic manner. Chapter 1 describes background information on the role of OXT in social behaviors. Thereafter, research on the developmental role of OXT is discussed. Chapter 1 ends with the proposal of a novel mechanism by which socially acquired OXT may regulate social behaviors. In chapters 2-5, experiments are described which aim to empirically test this central hypothesis. In chapter 2, a functional role for oxytocin receptors (OXTR) in the oronasal cavity were investigated in developing mice as a potential mechanism by which OXT can interact with early life sensory experience to regulate brain activity and behavior. OXTRs have recently been characterized in the periphery of developing mice that appear to be located on sensory apparatuses. We tested the effects of orally applied OXT, compared to saline, on a marker of neural activation, c-Fos, in sensory processing brain regions and the paraventricular nucleus of the hypothalamus (PVN). To test the effects of orally applied OXT on sensory-dependent brain activity, we also brushed the whiskers of mice after OXT or saline treatment in a separate experiment. Orally administered OXT, compared to saline, increased c-Fos in the PVN, and decreased c-Fos activity in sensory processing brain regions after whisker brushing. Additionally, orally applied OXT, compared to saline, with whisker brushing decreased Fos in the trigeminal motor nucleus as well as oral-motor behavior of females. Compared to saline, oral OXT with whisker brushing also increased males long distance locomotor behavior. These data support the possibility of a functional role for OXT acting on oronasal OXTR to modulate the brain and behavior in developing mice. In chapter 3, the idea of OXT exchange between conspecifics as a potential driver of social behaviors was tested by examining the preference of male and female mice towards OXT containing social stimuli. Male and female mice showed a preference to investigate same-sex mice that contained OXT versus OXT knock-out (KO) mice. Next, we tested if mice prefer OXT KO bedding containing OXT versus saline and found that males prefer female OXT KO bedding with OXT compared to saline. Finally, we tested the role of OXTR in sensory ganglia in the social preference of live mice by using transgenic mice breeding strategies to selectively knock out OXTR in sensory ganglia. We found that female mice lacking sensory OXTR (OXTRsensory KO) had reduced social investigation levels compared to their wild-type (OXTRsensory WT) litter mates. The role of OXTR in sensory ganglia in social behaviors was further tested in chapter 4 by examining sociability, preference for social novelty, and aggression in OXTRsensory WT and KO mice. OXTRsensory KO females had reduced approach behaviors during the sociability test, compared to OXTRsensory WT females. Altogether, data from chapters 2-4 indicate that environmentally acquired OXT can regulate brain activity and influence behaviors. In addition, mice preferred other mice that contain OXT over OXT KO mice, but not same-sex OXT KO bedding with OXT over saline. These data suggest that preference for an OXT containing live same-sex conspecific may be due to an interaction between OXT and social sensory signals rather than OXT alone. Lastly, these data indicate that OXTRs in sensory ganglia are an important regulator of social behaviors, particularly for females. Finally, in chapter 5, we aimed to explore the translational significance of these findings by examining if variation in the OXTR gene is associated with variation in social sensory processing in humans, with significance for trait meanness. We genotyped the common OXTR single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) rs1042778 and rs53576 in male and female participants that had brain event related potentials (ERP) recorded in response to viewing affective faces. We found that females homozygous for the OXTR SNP rs1042778 G allele had enhanced fear-specific brain responses compared to T allele carriers. Additionally, the rs53576 A allele was associated with higher ERP amplitudes to face stimuli, but not scrambled faces, compared to GG allele carriers. Further, OXTR SNPs rs1042778 and rs53576 interacted to predict trait meanness in females. These data implicate OXTR gene variability in the etiology of sensory processing variation in the brain as well as trait meanness. A summary of results as well as implications and suggestions for future research are discussed in chapter 6.</mods:abstract>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Psychology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Degree Awarded">Summer Semester 2019.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Date of Defense">July 10, 2019.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Keywords">Development, Oxytocin, oxytocin receptor single nucleotide polymorphism, Psychopathy, Sensory, Social beahvior</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</mods:note>
   <mods:note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Elizabeth A. D. Hammock, Professor Directing Dissertation; Akash Gunjan, University Representative; Christopher J. Patrick, Committee Member; Zuoxin Wang, Committee Member; Gregg Stanwood, Committee Member.</mods:note>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91006099">
      <mods:topic>Neurosciences</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <mods:subject authority="lcsh"
                 authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
                 valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014203">
      <mods:topic>Biology</mods:topic>
   </mods:subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2019_Summer_Tabbaa_fsu_0071E_15376</identifier>
   <mods:extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Psychology</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </mods:extension>
   <mods:recordInfo>
      <mods:recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2020-01-08T16:41:25.408-05:00</mods:recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </mods:recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
