<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>#Black Girls' (Opinions) Matter</title>
      <subTitle>Instagram in 2020, BLM, &amp; Racialized Differences in Girls' Perceptions of Police and SROs</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0009-0001-8150-001X</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Hernandez</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Isamar</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jrreynolds">
      <namePart type="family">Reynolds</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">John R.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016002095">
      <namePart type="family">Warren</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Patricia Y.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/sbuggs">
      <namePart type="family">Buggs</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Shantel</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dschrock">
      <namePart type="family">Schrock</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Douglas P.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Social Sciences and Public Policy</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Sociology</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (189 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >This dissertation investigates Black and White teenage girls' perceptions of police and how those perceptions are informed by two distinct sources: school resource officers (SROs) in high schools, and social media content related to police violence in the aftermath of George Floyd's killing by Minneapolis police officer Derek Chauvin. Existing sociological research on young peoples' perceptions of police has found that their attitudes vary according to race, gender, neighborhood, as well as vicarious and personal experiences with police. Vicarious police exposure refers to police interactions they observe in the neighborhood or hear of from friends and family members. This work finds that Black girls are more likely to have negative perceptions of police than White girls, in part due to their higher rate of negative vicarious experiences with police. Little is known, however, about how the recent proliferation of police brutality videos on social media affects teenage girls' perceptions of police or racial differences in those perceptions. Additionally, police perceptions research tends to focus on only one type of police by asking general survey questions like, "How good or bad a job is being done for the country as a whole by the police?" Most of the research on the social determinants of attitudes towards police does not include SROs. This dissertation research contributes to both the literature on perceptions of police and the literature on SROs by investigating teenage views and experiences with police in and out of schools and their experiences on social media in 2020. Data come from in-depth interviews with 30 girls (18 Black girls and 12 White girls) who attended a public high school in 2020 that had at least one SRO. Transcripts of interviews were analyzed through coding, memo-writing, sorting narrative blocks, and comparing life-event narratives. Unlike other studies that find more negative views of police among racialized minorities, the Black and White girls in this study rated police similarly. However, they arrived at these views by very different means. Black girls developed negative perceptions of police at much earlier ages than White girls and, according to their recollections, for different and more numerous [or "varied"] reasons compared to most White girls. White girls recalled their views of police as being vague or positive in childhood and early teen years, but most had developed quite negative views of police by their late teen years. White girls were more influenced by viewing videos of police brutality on social media in 2020 compared to Black girls, because Black girls all reported being familiar with police brutality prior to 2020. Black and White girls described different experiences on social media, including racially patterned emotional responses to watching videos of police brutality and racialized differences in motivations to post/not post about police brutality on social media in 2020. Black and White girls also shared similar views of SROs. Findings reveal that if students like an SRO, it does not diffuse to other police personnel because SROs are not seen as real police unless they engage in behaviors that many students see as inappropriate and criminalizing. Lastly, the majority of girls reported not feeling safe because of SRO presence and were not able to clearly describe SRO roles, with many girls reporting that SROs mostly sat around and made casual conversations with students and staff.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Sociology in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">November 17, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">Black girls, Black Lives Matter, Perceptions of police, School to Prison Pipeline, Social media, SROs</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">John Reynolds, Professor Directing Dissertation; Patricia Warren-Hightower, University Representative; Shantel Buggs, Committee Member; Douglas Schrock, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124200">
      <topic>Sociology</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041146">
      <topic>Educational sociology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Hernandez_fsu_0071E_18365</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Sociology</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-05-06T16:57:02.841686-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
