<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Human Chronotype Is Determineded by Period Oscillations</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <titleInfo  type="alternative" lang="eng">
      <title>Human Chronotype Is Determined by Period Oscillations</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-7966-6846</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Lee</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kwangjun</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/clee">
      <namePart type="family">Lee</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Choogon</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nb2012004932">
      <namePart type="family">Bass</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Hank W.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/jirianto">
      <namePart type="family">Irianto</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jerome</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/ywang33">
      <namePart type="family">Wang</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Yue Julia</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Medicine</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Biomedical Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (162 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Circadian clocks are endogenous timekeepers, but they need to be synchronized, or entrained, with external cues such as solar time to stay in harmony with the external environment. The circadian clocks give selective advantages to humans by adapting and optimizing our body system in this 24 h living environment. These intrinsic circadian clocks intertwine with nearly all aspects of human physiology. Thus, disruption of circadian clocks is closely associated with diverse disease conditions such as metabolic, cardiovascular, and sleep diseases. Sleeping is regulated by two internal mechanisms, homeostasis and circadian rhythms. These two internal biological systems are synchronized with environmental cues to optimize the timing and duration of sleep closely related to the quality of life. More than 70 million people suffer from sleep disorders in the U.S. The deprivation of sleep interferes not only with cognitive function but also with personal mood. Specifically, circadian rhythm sleep disorders (CRSD) are caused by alterations in the endogenous circadian time-keeping system itself or a misalignment between the endogenous circadian clock and external circumstances. The CRSD patients are primarily treated by pharmacological strategies by targeting melatonin, orexin, or core clock genes. Behavioral approaches such as light exposure adjustment and scheduled feeding have reported promising outcomes. However, understanding the molecular mechanism and genetics of human CRSDs is at a very early stage. We examined the molecular mechanism of PERIOD (PER), a key factor in the circadian clock, by generating PER1-Luc and PER2-Luc cell lines using the CRISPR-mediated HDR system. This allowed us to monitor PER1/2 oscillations in real-time. Next, we targeted several key amino acids in the PAS and CKBD domains and monitored PER oscillation to identify functional sequence motifs in Per1/2. Our study revealed that PAS dimerization-induced phosphorylation is crucial for PER oscillations, leading to its translocation into the nucleus. Additionally, we explored the diverse roles of functional sequence motifs in CKBD. Deletion of FASP in-frame mutant PER1 and PER2 shortened the period, while newly synthesized FASP mutants accelerated phosphorylation and underwent hyperphosphorylation and earlier degradation. Mutants in CK1BD-A or CK1BD-B exhibited defective phosphorylation, resulting in a lengthened period. In CK1BD-B mutant PER2, hPer1 knockout disrupted phosphorylation, rendering PER2 stable and arrhythmic. Furthermore, we created PER1 and PER2 PAS B mutant mice, with Per1W448E/W448E; Per2W419E/W419E mice displaying a human FASP chronotype. These findings significantly enhance our understanding of PER's functional role in sustaining circadian clocks and regular sleep-wake cycles. We demonstrated the invaluable utility of PER-Luc reporter cell lines as a resource for studying the circadian clock. Additionally, we introduced a method for generating mutant mice with disrupted circadian rhythms. Through our approach, it becomes feasible to create mouse models mimicking human sleep disorders effortlessly. While our focus was on investigating functional sequence motifs in PER, the experimental approach employed in this study could be extended to other clock genes for studying sleep disorders.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Biomedical Sciences in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">October 24, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Choogon Lee, Professor Directing Dissertation; Henry W. Bass, University Representative; Jerome Irianto, Committee Member; Yue Julia Wang, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086577">
      <topic>Molecular biology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Lee_fsu_0071E_18315</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-05-06T16:57:02.841686-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
