<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Investigating the Pattern and Process of Mate Choice in a Tropical Lekking Passerine Bird</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-4504-9807</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Rivers</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Pearl Rae</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/eduval">
      <namePart type="family">DuVal</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Emily H.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/eduval">
      <namePart type="family">Duval</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Emily</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/beerli">
      <namePart type="family">Beerli</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Peter</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/kahughes">
      <namePart type="family">Hughes</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kimberly A.</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1960-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/dlevitan">
      <namePart type="family">Levitan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Don R.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86861195">
      <namePart type="family">Travis</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Joseph</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1953-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Biological Science</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (145 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Variation in female mate choice affects the strength of sexual selection, and understanding this variation is important to understanding the evolution of elaborate secondary sexual characteristics. However, female mate choice is a multidimensional process, incorporating complex male traits, variable female states, and environmental contexts. Despite decades of research on female mate choice, we still do not fully understand how these factors interact to drive variation in female mate choice decisions. My dissertation research investigates the causes and consequences of variability in mate choice in a population of lance-tailed manakins (Chiroxiphia lanceolata), a species of small Neotropical passerine bird. I address three aims with lance-tailed manakins as a study system: (1) understanding the causes and consequences of multiple mating in a lek mating system; (2) investigating the role of chemical signaling in mating behavior; and (3) characterizing the genomic structure of an immune system gene complex, the major-histocompatibility complex (MHC). Finally, I take a comparative approach to (4) investigate the relationship between sexual selection and gene duplication in the MHC across the passerine bird radiation. To understand variation in female mate choice in lance-tailed manakins, I combined data from long-term monitoring of a study population with data from short-term controlled field experiments. First, I explored variation among females in the choice to mate with one or more males in a reproductive bout. I tested several hypotheses about multiple mating in lance-tailed manakins, a system where female choice is unconstrained by the need to form a pair-bond. I found that multiple paternity within a nest was best predicted by male experience: males that were subordinate "betas" or that had fewer years of experience as an alpha male were more likely to share paternity in nests. Females may choose to mate with multiple males when their choices are not optimal. Second, I investigated chemical signaling in the mating behavior of a highly polygynous bird by experimentally altering the chemical cues at lance-tailed manakin courtship sites. I found that male lance-tailed manakins detect and respond to changes in the chemical environment on display perches, but females do not. The information conveyed by chemical cues may be most salient for males in this system, unlike trends reported in other passerine birds where both males and females respond to olfactory cues. While mate choice research in highly polygynous lek mating systems typically focuses on the most elaborate and obvious traits, the results presented here indicate that chemical signaling may be important to mating behavior. Third, I characterize the genomic structure of an immune system gene complex, the MHC, in lance-tailed manakins. Gene duplication and polymorphism in the MHC make it a challenging genome region to characterize. Using a recent high-quality genome assembly for lance-tailed manakins, I assembled and annotated MHC genes using two methods. Manual annotation methods more reliably recovered MHC loci, compared to the available algorithm-based annotations. Additionally, preliminary analysis of signatures of selection across an alignment of MHC sequences from several manakin species identified codons under positive and negative selection. These results set the stage for future analyses of the evolutionary consequences of sexual selection for the MHC. In my final chapter, I take a comparative approach to investigate the evolutionary consequences of sexual selection for gene duplication in the MHC. Across passerine birds, the MHC region is characterized by extreme copy number variation. Using whole genome assemblies, I estimated MHC copy number tested hypotheses about drivers of MHC duplication across the passerine bird radiation. I did not find any support for the hypothesis that sexual selection could drive accelerated duplication in the MHC region. Genome assembly quality was the only consistent predictor of MHC copy number, highlighting the challenges of characterizing complex and highly duplicated genomic regions. By examining variation within mate choice bouts, in relation to neglected signaling modes, and across long temporal scales, this work improves understanding of the axes of variation in mate choice and their effects on the evolutionary outcomes of sexual selection.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the  in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">November 8, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Keywords">chemical communication, major histocompatibility complex, manakin, mate choice, polyandry, sexual selection</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Emily H. DuVal, Professor Directing Dissertation; Peter Beerli, University Representative; Kimberley A. Hughes, Committee Member; Don R. Levitan, Committee Member; Joseph Travis, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014203">
      <topic>Biology</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Rivers_fsu_0071E_18357</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Biological Science</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-05-06T16:57:02.841686-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
