<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo  lang="eng">
      <title>Rethinking Guilt Appeals in Environmental Messages</title>
      <subTitle>Testing the Effects of Empathy-Eliciting and Shame-Free Guilt Appeals on Behavioral Intentions</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name  type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-5388-2508</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Yan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Zhuxuan</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/larpan">
      <namePart type="family">Arpan</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Laura M.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016122444">
      <namePart type="family">Clayton</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Russell B.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor co-directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="etd-naf"
         authorityURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/"
         valueURI="https://authorities.lib.fsu.edu/etd-naf/yyang3">
      <namePart type="family">Yang</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Yanyun</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2015145017">
      <namePart type="family">Bailey</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Rachel L.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2007015761">
      <namePart type="family">Cortese</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Juliann</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name 
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Communication and Information</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name  type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>School of Communication</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource >text</typeOfResource>
   <genre  authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre 
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo >
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2023</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language >
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription >
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (168 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract >Guilt appeals are a widely used type of emotional appeals in social advocacy messages. However, studies have found inconsistent results regarding the effects of guilt intensity on influencing viewers' attitudes and behavioral intentions. Some found guilt-appeal intensity has a curvilinear relationship with post-message attitudinal and behavioral intention changes, whereas others found the relationship is linear or even neither linear nor curvilinear. Scholars pointed out that these inconsistencies might imply several crucial problems and challenges related to the manipulation of guilt in pervasive messages. The first problem might result from inadvertently eliciting reactive guilt instead of anticipated guilt via messages, which can lead to increased reactance among audiences. The second problem might result from inadvertently including shame-eliciting language in guilt appeal messages. Accordingly, it is recommended that messages designed to promote pro-environmental behavioral intentions should attempt to elicit anticipated guilt and avoid eliciting feelings of shame. This study tested effects of messages designed and found to elicit significantly more guilt than shame. Messages that elicit empathy might be effective in eliciting anticipated guilt and promoting behavioral changes. Additionally, narrative messages might elicit greater empathy than non-narrative messages. Therefore, using an online experiment that employed a 2 (message feature: narrative vs. non-narrative stories) x 4 (animal type: more similar vs. less similar to humans) between-subjects design, the first study investigated the causal association between empathy, anticipated guilt, and pro-environmental intentions. Results demonstrated that narrative stories featuring an animal or insect harmed by climate change elicited greater feelings of anger and sadness than viewing non-narrative stories, which led to heightened feelings of empathy among audience members. Results also showed that empathy was positively associated with anticipated guilt. Anticipated guilt was positively associated with pro-environmental behavioral intentions. Finally, anticipated guilt mediated the association between feelings of empathy and pro-environmental behavioral intentions. Scholars also suggested that the magnitude of the request in persuasive messages might influence viewers' self-efficacy, and self-efficacy might be a potential predictor in generating more effective responses to guilt appeals. Based on the proposition of the extended parallel process model (EPPM), including high self-efficacy instead of low self-efficacy components in emotional-appeal messages can promote recipients' behavioral intentions and help reduce defensive motivation such as psychological reactance to the messages. Reducing viewers' reactance to the message is important because psychological reactance theory (PRT) states that eliciting reactance among audiences can lead to ineffective persuasive messages. Using EPPM and PRT as theoretical foundations, the second study manipulated 2 levels of magnitude of the request (lower vs. higher) x 4 (animal type: more similar vs. less similar to humans) with a between-subjects design to examine the effects of shame-free guilt messages on self-efficacy, reactance to the messages, anticipated guilt, and pro-environmental intentions. Results demonstrated that viewing a shame-free guilt message with a lower magnitude of the request generated greater levels of self-efficacy compared to viewing the same message but with a higher magnitude of the request. Results from the mediation model found that self-efficacy was negatively associated with audiences' perceived threat to freedom. Perceived threat to freedom was positively associated with psychological reactance. Results revealed some evidence that psychological reactance was negatively associated with anticipated guilt. Finally, anticipated guilt was found to be positively associated with pro-environmental behavioral intentions. Results from both studies provided further insights into designing effective guilt appeals in climate change mitigation messages. The theoretical and practical implications are discussed, as well as suggestions for future research.</abstract>
   <note  displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the School of Communication in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Date of Defense">November 14, 2023.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note  displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Laura M. Arpan, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Russell B. Clayton, Professor Co-Directing Dissertation; Yanyun Yang, University Representative; Rachel L. Bailey, Committee Member; Juliann Cortese, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject 
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029027">
      <topic>Communication</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier  type="IID">Yan_fsu_0071E_18316</identifier>
   <extension >
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Communication</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo >
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2024-05-06T16:57:02.841686-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
