<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods:mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:flvc="info:flvc/manifest/v1"
           xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
           xmlns:etd="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/"
           xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd"
           version="3.6">
   <titleInfo lang="eng">
      <title>Cato in Cicero</title>
      <subTitle>Reading Roman History in the Late Republic</subTitle>
   </titleInfo>
   <name type="personal" authority="local">
      <nameIdentifier type="orcid" typeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-1855-8884</nameIdentifier>
      <namePart type="family">Carrara</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Eva</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">author</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2008131664">
      <namePart type="family">Clark</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jessica Homan</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1980-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">professor directing dissertation</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2015024182">
      <namePart type="family">Valisa</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Silvia</namePart>
      <namePart type="date">1971-</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">university representative</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2014022874">
      <namePart type="family">Luke</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Trevor S.</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="personal"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n96043208">
      <namePart type="family">Marincola</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">John</namePart>
      <affiliation>Theses and Dissertations</affiliation>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">committee member</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name
         type="corporate"
         authority="naf"
         authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/"
         valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80126238">
      <namePart>Florida State University</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="rda" type="text">degree granting institution</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>College of Arts and Sciences</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting college</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <name type="corporate" authority="local">
      <namePart>Department of Classics</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="local" type="text">degree granting department</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator" type="code">dgg</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="rdacontent">text</genre>
   <genre
          authority="coar"
          authorityURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type"
          valueURI="http://purl.org/coar/resource_type/c_db06">doctoral thesis</genre>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm type="text">Tallahassee, Florida</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateIssued encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">2022</dateIssued>
      <publisher>Florida State University</publisher>
      <issuance>monographic</issuance>
   </originInfo>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text">English</languageTerm>
      <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="rdamedia" type="RDA media terms">computer</form>
      <form authority="rdacarrier" type="RDA carrier terms">online resource</form>
      <extent>1 online resource (261 pages)</extent>
      <digitalOrigin>born digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
   </physicalDescription>
   <abstract>This dissertation explores Cicero's reception of Cato the Elder, particularly in respect to his fragmentary history of Rome and Italy, the Origines. I revisit commonly held conceptions about Cato's style, aims, and influences which I suggest are owed more to the transmission history of the fragments than to Cato's intent and authorial agency. I rely on philological and digital methodologies to catalog and analyze Cicero's engagement with Cato's writings, but I focus particularly on the dialogues written from the mid-50s BCE until the end of Cicero's life. In a departure from previous approaches to the research problem, which center authorial intent or remove Cato's fragments from their transmission context, I focus on reader responses to Cicero's Cato. I both analyze Cicero's citation of Cato as form of reading, and consider how readers in the Late Republic, many of whom were interested in Cato, would in turn read Cicero's Cato as compared to their external knowledge of Cato's life, career, and writings. I suggest that Cicero's representations of Cato would not have been accepted by all ancient readers, and that we should thus expect a variety of potential responses to Cicero's uses of Cato. I thus argue that readers, including Cicero's audience and Cicero himself, fundamentally shape Cato's image as a historian. Relying on the work of scholars who suggest that citations may provoke skeptical reader responses in fictional narratives, and also that we can understand the fictionalized interlocutors in Cicero's dialogues as an internal audience analogous to Cicero's readers, I analyze potential responses to Cicero's citations both of Cato and in Cato's voice. In this way, we can better understand the reception of Cato the Elder and the place of his Origines, the earliest Latin history, in the cultural and intellectual history of the Roman world. My dissertation contains five chapters, an introduction, and a conclusion. My first chapter provides an overview of Cicero's reference to and citation of Cato throughout his career. Building on this foundation, the second chapter explores how Cicero tends to name Cato in groups with other famous Romans and Greeks. I argue that this tendency reflects Cato's multivalence as a political, literary, and military figure, but also that it helps Cicero to designate Cato as the first orator and historian worth reading, a role he often takes on in Cicero's rhetorical works. In the next chapter, I offer a case study in how the goals of the citing authority alter our conceptions of Cato's most famous stylistic device, antonomasia, or the omission of personal names by focusing on Cato and dialogic verisimilitude in De re publica. In the last two chapters I discuss his De senectute, the dialogue delivered in Cato's voice and written late in Cicero's life. In the penultimate chapter I explore how Cicero cites and refers to Roman authors in the dialogue, especially to Ennius and to Cato himself. I suggest this citation practice makes the dialogic Cato plausible, not realistic, but that it also shapes our understanding of the historical Cato, whose Origines are cited in the dialogue. Finally, I end with a case study that argues that Cicero in this dialogue (and elsewhere) is ultimately responsible for the tradition that Cato's histories were influenced by Xenophon. Thus, I conclude that Cicero's citation of Cato has had not just profound influence on Cicero's literary career or Cato's legacy, but our very understanding of the origins of Roman literary history.</abstract>
   <note displayLabel="Submitted Note">A Dissertation submitted to the Department of Classics in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Date of Defense">March 2, 2022.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Keywords">Cato the Elder, Cicero, Latin literature, Roman history</note>
   <note displayLabel="Bibliography Note">Includes bibliographical references.</note>
   <note displayLabel="Advisory Committee">Jessica H. Clark, Professor Directing Dissertation; Silvia Valisa, University Representative; Trevor Luke, Committee Member; John Marincola, Committee Member.</note>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026454">
      <topic>Civilization, Greco-Roman</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject
            authority="lcsh"
            authorityURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/"
            valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061232">
      <topic>History, Ancient</topic>
   </subject>
   <identifier type="IID">2022_Carrara_fsu_0071E_16994</identifier>
   <extension>
      <etd:degree>
         <etd:name>Doctor of Philosophy</etd:name>
         <etd:level>Doctoral</etd:level>
         <etd:discipline>Classics</etd:discipline>
      </etd:degree>
      <flvc:flvc>
         <flvc:owningInstitution>FSU</flvc:owningInstitution>
         <flvc:submittingInstitution>FSU</flvc:submittingInstitution>
      </flvc:flvc>
   </extension>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2022-10-10T17:55:50.20129-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <descriptionStandard>rda</descriptionStandard>
   </recordInfo>
</mods:mods>
